<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mamillia The second part of the triumph of Pallas: wherein with perpetual fame the constancie of gentlewomen is canonised, and the vniust blasphemies of womens supposed ficklenesse (breathed out by diuerse iniurious persons) by manifest examples clearely infringed. By Robert Greene Maister of Arts, in Cambridge.</title>
            <title>Mamillia. Part 2</title>
            <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105831</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841557</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841557</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6147</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6147)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 344:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mamillia The second part of the triumph of Pallas: wherein with perpetual fame the constancie of gentlewomen is canonised, and the vniust blasphemies of womens supposed ficklenesse (breathed out by diuerse iniurious persons) by manifest examples clearely infringed. By Robert Greene Maister of Arts, in Cambridge.</title>
                  <title>Mamillia. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Th. C[reede] for William Posonbie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Part 2 of "Mamillia".</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-O⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MAMILLIA.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of the triumph of Pallas: WHEREIN WITH PERPETVAL fame the conſtancie of Gentlewomen is canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the vniuſt blaſphemies of womens ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed fickleneſſe (breathed out by diuerſe iniurious perſons) by manifeſt examples clearely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed.</p>
            <p>BY ROBERT GREENE MAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Arts, in Cambridge.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Th. C. for William Ponſonbie. 1593.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL, AND HIS ESPECIALL friends, Robert Lee and Roger Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington Eſquires, Robert Greene wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth health, wealth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Philoſopher Hermes (right worſhipfull) being demanded why continually he carried the ſtone Celonites about with him, anſwered, leaſt happily he might become vnthankefull. Meaning hereby that ingratitude is ſuch a loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vice in a liberall minde, and ſuch a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous offence ſo repugnant to nature, that the forfeit of ſuch a fault can be no leſſe than the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of death can afoord. For the nature of the ſtone is preſentlie to depriue him of lyfe which is infected with ingratitude. Which ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Hermes throughly conſidered, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to minde the innumerable benefits and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite good turns which I haue receiued at your worſhips hands, finding my abilitie far vnfit to
<pb facs="tcp:6147:3"/> requite ſuch curteſie, I was driuen into a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Dilemma, whether excuſing my ſelf by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abilitie I ſhould incurre the ſuſpition of ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, or in offering ſuch ſimple ſtuffe my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiencie could affoord, I ſhould be counted impudent. Staying thus in ſuſpence, I ſhaked off the ſhakles with calling to remembraunce the ſaying of a poore Painter in Sienna, who offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a ſimple picture to Charles the ſecond, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a preſent farre vnfit for ſuch a Potentate, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded how he durſt offer ſuch a baſe gift to ſo princely a perſonage. I feared not (quoth he) in that I knew he was our Emperour, knowing that it was kingly to accept of a gift though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo ſimple, and the ſigne of a worthie minde to thinke as well of the poore mans myte as of the riche mans treaſure. Artaxerxes receiued thankfully the handful of water offered to him by a poore peſant, Cyrus was preſented with a Pomgranat, and Iupiter himſelfe vouchſafed of the graine of wheate which the poore Piſmier offred to him for a new yeeres gift. Pricked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (right worſhipfull) with theſe examples, I was the more bold to preſent this vnworthie worke as a witneſſe of my vnfained good will and affection, aſſuming ſo vpon your worſhips
<pb facs="tcp:6147:3"/> wonted curteſies, as I aſſure my ſelfe you wil ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this my toy be it neuer ſuch a trifle, and vouchſafe of my good will though the gift bee neuer ſo ſimple: Promiſing that if hereafter ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my witte or skill ſhall be able to yeeld anie better fruite, I will offer it at your worſhippes ſhrine, that al the world may know you are the two Saints to whome in heart I owe moſt duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deuotion. Hoping in the mean time that you will accept more of my wil than of the worke, and of my meaning more than of the matter, I commit your worſhippes to the Almightie. From my Studie in Clarehall the vij. of Iulie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours Worſhips bounden to commaund, ROBERT GREENE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:4"/>
            <head>TO THE GENTLEMEN REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERS, HEALTH.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lexander the great (Gentlemen) commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a certaine Embroderer to worke him a moſt curious carpet, who in deed was ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull in his ſcience, as his worke amongſt meane men could carrie ſmall credite, ſtaied almoſt two yeares ere the worke was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and at laſt preſenting that vnperfect peece to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, Alexander ſmiled at the follie of the man which would enterpriſe ſuch a curious worke hauing ſo ſmall cunning: and being demanded of his Lordes, how he liked of the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, anſwered, that how bad ſo euer the work were, he muſt needs thinke it paſſing curious, becauſe it was ſo long in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. I feare Gentlemen to incurre the like forfeite with the Embroderer becauſe I haue committed the like offence, for both I ſhall be appeached of follie for preſuming ſo farre without skill, and condemned of ſloth, in that I haue bene breeding a Mouſe while others would haue brought forth an Elephant. And alſo I ſhall feare, if Gentlemen ſpeake well of my worke, that they ieſt with Alexander, and though they know my want of wit and lacke of skil to merit diſpraiſe, yet they will Ironice ſay all is well, becauſe it hath bene ſo long in penning. Well (Gentlemen) let Momus mocke, and Zoilus enuie, let Paraſites flatter, and Sicophants ſmile, yea, let the ſauage Satyre himſelfe, whoſe cynicall cenſure is more ſeuere than need, frowne at his, pleaſure, I hope honeſt Gentlemen will make account of Mamillia for her modeſt conſtancie, although ſhee hath not the Pumiſtone of learning to pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh her words with ſuperficiall eloquence: and ſo (Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen) ſhrowding her vnder your curteous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, hoping you will thinke well of my toy, I bid you fare-well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robert Greene.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:4"/>
            <head>RICHARD STAPLETON GEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TLEMAN, TO THE CVRTEOVS and Courtly Ladies of England.</head>
            <l>YE peereleſſe Dames of Pallas crue,</l>
            <l>and Brittaine Ladies all</l>
            <l>Addicted to Dianas traine</l>
            <l>your ſacred Nymphes I call,</l>
            <l>And veſtall virgins whoſe renoune</l>
            <l>ſhrynes vp your laſting name,</l>
            <l>Yea all the crue of womankinde,</l>
            <l>come heare your paſſing fame</l>
            <l>Diſplaide abroad with golden trumpe,</l>
            <l>which ſoundeth out ſo ſhrill,</l>
            <l>As that your praiſe in learned proſe,</l>
            <l>ſhall all Europa fill.</l>
            <l>See here with ſugred happie ſtyle,</l>
            <l>as in a perfect glaſſe,</l>
            <l>He figureth foorth how Venus troupe,</l>
            <l>in loyall faith ſurpaſſe</l>
            <l>The martiall broode of Mars his traine,</l>
            <l>decyphering to their face,</l>
            <l>That Pallas Ladies for their faith,</l>
            <l>do daunt them with diſgrace.</l>
            <l>With penne he paints your conſtancie,</l>
            <l>with penne he here diſplaies,</l>
            <l>Your faith, your troath, your loyaltie,</l>
            <l>and what imports your praiſe.</l>
            <l>And champion like he chalenge makes,</l>
            <l>with Ladie Pallas ſhield,</l>
            <l>To ſtand in armes againſt your foes</l>
            <l>in open camped field.</l>
            <l>He firſt cals out Euripides</l>
            <l>which your reproach aſſignde,</l>
            <l>And challenge makes to Mantuan,</l>
            <l>which ſo blaſphemde your kinde.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:5"/>
            <l>He iars likewiſe with Iuuenall,</l>
            <l>and mazeth Martiall quight,</l>
            <l>He doth profeſſe himſelfe a foe</l>
            <l>to all that owe you ſpight,</l>
            <l>And plainly proues by reaſons rule</l>
            <l>that euerie Authors clauſe,</l>
            <l>Which raſhly railes of womankinde,</l>
            <l>comes more of ſpight than cauſe.</l>
            <l>Sith then you peereleſſe Brittaine Dames,</l>
            <l>your Champion here in place</l>
            <l>Sounds forth your praiſe, defends your right,</l>
            <l>defies your foes in face:</l>
            <l>Repaie ſuch guerdon for his paine,</l>
            <l>as he deſerues to haue,</l>
            <l>I meane to ſhrowde Mamillia ſafe,</l>
            <l>tis that the Author craue,</l>
            <l>Your wits and wils, your tongue and talke,</l>
            <l>againſt all thoſe to vſe,</l>
            <l>Which ſhall like biting Momus broode</l>
            <l>his booke or him abuſe.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>RICHARD STAPLETON Gentleman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:5"/>
            <head>MAMILLIA. The Triumph of Pallas.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that <hi>Pharicles</hi> vnder the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Pilgrim was parted from the coaſtes of <hi>Italie,</hi> his ſecret and ſodaine departure cauſed all the citizens of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua</hi> to coniecture diuerſly of the cauſe of his iourney, but eſpecially it draue ſuch a doubt into the ſorrowfull heart of <hi>Mamillia,</hi> and ſtroke ſuch a dump into the muſing mind of her father <hi>Gonſaga,</hi> as it was hard to geſſe whether <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millia</hi> conceiued greater griefe for the vnkinde departure of her newe betrothed friend, or her father ſorrow, in that he gaue his conſent of ſo chary chaffre to ſo churliſh a chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: But whether it were, no doubt their care was grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than their well meaning mindes in any reſpect had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and by ſo much the more their ſorrowe increaſed, by how much the report of <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſuppoſed Pilgrimage was to his great reproch daily bruted abroad the Cittie: <hi>Gonſaga</hi> ſuppoſing <hi>Pharicles</hi> diſcredite conſidering the late contract, to bréede his daughters vtter infamie. For the Citizens gaue their verdit of the Gentlemans iourney as their fond affection had perſwaded them to thinke eyther
<pb facs="tcp:6147:6"/> well or ill of his perſon: his friendes ſuppoſing the beſt, ſaid, that he meant to ſpend his time in trauell vntill the next ſpring, wherein he meant to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummate the mariage his foes contrariwiſe coniecturing the worſt, ſaid that his pompous prodigalitie and rich attire, were the two bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtarres and carefull comets which did alwaies prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate ſome ſuch euent in tract of time ſhould happen, and that his ſumptuous expenſes had ſo rackt his reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, waſted his patrimonie, and brought his wealth to ſuch a lowe ebbe, as being fallen into an engliſh conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there remained no hope of his health, vnleſſe hée meant for debt to take his Innes in S. <hi>Patricks</hi> purgatory. But theſe dry blowes could draw no bloud, this wauering winde could ſhake no corne, neither coulde thoſe ſpightfull reportes of his proteſted foes anie iot mooue <hi>Mamillia</hi> to thinke euill of her profeſſed friend, &amp; by ſo much the leſſe, in that ſhe knew his reuenewes were able to maintaine a greater port than euer he caried in <hi>Padua.</hi> But as thus her panting heart wauered betwéene feare and hope, it was for certaintie told her and her father by a ſecret friend, that <hi>Pharicles</hi> was either married or betroathed to her couſin <hi>Publia,</hi> and the ſting of conſcience ſo combred his guiltie minde for committing this troathleſſe treacherie, that the ſhame of ſo hapleſſe a fact cauſed him to take this vnhappie iourney. This tale not fully finiſhed, <hi>Mamillia</hi> ſtoode vpon thornes caſt beyond the moone, and coniectured that which neither the tale did import, nor <hi>Pharicles</hi> himſelf imagine: but the leſſe ſhe was to be blamed, becauſe the more perfect loue, as the ſooner it is drencht with the miſling ſhowres of diſtruſt, and this direfull diſtruſt is ſuch a helliſh foe to the heauie minde, that it ſuffers the paſſionate perſon to take no reſt till manifeſt triall hath raced out this fooliſh frenzie, which <hi>Mamillia</hi> tried true: for combred thus with the clog of care, ſhe conueied her ſelfe couertly into her clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, where ſurcharged with the ſorrowe of this noyſome
<pb facs="tcp:6147:6"/> news, ſhe burſt forth into bitter teares and balefull terms to this effect.</p>
            <p>With what greater plague quoth ſhe, can either the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt gods or cruel deſtinies wreck their wrath and exreme rigour vppon any man, than whiles he ſafely flotes in the ſeas of proſperitie, to ouerwhelme him with the raging waues of aduerſitie, than amidſt the happie gale of good lucke, to daunt him with the ſtormes of diſaſter fortune, than to repay his bliſſe with bale, his ioy with annoy, and his happy felicitie with moſt hapleſſe &amp; diſtreſſed miſery? And yet there is no ſore ſo ill, but it ſéemes more ſower be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remedileſſe, than if it might be cured with cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, nor no wound ſo déepe, but it is thought more dangerous being incurable, than if either nature or art had prouided a ſalue to heale it, nor no miſfortune ſo great but it ſéemes more grieuous if there be left no hope that the preſent miſerie may in time be requited with proſperitie. For where the conſerue of hopes is wanting to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the diſtreſſed heart, there the coraſiue of deſpaire doth ſo fret aſunder the mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted mind as it maketh the perplexed perſon to pine in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall calamitie.</p>
            <p>All which alaſſe I ſée performed by proofe in mée moſt miſerable creature, which alate ſafely harboured in the hauen of happineſſe, and ſo foſtered vp by fortune as ſhée ſéemed to will that I did wiſh, am now ſo daunted with the deſpight of ſiniſter miſhap, and ſo croſſed with the rigorous repulſe of frowning fortune by the diſloyall dealing of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering <hi>Pharicles,</hi> as my weale to woe, my happineſſe to heauineſſe, yea all my ioy and delight is turned to extreme ſorrowe and deſpight: and by ſo much the more this my griefe is intollerable, by howe much the more there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth the hope of redreſſe. For alaſte, too late it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call the ſtone alreadie caſt, to beate the buſh the bird being flowen, to breake the bargaine the bandes being ſealed, and to reclaime affection where both lawe and loue hath
<pb facs="tcp:6147:7"/> fettered fancie with conſtraint, and as hard it is for thée poore <hi>Mamillia</hi> to hope to winne <hi>Pharicles</hi> againe to thy lure he being alreadie ſeaſed on his deſired pray, yea, ſo faſt tied to his tackling with thy coſin <hi>Publia,</hi> as no means but death can breake the bargaine, no the knot is ſo knit, that if <hi>Pharicles</hi> himſelfe did will what thou didſt wiſh, and would proue as lewd vnto her as light vnto thée, yet hée ſtriues againſt the ſtreame, and ſéekes to beare ſaile both againſt winde and weather: for as hée was aſſured vnto thée by promiſe, ſo he is betrothed vnto her by performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: as he was linked vnto thée (as thou ſuppoſedſt) in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect league of amitie, ſo he is (for certaine) coupled vnto her in the perfect lawe of matrimonie.</p>
            <p>O ingratefull and periured <hi>Pharicles,</hi> hath the conſtant ſtate of thy <hi>Mamillia</hi> procured thy inconſtancie? hath her troath made the trecherous? hath her loue made thée diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall? wilt thou diſgreſſe ſo farre from nature, and reſiſt the lawe of nurture, as to repay faith with flatterie, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere affection with fained fancie, and good will with hate? haſt thou no more care of thy credite but to cracke it with inconſtancie? nor no more regard to thy ſolemne othe than to foile it with periurie? Why was nature ſo fond vnder ſo fine a ſhell to hide ſo rotten a kernell, vnder ſuch golden fethers ſuch ranke fleſhe, vnder the ſhape of a Lambe the ſubſtaunce of a Tigre, vnder ſo ſweete a face ſo ſower a minde, to match ſo currſh conditions vnder ſo courteous a countenance, ſo perfect a perſon with ſuch imperfect quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſo fine a feature with ſuch filthy flatterie?</p>
            <p>Why but <hi>Mamillia</hi> can theſe ſorrowfull exclamations cure thy maladie, or can the rubbing of thy wound procure thine eaſe? nay rather remember the olde prouerbe, not ſo common as true, paſt cure, paſt care, without remedie without remembrance? Wilt thou proue ſo fond to ſet that at thy heart which <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſets at his héele, to wéep for him which wailes not for thée: to ſorrow for his amitie
<pb facs="tcp:6147:7"/> which laughes at thy miſerie? No no, caſt away care, let the remembraunce of his treacherie mittigate the fire of thy fancie, lyke not where thou art not loued, nor loue not where thou findes ſuch inconſtancie: as hée hath made a chaunge, ſo make thou a new choice, for ſince he hath falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his faith without cauſe, thou art frée from thy promiſe without care: yea as he hath laide his loue vpon <hi>Publia,</hi> ſo laie thou thy liking vpon ſome other gentleman which both for his perſon and parentage may deſerue as well to be loued as hée to be liked, and in ſo doing ſhalt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thy parents, procure thine owne eaſe, and pay <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> his debt in the ſame coine.</p>
            <p>Why <hi>Mamillia</hi> art thou mad, or is fancie turned into frenzie? Shal the cowardize of the Kiſtrel make the Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con fearefull? Shall the dread of the Lambe make the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a daſtard? Shall the leaudneſſe of <hi>Pharicles</hi> procure thy lightneſſe, or his inconſtancie make thée wauering? His new deſire in choice make thée delight in chaunge? Shall I ſay his fault make thée offend, his want of vertue force thée yéeld to vanitie? If hée by committing periurie be a diſcredite vnto men, wilt thou by falſifying thy promiſe be an vtter infamie to women? No the Gods forbid. For ſince <hi>Pharicles</hi> firſt wonne me, either he himſelfe or none ſhall weare me, and although he hath crackt his credit, violated his oath-falſified his faith, and broke his proteſted promiſe, yet his inconſtancie ſhall neuer make mée to wauer, nor his fléeting fancie ſhall not diminiſh mine affection. But in deſpight both of him and fortune, I will be his in duſt &amp; aſhes. Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen that vnfaithfull <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſhall be the ſaint at whoſe ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e I meane to doo my deuotion vntil my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe heart through extreame ſorrow receiue the ſtroke of vntimely death, which if it come not ſpéedelie, theſe hands inforced by diſpaire, by ſome ſiniſter meanes ſhall ende my miſerie, and with that ſuch ſcalding teares diſtilled from her chriſtall eyes, as they were ſufficient witneſſes of her
<pb facs="tcp:6147:8"/> inſupportable ſorrow.</p>
            <p>Where, by the way, Gentlemen, if fond affection be not preiudiciall vnto your iudgement, wée are by conſcience conſtrained to condemne thoſe vnſéemly <hi>Satyres</hi> and vaine inuectiues, wherein with taunting tearmes and cutting quippes diuerſe iniurious perſons moſt vniuſtlie accuſe Gentlewomen of inconſtancy, they themſelues being ſuch coloured Camelions, as their fondneſſe is ſo manifeſt, that although like <hi>Aeſops</hi> aſſe they clad themſelues in a Lions ſkinne, yet their eares wil bewray what they be: yea they accuſe women of wauering when as they themſelues are ſuch weathercocks as euerie wind can turne their tippets, and euerie new face make them haue a new fancy, diſprai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing others as guiltie of that crime wherewith they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are moſt infected, moſt vniuſtly ſtraining at a gnat, and letting paſſe an elephant, eſpying one dram of droſſe, and not ſéeing a whole tunne of ore, ſo iniuriouſly deſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vppon ſome one dame which for her wauering minde perhaps deſerueth diſpraiſe, and not attributing due honor to ſo manie thouſand Ladies which merite to be canonized as Saintes for their incomparable conſtancie. But now their cauilling is ſo common, and their cauſeleſſe condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning come to ſuch a cuſtome, as Gentlewomen thinke to bee diſpraiſed of a vaine iangler rather bringeth commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation than inferreth diſcredite, eſtéeming their wordes as winde and their talke as tales: yea their deſpightfull ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches carrie ſo litle credite, as euerie man thinkes they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come of courſe than of cauſe, &amp; that their cynicall cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures procéed rather of ſelfe will than either of right or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Well Gentlemen, if I might without offence inferre compariſon, we ſhould plainly perceiue that for inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie men are farre more worthie to be condemned than wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be accuſed. For if we reade the Romane records or Grecian hiſtories, either fained fables or true tales, yet we ſhall neuer finde anie man ſo faithfull which hath ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed
<pb facs="tcp:6147:8"/> women in conſtancie. Their onelie paragon wherof they haue to boaſt is poore <hi>Piramus,</hi> which killed himſelfe for <hi>Thisbe,</hi> but to giue them a ſop of a more ſharper ſauce, let them tel me if euer any of their braueſt champio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to die for his wife as <hi>Admeta</hi> did for her huſband <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt?</hi> What man euer ſwallowed burning coales as <hi>Portia</hi> did for <hi>Cato?</hi> Who ſo affectioned to his wife as <hi>Cornelia</hi> was to <hi>Gracchus?</hi> Who euer ſo ſorowed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſfortune of his Lady as <hi>Iulia</hi> did for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſhap of her beſt beloued <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey?</hi> Did euer any adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſuch deſperat dangers to inioy his loue as <hi>Hipſicratea</hi> did for her huſbande <hi>Mithridates?</hi> What ſhuld I ſpeak of <hi>Tercia, Aemillia, Turia, Lentula, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelope,</hi> or this our conſtant <hi>Mamillia</hi> with innumerable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whoſe chaſtitie faith &amp; conſtancy toward their louers could not euen by the dint of death be chaunged? But leaſt for ſaying my fancie ſome accuſe me of flatterie, againe to <hi>Mamillia,</hi> who thus plunged in perplexity, &amp; driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the dangerous gulf of diſtruſt, ouercharged afreſh with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of <hi>Pharicles</hi> diſcurteſie, had burſt foorth a new into her woonted teares, had not her father preuented her by comming into the cloſet, where finding her ſo bedewed with teares, yea in ſuch diſtreſſe as a woman halfe in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, blamed her follie in this effect.</p>
            <p>Daughter, quoth hée, as it is a ſigne of a careleſſe minde not to be moued with miſhap, ſo it is a token of follie to be careful without cauſe, and to be gréeued for that which if it were iuſtly weied offreth at al no occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſorow: in which you commit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fault, &amp; deſerue the blame, for your care is too great, &amp; the cauſe none at all. The ſodain departure of your friend <hi>Pharicles</hi> (as I geſſe) brought you into this dumpe, which in my fancie could bréed no doubt: for although ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie and vncertaine rumors be ſpredde of his iourney, and diuerſe men deſcant diuerſlie of his departure, as fonde affection leadeth them, his friendes ſuppoſing the beſt excuſe his faulte, his foes miſtruſting the worſt accuſe him
<pb facs="tcp:6147:9"/> of follie, and yet they both ayme at the marke as the blinde man ſhootes at the crowe, <hi>Pharicles</hi> perhaps hauing ſo iuſt occaſion of his iourney (as his ſpéedie and happie returne ſhall make manifeſt) that his friends by hoping well ſhall merite praiſe, and his foes by iudging ill diſcredite. But perhaps the late report how either he was married or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troathed to your couſin <hi>Publia</hi> is the fretting canker which ſo combers your diſquiet conſcience, which tale in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as it was laſt ſet abroach, ſo it deſerueth leaſt truſt, and eſpecially on your behalf, ſince neither you haue heard him counted for inconſtant, nor you your ſelfe haue tryed him wauering. Wil you then be ſo light as to call his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite in ſuſpence which neuer gaue you occaſion of ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reward him with diſtruſt which neuer gaue you occaſion to doubt? No <hi>Mamillia,</hi> beware of ſuch fondneſſe, leaſt <hi>Pharicles</hi> hearing of your follie performe that in déed whereof you ſuſpect him without deſert. But ſuppoſe the worſt, he hath falſified his faith, hath crackt his credit, and like a troathleſſe <hi>Theſeus</hi> proued himſelfe a traitor: what then? Shall this his diſſembling driue thée into diſpaire? or his péeuiſh inconſtancie be thy perpetuall care? No, but rather <hi>Mamillia</hi> as he hath ſtained his faith, ſo ſtraine thou thy affection, as hée hath fainted in performance, ſo faile thou in promiſe, yea learn to loath him for his vice as thou louedſt him for his vertue, moderate thine affection, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw thy good will, and if thou hap to finde him halting, race him quite out of thy remembrance, and in ſo doing it ſhall both pleaſe me and eaſe thée, in the meane time ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the beſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mamillia</hi> perceiuing her fathers friendly affection by this his carefull counſel, and ſeeing his talke tended to her weale, was driuen into a doubtful <hi>dilemma</hi> what anſwere to frame: for if ſhe ſhould ſéeme ſo light of loue as to haue her heart at libertie both to like and loath as fickle fancie ledde her, all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world might condemne her of inconſtancie:
<pb facs="tcp:6147:9"/> againe if ſhée did not whollie agrée to her fathers iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he might thinke ſhée did contemne his counſell and her owne commoditie: to auoid therfore the blame of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and the blemiſh of diſcurteſie, ſhe framed him an anſwere on this wiſe.</p>
            <p>Sir, quoth ſhe, it is farre more eaſie for the Phiſition to giue counſell, than for the patient to put it in practiſe, and a thing of leſſe charge to finde a fault than to amend it: yea it were an eaſie matter to be prickt with ſorrow if the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed man might aſſoone bée cured as counſelled: but to remoue care or ceaſe from griefe is lightly perſwaded, but verie hardly performed, which by experience I finde in my ſelfe. For I both know your counſell to be good, and alſo I moſt heartily deſire to follow it, yet the griefe of <hi>Pharicles</hi> ingratitude hath taken ſuch déepe roote in my hapleſſe hart that neither counſaile nor conſtraint can race it out of my remembrance. And whereas ſir you perſwade me to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate mine affection, to withdraw my good wil from <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles,</hi> and to quench the fire of fancie with the deſpightfull droppes of hatred, I coniecture they be rather wordes of courſe to trie my conſtancie, than ſpoken in good earneſt to exhort mée to ſuch trecherie. For you know I choſe <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles</hi> for my mate, and you were content with the match, I fixed mine affection not to continue with him a yeare in dalliance, but to remaine with him all my life in marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, wherin no fond and vncertaine liking but ſincere and perpetuall loue is to be required: for to marrie without the force of fancie, is to become a ſeruile ſlaue to ſorrowe. There muſt bee a knitting of hearts before a ſtriking of hands, and a conſtraint of the minde before a conſent with the mouth, or elſe whatſoeuer the flower is, the fruite ſhall be repentaunce. Which things conſidered, I am not to be blamed, though I cannot leaue to loue at mine owne pleaſure, nor to be condemned though I am ſo ouerchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with ſorrow, ſith an other ſhall enioy him vpon whom
<pb facs="tcp:6147:10"/> my heart is wholie fixed.</p>
            <p>Tuſh <hi>Mamillia</hi> quoth <hi>Gonzaga</hi> interrupting her talke, I ſay as I ſaid before, that it is good to be carefull if there were any cauſe, but ſince no occaſion of ſorrow is offered, why ſhould you be ouergrowne with griefe? <hi>Pharicles</hi> hath taken a ſodaine and vncertaine iourney, what then? Wilt thou condemne him of follie before thou heare the vrgent cauſe of his ſpéedie departure? No, but wil you ſay the caſe is too manifeſt, and ſo inferre the rumor of his late ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed marriage, which I deny as a moſt infamous ſlaunder raiſed vpon ſo honeſt a Gentleman. And for better proofe thereof come with me, for I will go to my brother <hi>Goſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> that there your couſin <hi>Publia</hi> may diſſolue your doubt and confirme my hope, and ſo without any delaie they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to heare the caſe decided.</p>
            <p>Where I cannot paſſe ouer without ſome ſpéech, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telwomen, the incomparable conſtancie of <hi>Mamillia,</hi> which was ſo ſurelie defenced with the rampier of vertue, as all the fierce aſſaults of fortune could nowhit preuaile as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to ſuch profeſſed amitie, no the fained treacherie of ſo troathleſſe a traitour as <hi>Pharicles,</hi> did rather ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then than aſtoniſh her infallible friendſhip: the counſell of her father, the feare of his diſpleaſure, the hope of profit, or the dread of future daunger, were of ſo litle force to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh her affection, as it rather remained by thoſe contrarie blaſtes of fortune farre more inflamed than anie whit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>And yet inferre <hi>Mamillia</hi> and a thouſand other Ladies (who for their loyaltie deſerue as good report and as great renowne) as perfect preſidentes againſt thoſe vniuſt prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, which ſéeke like ſicophants to diſcredit womens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, and forſooth they muſt ſtand for no paiment: but alaſſe, if they ſpie one ſilly dame to halt or tread her ſhoe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrie, her fault is as much as though all did offend, for they will exclaime againſt all in general, as though none were
<pb facs="tcp:6147:10"/> to bee founde guiltleſſe. But it is no maruell if the ſillie Lambe be vniuſtly accuſed where the Woolfe comes in as plaintife.</p>
            <p>Well, <hi>Gonzaga</hi> being come to the houſe of his brother in lawe <hi>Goſtyno,</hi> he found the olde gentleman ſo far ſpent with his long and lingring ſicknes, that he was very loth with ſuch friuolous queſtions to trouble his patience, yet after ſalutations and many wordes paſſed betwéene them, wherin the one deciphred his paines, and the other lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his caſe, the ſicke man vttering his griefe with ſighes, and the other his ſorrow with teares, <hi>Gonzaga</hi> like a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Foxe found occaſion to bring the matter in queſtion ſo ſubtilly, as <hi>Goſtyno</hi> either not at all, or elſe verie hardlie ſpied the fetch, framing his talke to this or ſuch like effect.</p>
            <p>Although <hi>Plato</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bookes of his common wealth doth counſell the <hi>Athenians</hi> not to viſit any of their friendes in time of aduerſitie, except they could by ſome meanes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe their miſerie, becauſe that comfort (ſaith hée) is cold and vnſauourie which commeth not bewrapt with ſome kind of remedy: yet as one condemning <hi>Platoes</hi> iudgement in this caſe, I am come to comfort you as a friend, but not to cure you as a Phiſition, leſt I might be thought to hant my friend in his health, and hate him in his ſicknes, which either belongeth to a foole or a flatterer. But if I were as cunning a Phiſition as a conſtant friend, and had as great ſkill to cure as to counſell, yet if I take not my markes amiſſe, I ſhoulde more profite you with good aduiſe than with anie potions were they neuer ſo ſoueraigne. For your daungerous diſeaſe, which moſt importeth death, is age, and your ſoreſt ſickneſſe is many yéeres, I ſpeake <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyno</hi> the more boldly, ſith I heare you are more willing to die than deſirous to liue, &amp; that you ſéek more the welth of your ſoule than the health of your bodie. In déed <hi>Appol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius Tianeus</hi> reporteth, that the <hi>Gymnoſophiſts</hi> made a lawe, that no man hauing paſſed thréeſcore yeares ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:6147:11"/> buy any land before he made himſelfe a graue, nor build a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny houſe before he had prouided for himſelfe a Sepulchre: becauſe in age wée ought to make more readineſſe to die than prouiſions to liue, for the ſtéele being ſpent, the knife cannot cut, the oyle conſumed the lampe goeth out, the Sunne being ſet the day cannot tarry, the flower being fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len there is no hope of fruite, and old age being once come life cannot be laſting. You knowing therefore that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo certaine in old age as euerie day to looke to die, hauing ſhewed your ſelf both to be wiſe and warie, in that hauing but one only daughter, you both ſée her brought vp in your life, and that which is more, moſt worſhipfully married before your death, yea and to ſuch a mate as ſhée cannot but loue for his perſon, and you like for his paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and patrimonie, I meane our friend &amp; neighbor <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles,</hi> whoſe wit, wealth, and exquiſite perfection both of minde and bodie, hath made all <hi>Padua</hi> aſtoniſhed.</p>
            <p>Staie there quoth <hi>Goſtyno,</hi> &amp; thinke not much though I interrupt your talk ſo raſhly, for as I receiue both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conſolation by your good aduiſe and counſaile, ſo your ſtrange news hath driuen me into a quandary, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhould take your wordes in earneſt or ieſt: for I am ſure my daughter <hi>Publia</hi> is as far from a huſband as I am from a wife, or elſe I am greatly beguiled. And with that he called <hi>Publia</hi> which ſtoode at the window talking with her couſin <hi>Mamillia,</hi> and began to ſift her on this wiſe.</p>
            <p>If the newes daughter be true that your vncle <hi>Gonzaga</hi> hath told me, I may iuſtly be accuſed of folly, &amp; you be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of diſobedience: for in that I alwaies left you the raines of libertie being yong, to vſe your wil as a law, and to leade your life after your owne luſt, I may be counted a foole, and in that you haue abuſed this law of libertie, wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your ſelf to your own wil &amp; deſpiſing my fatherly care &amp; counſel as of none effect, you may be thought a diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t child. Why? was my nature euer ſo ſtrange, or your nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:6147:11"/> ſo ſtraight, was I ſo vnwilling that you ſhuld match, or ſo wilfull to kéepe you from marriage, as you ſhoulde chooſe without my aduiſe, yea, and that which is more, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie without my conſent? Well, I knowe I haue alwayes had ſuch a care to pleaſure you as a father, and you ſuch a feare to diſpleaſe me as a daughter, that I both thinke the newes vntrue, and thée vnworthy of ſuch a report. But if the caſe be ſo, thou art not the firſt, nor ſhalt be the laſt which haue ſlipt awrie in this point: yet ſince thou haſt heere ſuch a care of thy choice as to looke before thou leape, and to loue ſuch a one as is to be liked for his liuing, both for his perſon and vertue, thou deſerueſt the leſſe to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and I haue the leſſe cauſe to be offended: to put mée therefore out of doubt, and to ſatiſfie thine vnckle <hi>Gonza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga,</hi> I charge thée by the law of dutie to tell me what hath paſſed betwéene thée and <hi>Pharicles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir quoth ſhe, as I haue alwaies found you to haue had a fatherly care to prouide for my welfare, ſo I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes counted it religion to requite that fatherly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the dutie and obedience of a childe, leaſt happily I might ſéeme to be more void of nature than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brute beaſts which want nurture. The yoong lamb by méere inſtinct of Nature obeieth the bleating of the old ſhéepe: The ſucking fawne followeth the ſteps of the Doe: The Cignets dare not reſiſt the call of the old Swan: the yong Tigre (though neuer ſo wild) runneth at the beck of the old Tygreſſe: and ſhould I then, ſyr, be ſo voide of grace, as to be more lewd than the yong lambe, more voide of Nature than the ſillie Fawne, more ſenſeleſſe than the yong Cignets, and more fierce than the cruell Tygres: No no ſir: But when I ſo farre forget my ſelfe, as to paſſe theſe vnreaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in careleſſe diſobedience, then the Gods requite ſo lothſome a fact with moſt helliſh miſery. Although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce of the common people be a great verdit to confirme a thing in queſtion, yet that which is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many is not always
<pb facs="tcp:6147:12"/> true, much leſſe the rumour which is raiſed by ſome one tatling perſon, doth followe by conſequence as a thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily to be beléeued. And therefore mine vncle <hi>Gonza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga</hi> did verie ill in giuing credite to ſuch a flying tale, and did more ouerſhoote himſelfe in blowing it into your eares, vntill by further triall he had ſearched out the trueth of the matter.</p>
            <p>In déede ſir I confeſſe, that <hi>Pharicles</hi> hath ſhewed mée ſome curteſie, and I haue not altogither requited him with curioſitie, he hath made ſome ſhew of loue, and I haue not wholie ſéemed to miſlike, leaſt in louing lightly I might ſéeme laſciuious, and in contemning churliſhly I might be iudged very curious: but for to contract I neuer meant without your conſent, nor neuer intended to ſet on the ſeales before you had ſtrooke vp the bargaine. And for the confirmation of theſe my wordes, and the better ſatiſfying of mine vnckle <hi>Gonzaga,</hi> ſée héere the letters which haue paſſed betwixt me and <hi>Pharicles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goſtyno</hi> perceiuing by the tenure of theſe letters, that this tale which was told of his daughter was wholy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out troth, woulde verie gladly haue knowen of <hi>Gonzaga</hi> who was the authour of ſuch a report, thinking himſelfe ill dealt withal to haue ſo cauſeleſſe a ſlaunder raiſed vpon his daughter: but <hi>Gonzaga</hi> not willing to bring the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any ſurther in queſtion, made him this anſwere.</p>
            <p>Brother <hi>Goſtyno</hi> quoth he, I know it is ill putting the hand betwéen the barke and the trée, &amp; great folly to meddle in other mens matters, neither was it my minde when I told you this tale, to ſowe any diſſention betwéene your daughter <hi>Publia</hi> and you, but I came to warne her as a friend, and counſell her as a kinſman, that ſhe might take héede of the traine, leaſt ſhe were taken in the trap, that ſhe might not ſtrike at the ſtale leaſt ſhe were canuaſed in the nettes, that ſhe might not venter no father into the foord than ſhe might eaſily retire without danger, I meane
<pb facs="tcp:6147:12"/> that ſhe ſhoulde not lay her loue no ſurer vppon <hi>Pharicles,</hi> but that ſhe might plucke it off at her owne pleaſure, for <hi>Pharicles</hi> is betroathed, and contracted long ſince to my daughter <hi>Mamillia,</hi> ſo that there remaineth nothing but that at his returne home they conſummate the marriage. To cauſe therefore your daughter to take héed of ſuch cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging copeſmates was the cauſe of my comming, leaſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly ſhée might buy repentance too deare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goſtyno</hi> ſéeing the danger whereinto his daughter had fallen, if <hi>Gonzaga</hi> had not preuented it, gaue him heartie thankes for his friendly counſell, and counted both himſelf and his daughter greatly bound vnto him for preuenting ſo ſecret a miſchiefe, being to exclaime againſt the péeuiſh periurie and trothleſſe trecherie of <hi>Pharicles,</hi> had not <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaga</hi> broken off the talke with taking his leaue of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>Mamillia</hi> giuing the <hi>A dio</hi> to her cooſin <hi>Publia,</hi> departed leauing <hi>Goſtyno</hi> and his daughter wholly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled, but not halfe comforted, becauſe they could not ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly diſgeſt the great abuſe of <hi>Pharacles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But poore <hi>Mamillia</hi> who before was drowned in dread, doth now ſwimme in hope, before (as ſhée thought) croſſed with calamitie, but now crowned with proſperitie, alate drenched in the dregs of diſtruſt, and now ſafely ſetled in aſſurance, before ſhe feared the worſt, and now ſhe hoped the beſt, at her comming nothing but woe woe, at her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne all was ioy, her woe to weale, her bale to bliſſe, her deſpight was turned to pleaſure and delight. For now ſhe hoped that although <hi>Pharicles</hi> had ſowen wilde Oates hée ſhould reape good graine, that he had not runne ſo farre but he might eaſily return, that bought wit was beſt, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> being throughly beaten with his owne rod, he would in time learne to be wiſe, and that whereas before hée was trothleſſe now he woulde be truſtie, as he was falſe ſo hée would be faithful: ſhe thus perſwading her ſelfe of the beſt was as merry as before ſhe was ſorie. But contrariwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:6147:13"/> 
               <hi>Publia</hi> being before ſecure was now croſſed with care, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in happineſſe now wholly in heauineſſe, alate in ioy, now in ſorrow and annoy, ſo that getting her ſelfe ſecretlie into her chamber ſhe fell into theſe pittifull plaints.</p>
            <p>Alaſſe quoth ſhe, poore ſoule, it is too late to defend the walles when the Citie is ouerrunne, to ſound the retreate when the battell is fought, to applie the ſalue when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſore is incurable, and to ſéeke to comfort where counſell com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth too late, and to reclaime affection fancie being alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die fixed. Thou ſpeakeſt poore <hi>Publia</hi> by experience, for the counſell thine vncle <hi>Gonzaga,</hi> gaue thée was not a confect to heale thy ſorrow, but a coraſiue to renew thy griefe. And why? becauſe to ſéeke to cure an incurable diſeaſe is to dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the patients paines. Mine vncle <hi>Gonzaga</hi> did wiſely warne me to beware of the traine, and alas I was before taken in the trap, he wiſht me to beware of liking and I was long before in loue, he had me take héede for wading too far, and I was before ouer my ſhoes. Why but fond foole thou haſt not gone ſo farre but thou mayſt retire, thou art not ſo faſt in the nettes but thou mayſt returne, thy loue is not ſo ſurely lodged, but thou mayſt pull off thy liking, thou haſt made no contract but thou mayſt reclaime, nor giuen no conſent but thou mayſt recall, yea, &amp; without clog to thy conſcience or crack to thy credit. For why, he hath ſworne to performe that which he could not iuſtly promiſe, he hath offered thée his faith, whereas before another had his frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the greateſt ſubſtance of his loue was but a meare ſhadowe of luſt, then <hi>Publia</hi> caſt him off which ſo did ſcoffe thée, and deteſt him which ſo déepely diſſembled: yea, for what fondneſſe were it for thée to like him which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther womans loue, to make a choice of him whom another already hath choſen, to fixe thy fancie vpon <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſince <hi>Mamillia</hi> ſhall enioy him. Alaſſe I know all this, but what then? the perſon of <hi>Pharicles,</hi> his beautie, bountie, and rare qualities are ſo ſurely ſhryned in my breaſt, as they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:6147:13"/> be raced out with obliuion: let <hi>Mamillia</hi> enioy him as her huſband (yea, and I pray the Gods ſend them long and happie daies togither) yet I will both loue him and like him in a chaſt minde for euer. What though he were falſe, ſhall I be faithleſſe? though he had no troth, ſhall I be tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous? ſhall his ſleeting make me fickle, or his inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie make me without conſcience? No, no, I haue once giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my heart and I meane not to pull backe my hand, I haue once loued him and I meane neuer to like any other: but here before the Gods I vowe my ſelfe a veſtall virgin till death ſhall end my ſorrow.</p>
            <p>And indéed ſhée promiſed nothing but ſhe did performe, for not long after <hi>Goſtyno</hi> died leauing her ſole heire to al his poſſeſſions. And although ſhée was dayly ſued vnto by diuerſe braue and gallant gentlemen, yet ſhe refuſed them all, and the better to auoyd the reſort of ſuters which dayly frequented her houſe, ſhe let all her lands to leaſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred her ſelfe into a religious Monaſterie where ſhée led her life as a chaſt and famous virgin, and at her death dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without iſſue (for all his treacherie) ſhe bequeathed her poſſeſſions to her beſt beloued <hi>Pharicles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where gentlemen (thinke of me what you pleaſe) I am conſtrained by conſcience (conſidering the conſtancie of <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blia</hi>) to blame thoſe blaſphemous blabs which are neuer in their vaine except they be breathing out ſome iniurious ſpéeches againſt the conſtancie of women, not yéelding any reaſon of their verdit or reproch, but the reckles rancor of their own peruerſe will pricks the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forward to this deſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full folly. But I hope whatſoeuer the enuious crue ſhall crow againſt me for defending the loyaltie of women, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous &amp; wel diſpoſed gentlemen wil neither appeach me of flattery, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne me of folly: But leauing theſe ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions at laſt to <hi>Pharicles,</hi> who after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnder the profeſſion of a Pilgrim he had cut the ſtraightes with a ſpéedie gale, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mariners by compas of their courſe were come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:6147:14"/> ken of land, and had deſcried the cliffes of <hi>Sicilia:</hi> ſéeing the place of this pretenſed ixile to be ſo neare, had his hart encountred with ſuch a diuerſe combate, and was ſo plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in perplexitie and drenched in the dregges of doubt, as being almoſt frettiſed for feare, the marriners by his oft changing of coulours thought that either the poore pilgrim was in his Oriſons, or elſe paying his debt by death vnto nature. But as their imagination procéeded but by coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his féeble complexion, ſo their aime was quite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the marke, for <hi>Pharicles</hi> was wiſhing for rayne when the ſhower was paſt, drying the malt when the kill was on fire, ſounding the retreat when the battell was fought, yea buying repentance too late. Now he confeſſed the fault when iudgement was paſt, and found himſelfe guilti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when there was no hope of pardon: Nowe he fealt within his crazed conſcience a cruell conflict betwéene wit &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, loue and lightneſſe, fancie and faith: on the one ſide the fixed minde of <hi>Mamillia</hi> proued his fading fancie to be founded on the tottering ſtage of flattery: on the other the conſtancie of <hi>Publia</hi> ſo galded his guiltie conſcience, as he frankly accuſed himſelfe to be as fickle in his faith, and as light in his loue, as the leaues of the hearbe <hi>Baaran</hi> which continually ſhake without ceaſing.</p>
            <p>But the Pirate although hée knowes his practiſe to be plaine theft, yet he turneth forth a newe leafe, till eyther he be drowned in the ſea, or elſe toſſed by ſome infortunate tempeſt, land his ſhippe at Tyborne: The counterfaite Coyner although hée knowes his craft to be a flatte trick of treaſon, yet hée will not take the checke for his fault, vntill he hath the finall mate for his offence. So <hi>Pharicles,</hi> although he knewe himſelfe to be a déepe diſſembler, and that flatterie was cooſin germain to trecherie, yet he feared not to mock ſo long with <hi>Mamillia,</hi> &amp; diſſemble with <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> vntill he gained nothing for his reward but a ſhip of ſorrow to diſgeſt the reckleſſe roote of repentance: for as he
<pb facs="tcp:6147:14"/> had receiued the ſtroke by fickleneſſe, ſo he meant to ſalue the ſore by flight: as he had bred his bane by their preſence, ſo he would cure his diſeaſe by abſence: thinking that <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> his ſentence in Logick was alſo an <hi>Axiome</hi> in loue, that one contrary driues out another: Iudging as priuate familiaritie was the father of fancie, ſo diſcontinuance ſhould be of ſufficient force to quench out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frying flames of loue. But he ſate beſide the ſaddle, for he ſpake by geſſe and not by experience, by wit, but not by wiſedome. The ſting of a ſerpent by continuance enuenometh the whole bodie. He which is charmed of the <hi>Torpedo</hi> by procraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation runneth mad, and the pricke of loue by delay is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable: yet <hi>Pharicles</hi> blinded with the vale of vanitie, and ſowſed in the ſeas of ſelfeloue, was ſo wrapped in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waues of wilfulneſſe, as at the firſt hee thought his iourney into <hi>Sicilia</hi> a perfect pumiceſtone to race out the memorie of his daintie dames in <hi>Italie.</hi> But he ſkipt beyond his ſkill, and was verie groſſely blinded with folly, for he was not only fruſtrate of his imagination, but did euen frie amidſt the flouds, that as he ſailed on the ſeas, the bewtie of his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes gaue his conſcience ſuch a cruell canuizado by the meanes of fancie, as the poore Gentleman driuen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt into the dungeon of deſpaire, burſt forth into theſe termes.</p>
            <p>O infortunate <hi>Pharicles,</hi> hath the dolorous deſtinies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>créed thy deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or the peruerſe planets in thy natiuity conſpired thy bitter bane? Hath froward fortune ſworne to make thée a miſerable mirrour of her mutabilitie? Shall thy friendes ſorrow at thy hap, and thy foes reioyce at thy chance? yea all the worlde wonder at thy ſtayleſſe ſtate of life. Shall <hi>Mamillia</hi> muſe at thy madneſſe in change, and <hi>Publia</hi> laugh at thy lightnes in choiſe? Yea ſhal they count thée more curious tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> careful, more wittie than wiſe, more light in thy loue than lewd in thy life, and yet ſo lewd as ſufficient to winne the beſt game? Ah <hi>Pharicles,</hi> ſhall thy
<pb facs="tcp:6147:15"/> daintie dames in <hi>Italie</hi> trie by experience, that although thy perſon is ſo brauely beautified with the dowries of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as ſhe ſéemed to ſhew her cunning in caruing a péece of ſo curious perfection, yet thy mind to be ſo blotted with the blemiſh of inconſtancie, and ſo foiled with the filthie ſpot of fickleneſſe, as nature may ſéeme to make a ſupplie in the bodie, ſith there was ſuch a want in the mind? Shall (I ſay) they compare thée to the diamonde, who for all her gliſtering hue diſtilleth deadly poyſon? To the Seaſtar, whoſe ſhell ſtayneth the Iuorie and whoſe meat is blacker than Iet? Vnto the trées in the Mount <hi>Vermiſe,</hi> whoſe barke burneth like fire, and whoſe ſap is colder than Ice? Well <hi>Pharicles,</hi> caſt thy cardes, make thine accountes, and thou ſhalt finde the greateſt gaine to be loſſe, and thy profite to be ſuch as hee that maketh of a mountaine of golde a myerie moulhill, of an Elephant a Gnatte, and commeth from a wealthie merchant to a bare banckrout. Conſider with thy ſelfe thou haſt ſtayned thy ſtocke, and what more to be regarded? Thou haſt crackt thy credite, and what of greater price? Thou haſt loſt thy friendes, and what of more value? Thou haſt purchaſed two moſt truſtie louers to be thy mortall foes, and exiled thy ſelfe as a poore pilgrime into a ſtrange countrie. Why <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles,</hi> can theſe thy dolorous diſcourſes cure thy care? or can vnfoulding of thy infortunate life be a meanes to mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate thy miſerie? rubbe not thy galded conſcience for feare of a déeper ſore, but if thou haſt béene careleſſe in chaunge be nowe carefull and conſtant in choyce, if thou haſt committed a fault ſéeke in ſecret wiſe to make ſome part of amendes, if thou haſt offended by breaking pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe make a recompence in paying performance. Yea but the ſalue (be it neuer ſo pure) is not worth a ruſh if vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt for the ſoare, the medicine being vnfit for the patients diſeaſe, though neuer ſo ſoueraigne, bringeth ſmall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, ſo this thy clarkely counſell vnapt for the cauſe will
<pb facs="tcp:6147:15"/> procure thée but litle eaſe: for thou haſt deceiued <hi>Mamillia,</hi> and halted with <hi>Publia,</hi> thou haſt made a fault to both and canſt make amendes but to one, thy promiſe is to laie thy loue on two where the performance can light but vppon ſome particular perſon, ſo that in any wiſe thou canſt not make a ful ſatiſfaction for thy fault, vnleſſe thou take vpon thée ſuch a charge as thou ſhalt neuer bée able to rule nor they ſuffer. O vnhappie man art thou the onelie marke at which fortune meanes to vnlooſe her infortunate quiuer? And with that hée caſt foorth ſuch a ſigh, as it was a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſign to witneſſe a ready remorſe in his troubled mind, that the maiſter of the ſhip taking compaſſion on this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed pilgrim, thought to comfort his care with this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie motion.</p>
            <p>Sir, quoth he, your bitter teares and déepe ſighs which you powre foorth ſo plentifully, as tokens of ſome inwarde griefe, hath driuen both the marriners &amp; me into a diuerſe dumpe, as we all ſtand in doubt whether thoſe pittifull plaints procéed from a carefull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience combred with ſin, or elſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you are of that order of pilgrims, whoſe pretenſed pilgrimage is to ſéeke S. <hi>Iames,</hi> but their heart &amp; deuotion is vowed to an other Saint, which with a crabbed counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance hath giuen them ſuch a cutting coraſiue as they ſéek by abſence either to mittigate her moode or procure their owne eaſe: and if you bée of the ſame caſe and in the like minde, I will thinke you as madde as he that counteth fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting a ſoueraigne preſeruatiue againſt famine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> hearing the Pilots parle to touch him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, &amp; perceiuing his talke to ſende to ſome end, thought as cloſely to ſtand him the warde as he had clarkely giuen him the blow, and therefore trickt vp his talke with this cunning ſcuſe.</p>
            <p>Pilot quoth <hi>Pharicles,</hi> although they ſkill in nauigation be great, yet if thou hadſt no greater cunning in ſtirring of the ſtearne, than in coniecturing the cauſe of my ſorrow,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:16"/> I would verie lothly haue committed my ſelfe vnder thy charge to haue ſailed into <hi>Sicillia:</hi> for whether thou preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt vppon phiſiognomie or follie, it is but a bare diuiſion to ſay that either loue or ſinne muſt be the cauſe of griefe: but put caſe thou haſt hit the marke, and that my outward ſighes be ſignes of inward loue, will not abſence thinkeſt thou diminiſh affection?</p>
            <p>Yes quoth the Pilote, when you finde ſolitarineſſe a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne ſalue againſt ſorrow, then will the dewe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuance quench out the fire of fancie: but leauing theſe amorous queſtions, you are welcome to the coaſtes of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſéeing the cockboate readie to carrie him to the ſhoare, rewarded both the maiſter and the marriners very francklie, deſiring the Pilot (ſith he himſelfe was a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) to guide him to ſome honeſt Inne, where hée might make his aboade while he ſtaied in the countrie. Who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verie deſirous to gratifie the Gentleman, carried <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles</hi> to a verie friends houſe of his, who for the Pilottes cauſe gaue <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſuch curteous entertainment, as hée thought himſelfe to haue hapt on a verie good hoaſt.</p>
            <p>Where by the way Gentlemen, we ſée the tickle ſtate of ſuch yong youthes whoſe wits are wils, and their wils are lawes, coueting ſo much ſenſual libertie, as they bring themſelues into perpetuall bondage: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Polype</hi> hath not more colours, nor the <hi>Camelion</hi> more ſundrie ſhapes than they haue change in thoughts, now liking, now loathing: for a while profeſſed enimies to <hi>Venus</hi> court, &amp; then ſworn true ſubiects to the crowne of <hi>Cupid,</hi> ſo variable as a man can neither iudge of their nature, nor nourture, vnleſſe by natiuitie they be lunatikes, not taking this worde as the Engliſh men do, for ſtarke mad, but as borne vnder the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of <hi>Luna,</hi> and therfore as firme in their faith as the melting waxe that receiueth euerie impreſſion, thinking
<pb facs="tcp:6147:16"/> as <hi>Pharicles</hi> did, that it is a Courtiers profeſſion to court to euerie dame but to bee conſtant to none, that it is the grace to ſpeak finely though without faith, and to be wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in words to as many as the luſting eie can like: ſo that at length whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their talke is found tales, their loue luſt, and their proteſted promiſes ſmal performance, then their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite béeing crackt, they muſt be trauellers to ſéeke that in a ſtrange country which they could neuer find in their own: they muſt into <hi>Sicillia</hi> for ſhiftes, into <hi>Italie</hi> for pride, to <hi>France</hi> for fraude, and to <hi>Englande</hi> for faſhions and follie, ſo that they returne home laden, not with learning, but with leaudneſſe, not with vertue but with vice, yea, their whole fraught is a maſſe of miſchiefes. I ſpeake not of all trauellers Gentlemen, but of ſuch as <hi>Pharicles,</hi> which take their iourney, either that their credite at home is craſie, or elſe being wedded to vanitie ſéeke to augment their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</p>
            <p>But againe to <hi>Pharicles,</hi> who now ſafely ſetled in <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſſa</hi> the chiefe citie in <hi>Sicillia,</hi> a place of no leſſe ſuſpition than reſort (and yet the moſt famous mart in all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie) dealt ſo clarkely in his calling, and behaued himſelfe ſo demurely, as his pretenſed kinde of life gaue occaſion to no man to ſuſpect his fained profeſſion: for his Palmers wéed was worne with ſuch a grauitie in his countenance, and ſuch a modeſtie in his maners, as all men thought the man to be halfe mortified. For <hi>Pharicles</hi> knew verie well that he could not liue in <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> vnder the ſtate of a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, but either he muſt ſpende with the beſt or ſit with the woorſt: yea, beſide that without companions hée could not bée: and hée thought it verie harde to chooſe a dramme of golde among a pounde of droſſe, to finde one Gemme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt a whole heape of flint, one Eele among many Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, and one friend amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a thouſand flatterers: it might aſſoone be his happe to chaunce on a diſſembling <hi>Dauus</hi> as on a truſty <hi>Damon,</hi> to commit his counſel to a ſubtil <hi>Sinon</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6147:17"/> as to a faithfull <hi>Pilades,</hi> to take him for a profeſſed friend which might be a proteſted foe, in the faireſt graſſe to finde the fowleſt Snake, in <hi>Oryllus</hi> boxe a deadly poyſon, in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus</hi> ſcarph a withered roote, in the ſhape of a friende the ſubſtance of a foe. Hée thought likewiſe that ſuch a Citie as <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> was often times as well ſtored with Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites as garded with ſouldiers, and as full of counterfaites as counſellers, and that he might finde many couſins clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming more acquaintance to his purſe than kinred to his perſon, more allyed to his liuing than to his linage: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, more to féed his fancie for gaine than either good wil or friendſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> partly feared and partly perſwaded with the conſideration of the former premiſſes, was fully reſolued in his minde to abandon all company, &amp; to giue a finall fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel to his forepaſſed follie, to make a change of his chaffer with better ware, of his droſſe with golde, and of his flée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting will with ſtaied wiſedome. Hauing thus determined to leade a Pilgrims life to puniſh his bodie with this Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers penance, in ſatiſfaction of his diſloyall dealings with his truſty louers, he had not liued in this Hermits ſtate by the ſpace of a moneth, but he proued the Pilots talke to be no tales, nor his wordes to be winde, but a ſetled ſentence: for want of company ſo increaſed his care, and brought ſuch melancholike motions to his muſing mind, as now he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſolitarineſſe to be the nurſſe of ſorrow, and diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance the father of fancie. The modeſtie of <hi>Mamillia,</hi> the conſtancie of <hi>Publia,</hi> his credite crakt in <hi>Italie,</hi> his youth ſpent in vanity, his great promiſes and ſmal performance, his fained faith &amp; forged flatterie, ſo battered the bulwarke of his breſt, &amp; gaue ſuch fierce aſſaults to his carefull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as he thought himſelfe to be in a ſecond Hell, vntill he might find a meanes to mitigate his miſerie: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as ſolitarines was the ſore, ſo he meant ſocietie ſhould be the ſalue, determining to driue away thoſe dumpes by
<pb facs="tcp:6147:17"/> frequenting of companie, which otherwiſe woulde haue bredde his vtter bane: reſpecting neither coſt, expences, nor hazarding of himſelfe, ſo his minde might remaine in quiet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> hauing thus caſt off his Pilgrimes wéed and Pilgrims profeſſion, gaue the citizens of <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> in ſhort time to vnderſtand that hée was as well a Gentleman by nature as by nurture, and as worthily brought vp as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfully borne. For firſt hée made a reſtraint of his will by wit, then vſed his wit ſo warilie and wiſelie, ſhewing ſuch a curteous countenance and franke liberalitie to al e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, as he draue them into a dout, whether the comlines of his perſon, or the worthineſſe of his mind deſerued grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter commendation: In ſo much as thoſe yong Gentlemen thought themſelues happie which might be counted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to this new gueſt, &amp; aboue all the reſt of this court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true which kept him company, a yong gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> named <hi>Ferragus,</hi> onely ſonne to the gouernour of <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> was ioyned with him in moſt priuate familiarity, thinking that day euill ſpent, wherein he had not viſited his new friend <hi>Pharicles,</hi> and the more to do him honor being a ſtranger, hée oftentimes carried him to his fathers houſe, where in ſhort time <hi>Pharicles</hi> wonne ſuch credit by his curteſie, that <hi>Signor Ferneſe</hi> (for ſo was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old gentleman called) thought his houſe the more luckie he had ſuch a gueſt, &amp; his ſonne the more happie he had choſen ſuch a companion: but for al this <hi>Pharicles</hi> fearing to find a pad in the ſtraw, and a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſparke amongſt colde aſhes, was a foe to none, nor a friend to anie, neither durſt truſt <hi>Ferragus</hi> without ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent triall, but bare himſelfe ſo indifferent to all, yet ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe ſo fit for all companies, as well in ripeneſſe of wit as reuenewes of wealth, that there was no talke for a time but of the perfection of <hi>Pharicles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While thus flattering fame had ſpread abroad his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous qualities, there was a yong gentlewoman in <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſſa</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6147:18"/> called <hi>Clarynda,</hi> of more wealth than beautie, and yet ſo ſufficientlie furniſhed with the perfections &amp; dowries of nature, that if ſhe could haue bene continent and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in her loue, ſhée might haue bene for her perſon a fit mate for the moſt famous Prince in the worlde. But ſhée being both yong, rich, and beautifull, hauing neither father nor mother which might make a reſtraint of her nature by due nurture, and enioying a libertie without controle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which be the greateſt bawdes in the world to make a Gentlewoman ſlide in ſuch ſlipperie pathes, hauing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther care of her perſon nor regard of her parentage, but ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting both honour and honeſtie to ſale became a profeſſed Curtizan.</p>
            <p>In which ſtayleſſe ſtate of life ſhe waded ſo far, that her chiefeſt care was to bée careleſſe in that which aboue all things ſhe ought moſt to haue regarded, for whereas both her birth and beautie had béene of ſufficient force to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her to beautifie the goods of fortune and gifts of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with a maidenlie modeſtie and ſilent chaſtitie, ſhée contrariwiſe linking her ſelfe to ſenſual libertie, and wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her minde to vanitie, ſought to reape renowne &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe fame by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ſhe tried in time to bréede her grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt infamie: for why, ſhe found both ſuch pleaſure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite by ſetting her honeſtie to ſale in the ſhameleſſe ſhop of voluptuous deſires, that neither the ſhame of her life, nor the feare of her death, the ſtate of her birth, or the ſtaine of her beautie, might in any wiſe mooue her from her loathed kinde of liuing: no her heart was ſo hardened, and her eares ſo enchanted with the alluring charme of <hi>Venus</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neither the perſuaſions of her friends lamenting her caſe, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reioyſing of her foes laughing at her leaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, could driue her to deſiſt from her deteſtable kinde of dealing. Nay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſhe was counſelled, the leſſe ſhe was conformable; the more ſhe was intreated, the leſſe ſhe was tractable: yea, ſhe ſetled her ſelfe ſo ſurely, as ſhe thought
<pb facs="tcp:6147:18"/> in the ſeate of ſelfewill and ſecuritie, that ſhe imployed all her time and ſtudie to entertaine her licentious louers, ſhewing her ſelfe ſuch a ſubtile <hi>Circes</hi> and craftie <hi>Calipſo,</hi> in giuing them peſtiferous potions, and drowning them in the dregges of diuelliſh delights, that vnleſſe it were ſome warie <hi>Vliſſes</hi> that had prouided a preſeruatiue againſt her poiſon, they returned tranſformed into apes or aſſes, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to worſe if worſe may be. And yet for all this fained affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, her fléeting fancie was neuer fixed vpon any, but laying the net, was frée her ſelfe, caſting the bayte, auoyded the hooke, ſéeking to entrappe others, ſhe her ſelfe was neuer intangled: and as the moſt infectious ſerpent hath alwaies the ſwéeteſt breath, ſo for all her vicious mind ſhe had ſuch a vertuous tongue, and trickt vp her talke with ſuch pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted colours, as they of <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> did maruell how ſhe could ſo clarkely couer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance of vice vnder the ſhape of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: yea they learned by her leaudneſſe to warn their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from ſuch ſtate of life, they did ſée verie well how that which was bredde by the boane would not out of the fleſh, that the yoong Adder would prooue an olde Serpent, that the cragged twigge woulde prooue a crooked trée, that ſhée which ſpent her youth without reſtraint, woulde leade her age without controlement, that the mayd which was vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to vanitie would wedde her ſelfe in time to follie. But againe to <hi>Clarynda,</hi> who wallowing in the waues of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, and offering her incenſe at the altar of <hi>Venus,</hi> heard as well as others y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rare report of <hi>Pharicles</hi> perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which tickling ſomewhat her toyiſh minde, made her deſirous to trie what was in the gentleman by experience, and to reape both pleaſure by his perſon, and profite by his purſe, which was the chiefeſt marke whereat ſhée al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies aymed: Couering therefore the heart of a Tigre with the fléece of a Lambe, the clawes of a Grype with the pennes of a Doue, the vanitie of <hi>Lais</hi> with the vale of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretia,</hi> the miſerable conditions of a Curtizan with the
<pb facs="tcp:6147:19"/> modeſt countenance of a matrone, decking her ſelfe with i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns &amp; iewels of infinit valour, ſet her ſelf in her window as an adamant obiect to draw the wauering eyes of <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> thinking that as none could heare the <hi>Syrens</hi> ſing, but they ſhould be charmed with their melodie, ſo it were as impoſſible to ſée her and not bee allured with her beautie. But as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lion ſéeking to intrap the hart as a pray, is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf vnwares taken in the toiles: ſo <hi>Clarinda</hi> making the ſnare fell in the pit, holding the view was taken at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gaze, ſéeking to catch an other captiue, was brought her ſelf into perpetuall bondage: for indéed (according to her deſire and imagination) <hi>Pharicles</hi> conſtrained by certaine his neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie affairs came by her houſe, yet armed with ſuch a priuie coate as hée warilie withſtood the greateſt daunger of her inuenomed ſhot: giuing her to vnderſtand that he could flie about the candle and not be ſinged, ſée the <hi>Scorpion</hi> and not be ſtricken, that hée could laugh and looke without liking: yea warme himſelfe verie nigh the fire and not be burned, that he could <hi>accedere ad hunc ignem,</hi> and yet not <hi>caleſcere pluſquam ſatis:</hi> For why, paſſing by her window and ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this gorgious Gorgon ſo ſhrined in the ſhape of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, did not onely repu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e at Nature for placing ſo helliſh a minde in ſo heauenlie a creature, but alſo ſmiled to ſée ſuch brauerie linked with ſo litle honeſtie, and ſuch perfect beautie blemiſht with the want of chaſtitie. Yet willing to ſhew himſelfe a friend to all, he gaue her the <hi>Salue</hi> with a cringing curteſie, and went to his lodging without anie more loſſe than in lending his looke to ſuch alluring vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But ſhe contrariwiſe being at diſcouert, noting the comelineſſe of <hi>Pharicles</hi> countenance, &amp; imprinting in her heart the perfection of his perſon, had her fancie ſo fettered aſwel with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> report of others as with her own iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that ſhe maruelled to find ſuch a ſtraunge <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> in her immodeſt mind: for thinking to ſhake off y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhackles with a bare farwell as ſhe had done before, ſhe felt her ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:6147:19"/> ſo faſt tyed to the ſtake, that it craued her greateſt cunning to vnlooſe the knot. Nowe ſhe felt the poyſon to worke on her ſelfe that ſhe had prouided for others, and perceiued that intending to lay the ſnare, ſhée her ſelfe was wholly entrapped: yea the force of fancie gaue ſuch fierce allarmes to her new beſieged minde, as no rampier that ſhe coulde make might withſtand the batterie. The more ſhe ſtroue againſt the ſtreame the leſſe it did preuaile, the cloſer ſhée couered the ſparke, the more it kindled: yea, in ſéeking to vnloſe the Lunes, the more ſhée was intangled: In fine after ſhe had paſſed two or thrée dayes in kicking againſt the pricke, ſhe felt ſuch a hapleſſe horrour in her troubled mind, that ſhe was forced to enter into conſideration with her ſelfe what conditions ſhe ſhould offer to her newe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed enemie, and therefore entering into her cloſet vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red theſe ſpéeches.</p>
            <p>O vniuſt Gods quoth ſhée, which haue indued brute beaſtes with greater perfection in their kinde than reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable creatures: The Garlike killeth the Serpent, &amp; ſhée by inſtinct of nature eſcheweth the ſame. The iuice of hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke poyſoneth the beare and what more abhorred? the greaſe of the ſnayle infecteth the ape, and what more loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed? yea euery creature ſhunneth the occaſion of danger, man onely excepted, which ſéeketh with purſuit to obtaine that which bréedeth his confuſion: what bruiſeth the brain? what mazeth the minde? what weakeneth the wit? what bréedeth feare? what bringeth frenzie? what ſoweth ſorrowe? what reapeth care more than loue? and yet the onely thing wherein man delighteth. The byrd louing the woodes loatheth the nets, the hart liking the lawnes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſnares: But man placing his felicitie in fréedome, taketh greateſt care to caſt himſelfe into perpetuall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Clarinda,</hi> would to God thou mighteſt accuſe others and be frée thy ſelfe from this follie: but alas thou doeſt
<pb facs="tcp:6147:20"/> condemne others of that cryme wherein thou thy ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueſt greateſt blame: Wilt thou now fond foole become a profeſſed friend to affection, which haſt alwayes béene a proteſted foe to fancie? wilt thou now ſuffer thy minde to bée nouſled vp in captiuitie, which hath alwaies béene nourſed vp in libertie? Thou haſt counſelled others to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the traine, and wilt thou now thy ſelfe be taken in the trappe? thou haſt boaſted that thou couldeſt both like and loath at thine owne pleaſure, and ſhall thy brags now bée daunted with diſgrace? wilt thou now proue ſuch a cowarde to yéelde to the file, to ſtoope at the ſtampe, to giue ouer the fielde before there be a ſtroake ſtroken, yea and to ſuch a cruell tyrant as loue is? It is a ſaying not ſo common as true, that ſhée which ſoweth all her loue in an houre, ſhall not reape all her care in a yeare, that ſhée which liketh without remembrance ſhall not liue without repentaunce. So then <hi>Clarynda</hi> be wiſe, ſince thou art warned, looke before thou leapeſt: there is no better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt daunger than to conſider the ende of thine enterpriſe. Thou art intangled with the loue of a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, who perhaps hath his heart fixed on ſome other place, thou haſt fondly ſet thine affection vpon one whoſe wealth, wit, and conditions, thou onely knoweſt by the flattering report of fame, he is in outwarde ſhewe a Saint, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes in inward mind a ſerpent, for his perſon a paragon of beauty, for his conditions ſince he ſoiourned in <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> moſt highlie to bée commended: yea ſo perfect in ſubſtance and qualitie as he may in no reſpect be appeached of want: why? but <hi>Clarynda</hi> fame is not alwaies true, and the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt bloome hath not alwayes the beſt fruite: thoſe birdes which ſing ſwéeteſt, haue oftentimes the ſowreſt fleſh, the ryuer <hi>Silia</hi> is moſt pleaſant to the eye and yet moſt hurtful to the ſtomacke, the ſtone <hi>Nememphis</hi> is not ſo delicate without, as deadly within, all that gliſters is not golde. <hi>Pharicles (Clarynda)</hi> for all his pompous fame of perfect co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
<pb facs="tcp:6147:20"/> may bée a paraſiticall flatterer of moſt imperfect conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Who was more curteous than <hi>Conon</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian?</hi> and yet a verie counterfeite; who more gentle than <hi>Galba</hi> in ſhewe? yet none more trecherous in proofe; <hi>Vliſſes</hi> had a faire tongue but a falſe heart, <hi>Metellus</hi> was modeſt but yet mutable: the cloath is not knowne till it come to the wéeting, nor a louers quallities perceiued till he come to the wearing. Well <hi>Clarinda</hi> although it is good to doubt the worſt, yet ſuppoſe the beſt, he is conſtant, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, not vain-glorious nor wedded vnto vanitie, but a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted foe to vice and a profeſſed friend to vertue: Alas fond foole? if thou wey thy caſe in the equall ballance the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is thy care &amp; the more is thy miſerie, for by how much the more he himſelfe is vertuous, ſo much leſſe hée will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeme thée which art vicious: doeſt thou thinke he which is truſtie wil regard thée which art trothleſſe? y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full curteſie will brooke thy fained inconſtancie? is thy ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſo beſotted with ſelfeloue to ſuppoſe that a Gentleman of great wealth and no leſſe wit, famous both for his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and parentage, will bée ſo witleſſe in chaunge or care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in choice, ſo light in his loue or leaude in his life, as to fixe his affection vpon a profeſſed Curtizan, whoſe honeſtie and credit is ſo wracked in the waues of wantonneſſe, and ſo weatherbeaten with the billowes of immodeſtie, that it is ſet to ſale in the ſhameleſſe ſhop of <hi>Venus</hi> as a thing of no value to be cheapt of euery ſtragling chapman. No no <hi>Clarinda,</hi> there is ſuch a great difference betwéene thy hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe chaunce and his happie choice, betwéene thy careleſſe liuing and his carefull life, as there remains to thée not ſo much as one dramme of hope to cure thy intollerable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie. And why fond foole? Was not <hi>Lamia</hi> in profeſſion a Curtizan, in life a laſciuious vaſſall to <hi>Venus</hi> vanitie, yea to figure her foorth in plaine tearmes a ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe ſtrumpet racking her honeſtie to the vttermoſt, therby to raiſe reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes to maintaine her immodeſt life, and yet for all the
<pb facs="tcp:6147:21"/> blemiſh of immoderate luſt wherein ſhe was lulled a ſléep by ſecurity, ſhe ſo charmed and enchanted with her Syren ſubtleties the ſenſes of king <hi>Demetrius,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was ſo blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the beames of her beautie, and dimmed with the wanton vale of her alluring vanities, forgetting that ſhée was by calling a curtizan &amp; by cuſtome common to all that could wage her honeſtie with the appointed price, he ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely loued this graceleſſe dame, that neither the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of her forepaſſed follie, nor the ſuſpition of her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent immodeſtie coulde driue that worthy king to miſlike her, vntill the extreame date of death parted their inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable amitie? Were not manie noble Princes allured to the loue of <hi>Lais?</hi> Was not that worthy Romane <hi>Caſſius</hi> ſo fettered with the forme of <hi>Flora</hi> the renowmed curtizan of <hi>Rome,</hi> that hee offered the prime of his yéeres at the ſhrine of that gorgeous Goddeſſe, and yet the worſt of theſe two worthie wights farre ſurpaſſing <hi>Pharicles</hi> as well in ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of wit as reuenewes of wealth. Yea but <hi>Clarynda</hi> inferre no compariſon, for theſe two ſtately dames were ſo decked and adorned with the giftes of nature, and ſo poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with princely perfection, that they were the moſt rare iems and péereleſſe paragons of beautie that euer were ſhrowded vnder the ſhape of mortalitie, ſo that if <hi>Iupiter</hi> had but once frequented their companie, no doubt <hi>Iuno</hi> would haue béen infected with ielowſie, wheras thy come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe deſerueth no ſuch ſurpaſſing commendation, but that thou mayſt yéeld the palme of a victorie to a thouſand whoſe beautie is ſuch as their greateſt imperfection may daunt thée with diſgrace. Why but <hi>Clarynda,</hi> art thou ſo mad to lay a cutting coraſiue to a gréene wound, to procure heat with colde, to repreſſe hunger with famine, to ſalue ſorrow with ſolitarineſſe, and to mittigate thy miſery with extreme diſpaire? No no, ſince thou art once lodged vp in the lothſome labyrinth of loue, thou muſt like <hi>Theſeus</hi> be haled out with the thréed of hope: for better hadſt thou met
<pb facs="tcp:6147:21"/> with <hi>Minotaurus</hi> in plaine combat, than be but once arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the miſerable maſe of diſtruſt. And therefore <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynda</hi> caſt away care, retire not before thou haſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe, but kéepe the courſe by thy compaſſe: and ſince thou haſt the ſore ſéeke the ſalue, applie thy wit &amp; will, thy hand and heart to atchieue that thing, in atteining whereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts either thy continuall calamitie or perpetuall ioy, and with that ſhe ſtept to her ſtandiſh which ſtoode in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and wrote a letter to <hi>Pharicles</hi> in this effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Signora Clarynda of Saragoſſa, to Don Pharicles proſperitie.</head>
                  <p>ALthough thou haſt both cauſe to muſe and maruell (O noble <hi>Pharicles</hi> and vnacquainted gentleman) in that thou receiueſt a letter from her whome neither fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie nor friendſhippe can giue iuſt occaſion ſo much as once to ſalute thée with a <hi>Salue,</hi> much leſſe to trouble thy patience with ſuch ſtuffe as may bréede thy miſliking &amp; my miſerie, if the gods be not ayding to my enterpriſe, yet if thou ſhalt vouchſafe to conſtrue my meaning to the beſt, or at the leaſt take the paines to turne ouer theſe imperfect lines procéeding from a perplexed perſon, which I hope thy noble minde and curteſie will commaund thée, thou ſhalt finde it no ſmaller cauſe than the fatall feare of death that forced mée to yéeld to this extremitie, nor the occaſion leſſe than the dread of pinching diſpair which draue me to paſſe the golden meaſure of ſurpaſſing modeſtie. In déede the noble and vertuous dames <hi>(Pharicles)</hi> of famous memorie, whoſe happie life hath canonized them in Chronicles for
<pb facs="tcp:6147:22"/> perfect paragons both of vertue and beautie, haue with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall conſent auerred, that ſhamefaſt modeſtie and ſilence be the two rareſt gems &amp; moſt precious iewels wherwith a Gentlewoman may be adorned. Notwithſtanding they haue all been of this mind, that where either loue or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie extend their extreme rigour to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttermoſt, there both humane &amp; diuine lawes ſurceaſe, as not of ſufficient force to abide the brunt of two ſuch terrible &amp; vntamed tyrants. For there is no ſilence ſuch but the fyle of loue will fret in ſunder: nor no modeſtie ſo ſhamefaſt but the ſting of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie will force to paſſe both ſhame and meaſure. <hi>Sappho (Pharicles)</hi> was both learned, wiſe, and vertuous, and yet the fire of fancie ſo ſcorched and ſcalded her modeſt minde, as ſhe was forced to let ſlip the raynes of ſilence to craue a ſalue of <hi>Phaon</hi> to cure her intollerable malady. If <hi>Phedra (Pharicles)</hi> had not both ſurpaſſed in beautie and modeſtie, poore <hi>Theſeus</hi> would neuer haue forſaken his <hi>Ariadne</hi> in the deſertes, to haue linked himſelfe with her in the inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable league of matrimonie, yet her beautie and modeſtie were brought to ſuch a lowe ebbe by the batterie of loue, that ſhée was faine to ſue for helpe to her vnhappie ſonne <hi>Hipolitus.</hi> I dare not <hi>(ô Pharicles)</hi> of theſe exemplified premiſſes inferre either compariſon or concluſion, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare my ſelf to them were a point of arrogancie, and to derogate ſo much fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their degrée, as to match them with my rudeneſſe were a trick of extreme follie. Yet this I am forced to confeſſe, that the ſelfeſame fire hath ſo infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med my fancie, &amp; the like batterie hath ſo beaten my breſt, as ſilence and modeſtie ſet aſide, I am forced by loue to pleade for pardon at the barre of thy bounty, whoſe captiue I remaine, till either the ſentence of life or death be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced vpon me poore carefull caytife. Loue, yea, loue it is, <hi>(ô Pharicles)</hi> and more if more may be that hath ſo fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered my fréedome and tyed my libertie with ſo ſhort a ted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as either thou muſt be the man which muſt vnloſe me
<pb facs="tcp:6147:22"/> from the lunes, or elſe I ſhal remaine in a lothſome Labe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth til the extreme date of death deliuer me. The Deare <hi>Pharicles,</hi> is more impatient at the firſt ſtroake, than the Hynde which before hath béene galded and yet eſcaped, the ſouldier gréeueth more at the firſt cut, than he which hath béene acquainted with many woundes: ſo I alas hauing neuer felt before the fire of fancie, nor tried the terrible torment of loue, thinke the burthen more great, &amp; the yoke more heauie, by how much the leſſe I haue bin acquainted with ſuch inſupportable burdens. Well <hi>Pharicles,</hi> I know thou wilt conclude of theſe my premiſſes, that ſince I haue béene an inhabitour ſo long <hi>Nell' la ſtrada cortizana,</hi> &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed my ſelfe a friend to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that either I haue béene a déepe diſſembler in féeding many fooles fat with flattery, or elſe that I neuer loued any but thee, is a trothleſſe tale, &amp; a flat trick of trecherie. Confeſſe I muſt of force (O worthie gentleman) that I haue flattered many, but neuer fancied any, that I haue allured ſome, but loued none, that I haue taken diuerſe in the trap, and yet always eſcaped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſnare, vntill too long flying about the candle, I am ſo ſcorched in the flame, &amp; ſo ſurely faſtened with the fetters of fancie by the only ſight of thy ſurpaſſing beautie, as of force I muſt remaine thy carefull captiue till either thy curteſie or cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie cut aſunder the thréed of hope, which makes me pine in miſerie. It is not <hi>(ô Pharicles)</hi> thy purſſe but thy perſon which hath pierced my heart, not thy coyne but thy comli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which hath made the conqueſt, not the helpe of gaine, but the hope of thy good will that hath intangled my frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, not the glitring ſhape of vanitie but the golden ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of vertue, not thy liuing, lands or parentage, but thy rare qualities and exquiſite perfections are the champions which haue chayned mée in the balefull bandes of laſting bondage. Laſting I may well tearme them, ſith there is ſuch a difference betwéene thy ſtate and my ſtay, as there remaines to me no hope of libertie. For perhaps <hi>Pharicles</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6147:23"/> thou wilt ſay, that the crooked twig will proue a crabbed trée, that the ſower bud will neuer be ſwéete bloſſome, how that which is bred by the bone will not eaſily out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, that ſhe which is common in her youth wil be more incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in her age: To conclude, that the woman which in prime of yeares is laſciuious, will in ripe age be moſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous. Yet <hi>Pharicles</hi> I anſwere, that the bloſſomes of the <hi>Mirabolanes</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> is moſt infectious, and yet the fruite verie precious: that the wine may be ſower in the preſſe, &amp; yet by time moſt ſwéet in the Caſke: that oftimes where vice raigneth in youth, there vertue remaineth in age. Who more peruerſe being yong than <hi>Paulyna,</hi> &amp; who more perfect being old? <hi>Loſyna</hi> the Quéene of the <hi>Vendales</hi> at the firſt a vicious maiden, but at the laſt a moſt vertuous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone. But to aime more neare the marke, was not <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dope</hi> in the prime of her youth counted the moſt famous or rather the moſt infamous ſtrumpet of all <hi>Egypt?</hi> ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a curtizan, as ſhe was a ſecond <hi>Meſſalyna</hi> for her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate luſt, yet in the floure of her age being married to <hi>Pſammeticus</hi> the king of <hi>Memphis,</hi> ſhe proued ſo honeſt a wife and ſo chaſte a Princes, as ſhe was not before ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached for the ſmall regard of her honeſtie, as after ſhée was renowned for her inuiolable chaſtitie. <hi>Phryne</hi> that graceles <hi>Gorgon</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> whoſe monſtrous life was ſo immodeſt that her careleſſe chaſtitie was a pray to euerie ſtragling ſtranger, after ſhe was married to <hi>Siconius,</hi> ſhée became ſuch a foe to vice, and ſuch a friend to vertue, yea, ſhe troad her ſteppes ſo ſteddily in the trade of honeſtie, as the <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> of her life to her perpetuall fame was ingrauen in the brazen gates of <hi>Athens.</hi> So <hi>(Pharicles)</hi> if the Gods ſhall giue me ſuch proſperous fortune as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſome fauour of thée in liew of my moſt loyal loue, and I ſhall reape ſome rewarde for my deſertes and haue my fired fancy requited with feruent affection, aſſure thy ſelf I will ſo make a change of my chaffre for better ware, of my
<pb facs="tcp:6147:23"/> fléeting will with ſtaied wiſdome, of my inconſtancie with continencie, from a moſt vicious liking to ſuch a vertuous liuing, from a laſciuious <hi>Lamia,</hi> to a moſt loial <hi>Lucretia,</hi> as both thou and all the worlde ſhall haue as great cauſe to maruell at my modeſtie, as they had cauſe to murmure at my former diſhoneſtie: &amp; thus languiſhing in hope I wiſh thee as good hap as thou canſt deſire or imagine.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine though the Gods ſay no, Clarynda.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>CLarynda</hi> hauing thus finiſht her Letter, called one of her maydes which ſhée thought moſt méete for ſuche a purpoſe, and willed her to carrie it with as much ſpéede as might bee to <hi>Pharicles,</hi> who hauing taken the charge in hand, dealt ſo clarklie in the cauſe as ſhée ſought ſuch fit opportunitie for the performance of her meſſage, that ſhée found <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſitting ſolitarie in his chamber, to whom ſhe offered the letter in her miſtreſſe behalf on this wiſe.</p>
            <p>Sir quoth ſhe, if my bold attempt to trouble your ſtudie may import ſmall manners or little modeſtie, the vrgent cauſe being once knowne, I hope both I ſhalbe excuſed and you pacified. For ſo it is, that my miſtreſſe <hi>Clarynda</hi> by the ſpace of two or thrée daies hath bene pinched with ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted paines, and griped with ſuche vnſpeakeable griefs, as the extremitie of her ſickneſſe is ſuch, as we looke onely when the ſtroake of death ſhall frée her from this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible calamitie. Yet amidſt the ſoreſt panges of her pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching diſtreſſe, ſhe commaunded me to preſent this letter
<pb facs="tcp:6147:24"/> to your worſhips hands, wherein both the cauſe and the ſickeneſſe it ſelfe is decyphered. For ſhe hath heard by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that you haue ſuch perfect ſkill in curing that kinde of maladie which by fortune is inflicted vpon her, that eyther of her death or the reſtoring of her health conſiſteth in your cunning, which if it be ſuch, as no doubt it is, if ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you haue the nature of a Gentleman, or your courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie be ſuch as all <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> ſpeaketh of, I hope her diſeaſe being once knowen, you will ſend ſuch a ſoueraigne ſalue for her ſickeneſſe, as we her poore handmaides ſhall haue cauſe to giue you thankes for our miſtreſſe health, and ſhe her ſelfe be bound to remayne a duetifull debter of yours for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> hearing the ſubtile ſong of this enchaunting <hi>Syren,</hi> doubted to touch the ſcrappe for feare of the ſnare, and was loath to taſte of any daintie delicates, leaſt he might vnhappilie be croſſed with ſome impoyſoned diſh of charming <hi>Cyrces,</hi> for <hi>Pharicles</hi> knewe himſelfe an vnfitte Phyſition for ſuch a paltring patient, neither could he on the ſodaine diuine of her dangerous diſeaſe, nor coniecture the cauſe of her inſupportable ſorowe, vnleſſe ſhe were fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in loue with his friend <hi>Ferragus,</hi> and thought to make him a meanes to perſwade his friend to the like affection. But to auoide the trappe whatſoeuer the trayne were, he though beſt to looke before he did leape, and to caſt the water before he gaue counſell, leaſt in knéeling to Saint <hi>Francis</hi> ſhrine, he ſhould be thought a Fryer of the ſame fraternitie: to auoyde therefore ſuch inconuenience as might happen by replying too raſhlie, he gaue her this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine anſwere.</p>
            <p>Maide quoth he, as you haue for your part ſufficientlie ſatiſfied me with this excuſe, not to thinke euill of your boldneſſe, ſo you haue driuen me into a doubt what I ſhould coniecture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrangenes of the meſſage, ſith that ſince I ſoiourned in <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> I haue neither openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb facs="tcp:6147:24"/> my ſelfe a Phyſition, nor ſecretly miniſtred to any of my friends wherby any ſuch ſuppoſition might be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but perhaps it pleaſeth your Miſtreſſe to deſcant thus merily with me for my pilgrims apparell which at my firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> I did vſe to weare, which if it be ſo, tell her I traueiled not as a Pilgrim that had cunning to cure the diſeaſe of a Curtizan, becauſe I would not buy repentance too déere, but that my pilgrims wéed did warne me to beware for cheaping ſuch chaffre, as was ſet to ſale in the ſhameleſſe ſhop of <hi>Venus:</hi> Marrie if your miſtreſſe be in earneſt, &amp; that her diſeaſe be ſo dangerous that all the learned Phyſitions in <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> dare not deale withall, and yet my ſmall ſkill may cure it, I meane firſt to ſéeke out the nature of the ſickneſſe, and then the vertue of the ſimples to make the receipt, which being done, my Page ſhal bring her an anſwer of her letter ſpéedily. The maide hearing this doubtfull anſwere departed, but <hi>Pharicles</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſée what clarklie concluſions he ſhould find in the Curtizans ſcrowle, could ſcarcely ſtay while the maide had turned her back from vnripping the Seales, wherein he found <hi>Clarinda</hi> combred with ſuch a perilous ſickneſſe, as muſt of neceſſity bréede her death if ſhe were not cured, or his extreme miſerie if ſhe were amended, ſéeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe therefore choſen a Phyſition for ſuch a paſſionate pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient as would reward him with large reuenewes &amp; rich poſſeſſions for his paines (yea and that which was more, yéelded her perſon into his power in part of payment, whoſe comely proportion ſurpaſſed the braueſt dames in Europe, if the ſtayne of her honeſty had not béen a blemiſh to her incomparable beawtie) he was with theſe large offers driuen into a doubtfull <hi>dilemma</hi> what he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie to <hi>Clarindas</hi> demaunde, his diſſembling with <hi>Mamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> his treacherie to <hi>Publia,</hi> his credite crackt in <hi>Italie,</hi> the loſſe of his friends, the hate of his foes, and nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the riches of <hi>Clarinda,</hi> her ſurpaſſing beawtie, and
<pb facs="tcp:6147:25"/> her promiſe to take a new courſe of life ſo aſſaulted the fort of this perplexed <hi>Pharicles,</hi> as he had almoſt yéelded a liſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eare to the melodie of this immodeſt mermaide. But as there is no hearbe ſo perillous which hath not ſome one vertue which is precious, nor no Serpent ſo infectious whiche is not indewed with ſome one qualitie which is commodious: So <hi>Pharicles</hi> although he was who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie wedded vnto vanitie, and had profeſſed himſelfe a mortall foe to vertue, béeing in the ſtate of his life ſuch a mutable machauilian, as he neither regarded friend nor faith, oath nor promiſe, if his wauering wit perſwaded him to the contrarie: yet he entered into ſuch déep conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the curtizans conditions and of the care of his owne credite, yea the feare of God and dread of man ſo daunted his conſcience, that now he ſo loathed this laſciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Lamia,</hi> as full of chollar he fel into theſe melancholike paſſions.</p>
            <p>Is it not ſufficient (O fickle and vnſtedfaſt fortune) that thou haſt drenched me in the waues of diſtreſſe, and toſſed me with the tempeſt of aduerſitie, in looſing two ſuch true and truſtie louers as by thy frowning frowardnes I haue loſt, but now to aggrauate my griefe and to repaie my care with greater calamitie, thou ſéekeſt in a ſtraunge countrie to trappe me in the ſnares of captiuitie, where I haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinſmen to comfort me, nor friendes to giue mée good aduiſe to redreſſe my miſerie: yea and that which is moſt deſpight, to entangle me with ſuch traſh, the burden wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is the greateſt plague that any mortall man can ſuſtain? O hapleſſe man, and vnhappie fortune! Why but <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> why doeſt thou ſo fondlie accuſe fortune of iniuſtice? Whereas if thou weyeſt all things in the equall ballance, ſhe ſéeketh more thy preferment than thou thy ſelfe canſt deſire. Conſider but thine owne caſe: <hi>Mamillia</hi> hath reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thée for a flatterer, and <hi>Publia</hi> accounts thée for a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, <hi>Gonzaga</hi> is thy foe, <hi>Goſtyno</hi> thine enemie, yea thy
<pb facs="tcp:6147:25"/> verie friendes are become thine aduerſaries, and all <hi>Padua</hi> deſpiſeth thée as a patterne of leawdeneſſe: what hope canſt thou haue then <hi>Pharicles</hi> to recouer thy credit where euerie man of reputation will refuſe thy companie? Doeſt thou hope to winne fame where thou art infamous, or to bée counted vertuous where thou art tried to be moſt laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuious? No, no, and therefore count fortune thy friende, who in a ſtraunge countrie hath offered thée ſuch a match, as for her parentage &amp; patrimonie, lands and liuing, birth and beautie, may deſerue to be a mate for the moſt famous Prince in the world. Yea but <hi>Pharicles,</hi> ſhe is a Curtizan, common and inconſtant. What then? Hath ſhe not promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to chaunge her vicious liking into a moſt vertuous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, the ſtate of a Curtizan into the ſtaie a of matron, &amp; to make a <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> of her forepaſſed diſhoneſtie into moſt perfect modeſtie? The palme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is moſt crooked being a twig is moſt ſtraight being a trée. What more hurtful to the heart than the buds of a date, &amp; yet no greater cordiall than the fruite: nothing ſauoureth worſe than a Panther being a whelp, yet no beaſt hath ſo ſwéet a ſmel being old: that which oft times in prime of yéeres is moſt perilous, in ripe age proueth moſt precious. So <hi>Pharicles</hi> althogh <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> hath bene a moſt graceleſſe monſter in her youth, yet ſhe may proue a moſt gracious matron in her age: yea and by how much the more ſhée hath knowne the filthineſſe of vice being a maide, by ſo much the more ſhe will embrace vertue being a wife. O <hi>Pharicles</hi> are thy ſenſes alate ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotted, and thy wit ſo inueigled, art thou ſo blinded with the vale of vice &amp; dimmed with the maſke of vanitie, that thou art become more ſottiſh than the ſenſeleſſe ſtones, or more bruite than vnreaſonable creatures. The <hi>Cryſolite</hi> being worne on the finger of an adultereſſe, ſo deteſteth the crime as it cracketh in péeces by méere inſtinct of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Vnicorne is ſuch a foe to adulterie, and ſuch a friend to chaſtitie, as hée alwaies preſerueth the one and
<pb facs="tcp:6147:26"/> killeth the other. The iuice of the Baſco leafe ſo abhorreth vnlawfull luſt, as it will not by any meanes be digeſted in the ſtomacke of a ſtrumpet. Wilt thou then <hi>Pharicles</hi> loue her whom the ſenſleſſe ſtones do loath, or deale with that perſon whom verie bruite beaſts do deteſt? No, no, <hi>Mamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> will rather both forgiue and forget thy flatterie, &amp; <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> pardon thy periurie, than they would but once haue thée conſent to companie with ſuch a graceleſſe Curtizan. And with that ſuch a ſorowfull ſadnes oppreſſed his melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like mind, as he had fallen into forepaſſed paſſions had not his friende <hi>Ferragus</hi> driuen him out of that dumpe, who comming into the chamber &amp; finding him as one hauing his heart on his halfpeny, wakened him out of his dreame with this pleaſant ſalutation.</p>
            <p>I am ſorie friend <hi>Pharicles</hi> to finde you in this dumpe, ſo I am the more gréeued becauſe I cannot coniecture the cauſe: and although it be the dutie of a friend to be copart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his friendes ſorrow, yet I dare not wiſh my ſelfe a partaker of your ſadneſſe, becauſe I ſuppoſe you are offring incenſe at the aultar of ſuch a Saint, at whoſe ſhryne you will not ſo much as once vouchſafe that I ſhould but ſing <hi>placebo.</hi> If this be the care that combers your minde, good <hi>Pharicles</hi> find ſome other time for your amorous paſſions: But if it be any ſiniſter miſhap which hath driuen you into this dumpe, either want of wealth, loſſe of friends or other frowne of Fortune, only reueale <hi>Pharicles</hi> wherein I may pleaſure thée, and I will ſupplie thy want with my weale, &amp; cure thy care with ſuch comfortable counſell as my ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wit can afoord. The faireſt ſandes <hi>Pharicles</hi> are oftimes moſt fickle. When the leafe of the Seahuluer looketh moſt gréene, then is the roote moſt withered, where the Sea breaketh with greateſt billows, there is the water ſhallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt: ſo oftimes in the faireſt ſpéech lies hid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſeſt heart, in flouriſhing wordes diſſembling déedes, and in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſhew of good wil the ſmalleſt effect of friendſhip. I can
<pb facs="tcp:6147:26"/> not <hi>Pharicles</hi> paint out my affection towards thée with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured ſpéeches, nor decipher my amitie with the penſill of flatterie, but if thou wilt account me for thy friend, &amp; ſo vſe me when thou haſt occaſion, thou ſhalt (to be ſhort) finde me farre more prodigall in performance than pratling in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and ſo I ende.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> for all theſe painted ſpéeches of his friend <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragus,</hi> durſt not wade vs farre where the foord was vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, nor reueale the cauſe of his care to his companion, leſt happily he might find a Pad in the ſtraw, and try that oftimes of the ſmootheſt talke enſueth the ſmalleſt trueth: to ſatiſfie therfore his friend and to cloake the cauſe of his care, he coyned this pretie ſcuſe.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Ferragus</hi> quoth he, it is not as you imagin the pangs of loue which haue driuen me into theſe paſſions, neither the want of wealth which haue thus wrapped me in woe? for to be intangled with loue I haue alwayes thought it a madneſſe, and to waile for wealth a point of méer folly, but it is <hi>Ferragus</hi> ſuch a miſerie, as the ſturdie Stoikes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, which were neuer moued with aduerſitie, did onlie dread to be ſtrooken with this deſpightfull dart of calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Yet amidſt this my greateſt miſfortune thy friendly affection is ſuch a comfortable collife to my crazed minde, &amp; I find ſuch comfort in thy frendſhip, as I think my lands life nor libertie halfe ſufficient to requite thy curteſie, but promiſing vnto thée the like vnfained affection, &amp; repoſing the ſtaie of my life in thy truſtineſſe, I wil vnfold vnto thée the cauſe of my diſtreſſe. The ſmoake <hi>Ferragus</hi> of <hi>Padua</hi> is more deare vnto mée than the fire of <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> and the waters of <hi>Italie</hi> doe farre more delight my taſte than the moſt delicate wines in <hi>Sicilia,</hi> and rather had I liue in a poore cottage in my natiue ſoyle, than be pampered vp in princely pallaces in a ſtrange country: Yea, it is <hi>Ferragus</hi> naturally giuen to all to chooſe rather to liue in aduerſitie amongſt their friends at home, than in proſperitie among
<pb facs="tcp:6147:27"/> ſtrangers abroad: in ſo much that no greater miſerie can be inflicted vppon any man, than to leade an exiled life in a forraine nation. This this <hi>Ferragus</hi> is the croſſe wherwith I am afflicted. For I muſt confeſſe vnto thée by the lawe of friendſhip, that through the diſpleaſure of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour I am condemned to leade my life in perpetuall exile, ſo that neither I cannot nor may not ſo much as once ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the confines of <hi>Italie,</hi> which reſtraint from my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue country is ſuch a hell to my minde, and ſuch a horrour to my conſcience, as death ſhould be thriſe welcome to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe me from baniſhment. It is not the loſſe of my landes or liuing <hi>Ferragus</hi> which ſo moleſts my mind, but the want of my faithfull and familiar friendes: for wealth may bée gotten by wiſedome, but a truſtie friend is hardly recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſo that <hi>Zeno</hi> himſelf was of this opinion, that the loſſe of friends is only to be lamented. <hi>Solon</hi> the <hi>Athenian</hi> being demaunded why he made no lawe for adulterers, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe there were none in his common wealth. Why quoth the other, but howe if there happen to be any, ſhall hée dye? No quoth <hi>Solon,</hi> hée ſhall be baniſhed, meaning that no torture, torment nor calamity is to be compared to the miſerie of exile. Woe is me then moſt miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Why <hi>Pharicles</hi> quoth <hi>Ferragus,</hi> wilt thou ſalue ſadneſſe with ſorrow, or cure care with calamitie? Wilt thou wipe away woe with wailing? or driue away theſe dumps with dith deſpaire? No no <hi>Pharicles,</hi> but to adde a ſalue to this ſore, thus I replie to thy complaint.</p>
            <p>The moſt wiſe &amp; auntient Philoſophers <hi>Pharicles</hi> haue bene of this opinion, that the worlde generally is but as one Citie: ſo that whereſoeuer a wiſe man remaineth, hée dwelleth in his owne home, for nature hath appointed the ſelfeſame lawes to euerie place, neither is ſhe contrarie to her ſelf in the furtheſt parts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. There is no place where the fire is colde, and the water hot, the aire heauie,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:27"/> and the earth light: neither hath wit or learning leſſe force in <hi>India</hi> than in <hi>Italie,</hi> and vertue is had in reputation as well in the North as in the South: ſo that <hi>Anacharſis</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>vnaquae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> patria Sapienti patria.</hi> But perhaps <hi>Pharicles</hi> thou wilt obiect thy great poſſeſſions which thou haſt loſt, and how thou wert of more account for thy birth and parentage among thine owne, than euer thou ſhalt be among ſtrangers. But I ſay <hi>Pharicles,</hi> that <hi>Coriolanus</hi> was more beloued of the <hi>Volſcians,</hi> among whome he liued in exile, than of the <hi>Romanes</hi> with whom he was a citizen. <hi>Alcibiades</hi> being baniſhed by the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> became chiefe Captaine of the armie of the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi> And <hi>Hanniball</hi> was better entertained by king <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus,</hi> than with his owne ſubiects in <hi>Carthage.</hi> And I dare ſay <hi>Pharicles,</hi> thou wert neuer more famous in <hi>Padua</hi> than thou art here in <hi>Saragoſſa:</hi> Yea, and the more to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate thy miſerie, conſider with thy ſelfe that there is no greater comfort than to haue companions in ſorrow: thou art not the firſt, nor ſhalt not be the laſt which haue béene exiled into forraine countries, yea, and ſuch to whom thou art farre inferiour both in calling and countenance. <hi>Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> the king of <hi>Thebes</hi> was driuen out of the ſelfe ſame citie which he had builded, and dyed old in exile among the <hi>Illyrians. Sarcas</hi> the king of the <hi>Moloſſians</hi> vanquiſhed by <hi>Philip</hi> king of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> ended his miſerable dayes in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Syracuſan</hi> driuen out of his countrie was conſtrayned to teache a Schoole at <hi>Corynth. Syphax</hi> the great king of <hi>Numidia</hi> ſéeing his citie taken and his wife <hi>Sophonisba</hi> in the armes of his mortall foe <hi>Maſyniſſa,</hi> and that his miſerie ſhould be a trumpet to ſounde out <hi>Scipios</hi> tryumph, ended his life both exiled and impriſoned. <hi>Perſeus</hi> the king of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> firſt diſcomfited and then depriued of his kingdome, and laſtly yéelded into the hands of <hi>Paulus Aemilius,</hi> remained long time a poore-baniſhed priſoner. Theſe <hi>Pharicles</hi> without reciting any more, are ſufficient,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:28"/> conſidering their crownes, kingdomes and Maieſties, to prooue that Fortune hath not onely offered the like miſhap to others, but alſo hath not done ſo great deſpite vnto thée as was in her power to haue done. But perhaps <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> thou wilt replie that theſe mightie Monarchs are not in the ſame predicame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for they were baniſhed their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes by open enimies, and thou thy countrie by ſuppoſed friendes: they were exiled by ſiniſter enmitie of forreine foes, and thou by the ſecrete enuie of flattering compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſo that the ſelfe ſame citizens who were bound vnto thy father for his prudent gouernement being their magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and to thée for thy liberalitie maintaining their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, haue repayed thy curteſie with moſt ingratefull crueltie. To which I anſwere, that <hi>Theſeus</hi> whoſe famous actes are ſo blazed abroade through all the world, was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out of <hi>Athens</hi> by the ſelfe ſame citizens which he him ſelfe had placed, and dyed an olde baniſhed man in <hi>Tyrus. Solon</hi> who gouerned his citizens with moſt golden lawes, was notwithſtanding exiled by them into <hi>Cyprus.</hi> The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> béeing bounde nor beholding to no man ſo much as vnto <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> for all his prudent policie in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning the citie conſtrained him to leade his life in exile. The <hi>Romanes</hi> ſuffered <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> the firſt which defended them from ſo many perils, moſt miſerablie to die in <hi>Lyntermum.</hi> And the ſecond <hi>Scipio</hi> for all that he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued <hi>Carthage</hi> and <hi>Numantia</hi> which refuſed to become tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butaries to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> found in <hi>Rome</hi> a murtherer but not a reuenger. Ingratitude <hi>Pharicles,</hi> is the moſt aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent miſchiefe which raigneth among the people, béeing ſo déepelie rooted that it doth not as all other things waxe olde, but waxeth daily more freſh, ſo that the flower falling there followeth great ſtore of fruite. And further <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> for the loſſe of thy friendes I confeſſe it is the greateſt cauſe of care, and yet oftimes the faireſt face hath the fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt heart, and the ſwéeteſt wordes the ſowreſt déedes, thou
<pb facs="tcp:6147:28"/> haſt therfore the meanes by this miſhap to iudge betwéene the faithfull and fained friende: for as the toucheſtone tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the golde, ſo aduerſitie prooueth friends. Had not <hi>Ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes</hi> fallen into his extreme phrenſie, he had neuer tried the ſacred faith of <hi>Pilades:</hi> and if the warres of the <hi>Lapy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans</hi> had not lighted vppon <hi>Perithous,</hi> hée mighte haue thought himſelfe to haue had many friendes, whereas hée found none but one, the famous <hi>Theſeus. Eurialus</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer prooued the conſtancie of <hi>Nyſus,</hi> had he not fallen into the hands of the ſouldiers of <hi>Turnus.</hi> Sith then <hi>(Pharicles)</hi> fortune hath but giuen thée occaſion to trie thy friendes, count it not for ſuch a miſerie. For if all thy companions and kinſemen in <hi>Padua</hi> prooue but clawbackes, aſſure thy ſelfe thou haſt ſuch a faithfull friend héere in <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> as counts thy miſhap his miſfortune, and thy care his owne calamitie: yea, if eyther my counſell may comfort thy cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed minde, or my wealth reléeue thy want, trie and then truſt: and if thou findeſt me troathleſſe, the gods reward my trecherie with moſt vile and extreme miſerie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> hearing the great proteſtations of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friende <hi>Ferragus,</hi> and perceiuing that his friendſhip was conſtant and not counterfeite, not onelie tolde him that this report of his exile was but a tale to trie his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, but alſo reuealed vnto him the verie troath of his departure from <hi>Italie:</hi> what hap had paſſed betwéene him and <hi>Mamillia,</hi> and alſo the letter of <hi>Clarinda:</hi> which when <hi>Ferragus</hi> ſawe, he both gaue him counſell to auoide ſuch a common Curtizan, and further to driue him out of thoſe dumps, caried him to his fathers houſe to paſſe away the time in parle.</p>
            <p>Where, aſſoone as they came, they found <hi>Signor Farneſſe</hi> in the garden deuiſing pleaſantlie with diuerſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, amongſt whome was <hi>Madam Gambara</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Saldena,</hi> and the yong Ladie <hi>Modeſta:</hi> who ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Pharicles,</hi> were verie glad of his ſo happie arriuall,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:29"/> that now they might trie what was in the Gentleman, ſith he was the man that bare the bell for courtly bringing vp throughout all <hi>Sicillia.</hi> But <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſéeing them in earneſt talke, thought they had béene canuaſing of ſome ſerious and ſecret matter, and not being verie well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Marqueſſe, knewe it paſt maners to come to counſell before he were called, began to withdraw himſelfe out of the garden had not <hi>Signor Farneſſe</hi> recald him on this wiſe.</p>
            <p>What Maſter <hi>Pharicles</hi> quoth he, is it the faſhion in <hi>Padua</hi> to be ſo ſtrange with your friendes, knowing that you are not ſo ſoone come as welcome, nor ſo haſtilie arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as hartilie deſired of all the companie? I ſpeake alſo for my Ladie <hi>Gambara</hi> and <hi>Madam Modeſta,</hi> eſpeciallie at this time, ſince there is ſuch a paſſing doubtfull matter in queſtion as all our cunning cannot decide. Wee knowing therefore that you trauellers cannot be without experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and eſpeciallie in ſuch louing caſes, will referre our whole controuerſie, if the Marqueſſe and my Ladie <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta</hi> be content, to your ſkilfull determination, and in my opinion we ſhall haue hapt on a verie fit iudge.</p>
            <p>Syr quoth he, I both knowe and finde my ſelfe far more welcome to your houſe than my ſmall deſerts can merite: yet not willing to ſtraine ſo much vpon your courteſie, to be ſo bolde to intrude my ſelfe into companie where both my betters are in preſence and the talke vtterly vnknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, leaſt they might iudge I had eyther ſmall nurture or leſſe manners. But ſince it hath pleaſed my Lady the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe and <hi>Madam Modeſta</hi> (to whome I thinke my ſelfe greatlie bound that their Ladyſhips will vouchſafe of ſuch a ſimple Gentleman) to admit mée for a hearer of ſuch a doubtfull diſcourſe: yet Syr I accept not the conditions, for if the caſe be ſo intricate as neyther your olde yeres nor great experience can decide, it were farre vnfit for me to ſet downe a ſentence whoſe age and ſkill is yet in the bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:29"/> and eſpeciallie in ſuch an honorable companie where either their countenance or calling may force me ſpeake eyther for feare or fauour.</p>
            <p>No Maſter <hi>Pharicles</hi> (quoth the Marqueſſe) although I haue ſuch opinion both of your wit and ſkill as I durſt in a more weightie matter than this admit you for a iudge: yet ſince you are a partie touched within the compaſſe of the commiſſion, I will not tie my ſelfe ſo ſtraightlie to your verdit, as eyther your yea or nay ſhall ſtand for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnleſſe you bring the ſoundeſt reaſon.</p>
            <p>Our queſtion is Maſter <hi>Pharicles</hi> whether the man or the woman be more conſtant or loyall in loue. The cauſe of our controuerſie aroſe about certaine vaine verſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by an iniurious Gentleman héere in <hi>Saràgoſſa,</hi> who with deſpightfull taunts hath abuſed the Gentlewomen of <hi>Sicillia,</hi> moſt péeuiſhlie deſcribing their apparell, and preſumptuouſlie decyphering their nature. But leauing him to his follie, you know both the caſe and the cauſe, and therefore let vs heare your opinion.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <head>The copie of the verſes.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SInce Ladie milde (too baſe in aray) hath liude as an exile,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>None of account but ſtout: if plaine? ſtale ſlut not a courtreſſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dames nowadayes? fie none: if not new guiſed in all points</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fancies fine, fawſt with conceits, quick wits verie wilie.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Words of a Saint, but deedes geſſe how, fainde faith to deceiue men.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Courtſies coy, no vale but a vaunt trickt vp like a Tuſcan.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paced in print, braue loftie lookes, not vſde with the veſtals.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In hearts too glorious, not a glaunce but fit for an Empreſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As mindes moſt valorous, ſo ſtrange in aray: mary ſtately.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vp fro the waſt like a man, new guiſe to be caſde in a dublet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Downe to the foote (perhaps like a maid) but hoſde to the kneeſtead.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some cloſe breetcht to the crotch for cold, tuſh; peace; tis a ſhame Syr.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heares by birth as blacke as Iet, what? art can amend them.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:6147:30"/>A perywig frounſt faſt to the frunt, or curld with a bodkin.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hats fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fraunce thicke pearld for pride, and plumde like a peacocke.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ruffes of a Syſe, ſtiffe ſtarcht to the necke, of Lawne; mary lawleſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gownes of ſilke, why thoſe be too bad? ſide, wide with a witneſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Small and gent I'the waſt, but backs as broade as a Burgeſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Needeleſſe noughts, as criſps, and ſcarphes worne Alla Moriſco.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fumde with ſweetes, as ſweete as chaſt, no want but abundance.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> hauing read theſe verſes ſmiling at the vaine of the Gentleman, found his minde clogged with a double care. For to praiſe men for their loyaltie he found his own conſcience a iuſt accuſer of their inconſtancie, to condemne women for their fickleneſſe he ſawe <hi>Mamillia</hi> and <hi>Publia</hi> two preſidents of perfect affection: yet for faſhion ſake he made this or ſuch like aunſwere.</p>
            <p>If credite Madame may bée giuen to thoſe auntient authors, whoſe wit, wiſedome and learning hath ſhrined them vp in the famous temple of immortalitie, your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund is anſwered, and the queſtion eaſily decided. For <hi>Socrates, Plato,</hi> yea and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelfe, who ſpent all their time in ſearching out the ſecret nature of all things, aſſigned this as a particular qualitie appertaining to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mankinde, namely, to be fickle and inconſtant, alledging this Aſtronomicall reaſon, that <hi>Luna</hi> a feminine and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Planet hath ſuch predominant power in the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of their complexion becauſe they be phlegmatike, that of neceſſitie they muſt be fickle, mutable and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, whereas Choller, wherewith men do abound, is contrarie, and therefore by conſequence ſtable, firme and without change: ſo that by how much the more the bodie is Phlegmatike, by ſo much the more the minde is fickle: and where the bodie is moſt Chollerick, there the mind is moſt conſtant. To leaue theſe rules of Aſtronomie, and to come to humane reaſon, <hi>Pindarus, Homer, Heſiodus, Ennius, Virgil, Martiall, Propertius,</hi> and many authors
<pb facs="tcp:6147:30"/> more, whoſe pithie and golden ſentences haue in all ages béene holden as diuine Oracles, haue in all their writings with one conſent auerred, that the naturall diſpoſition of women is framed of contraries: now liking, now loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, delighting this, and now againe deſpiſing the ſame: louing and hating: yea laughing &amp; wéeping, and all with one winde: ſo that it is their naturall conſtitution in this one propertie to be like the <hi>Polipe:</hi> that if it happen ſome one woman not to be variable, it is not ſo becauſe it is her nature, but becauſe ſhée hath amended her fault by nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For the confirmation of the former premiſſes, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, it is not neceſſarie to inferre examples, ſith there is none héere but could report infinite hiſtories of ſuch diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling dames as haue falſified their faith to their louers, whereas the conſtancie of men is ſuch, that neither hath any authors found it faultie, neither can as I coniecture, if you ſpeake as you thinke, your conſcience condemne them as guiltie, ſo that to confirme the loyaltie of men were as much as to proue that which is not denyed.</p>
            <p>How ſay you to this quoth <hi>Signor Farneſe,</hi> hath not <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles</hi> aunſwered you fully to your queſtion? is not nowe my former reaſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed and yours vtterly infringed?</p>
            <p>Tuſh ſyr quoth the Marqueſſe, one tale is alwayes good vntil another is heard, but all this winde ſhakes no corne, neither is the defendant ouerthrowen at the fiſt plea of the plaintife. The more gliſtring the ſkinne of the Serpent is, the more infectious: where the billowes be greateſt, there the water is ſhalloweſt: the rotten wall hath the moſt néed of painting, and the falſeſt tale hath néede of the faireſt toung: where the greateſt ſhowe of eloquence is, there is the ſmalleſt effect of troth. But to your ſurmiſed Sophiſtrie thus I aunſwere maſter <hi>Pharicles,</hi> that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you build your reaſons vppon the credit of auncient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, I will lay my foundation vppon the ſame rocke, and ſo thruſt you on the boſome with your owne launce.
<pb facs="tcp:6147:31"/> For as for <hi>Socrates, Plato,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> whom you alleage as ratifiers of your former reaſons, I ſay that both they and others who farre ſurpaſſe them in the ſacred ſkill of Aſtronomie, affirme (as you ſay) that the naturall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of women is Phlegme, and of men Choller, which if you conſider with indifferent iudgement, prooueth vs truſtie and you trothleſſe, vs conſtant and you variable, vs loyall vnder <hi>Luna,</hi> and you mutable vnder <hi>Mars.</hi> For the Phlegmatike complexion is cold and moiſt, vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the flaming heate of voluptuous deſires, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating of the nature of water, which ſo cooleth and quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the fire of fancie, as hauing once fixed the minde, it reſiſteth with the colde moiſture the frying heate of fond and fickle affection, whereas the Chollerike conſtitution is hote &amp; drie, ſoone ſet on fire and ſoone out, eaſily inflamed and as eaſily quenched, readie to be ſcorched with the leaſt heate of beawtie, being of the nature of fire which is the moſt light and mouing Element of all, fiering at the firſt ſight, and yet ſo dry as it hath no continuance, being verie violent and little permanent. And though <hi>Luna</hi> is predominant in our complexion, yet <hi>Mercurie</hi> is Lorde of your conſtitution, being in his conſtellation fléeting, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, variable, trecherous, trothleſſe, and delighting in change: ſo that it is not ſo common as true, the nature of men is deſirous of noueltie. And as touching <hi>Heſiodus, Homer, Virgil</hi> and others, I aunſwere that euill will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpoke well, and that <hi>Martiall</hi> &amp; the reſt of his cogging companions, becauſe they found ſome one halting, they wil condemne all for créeples, thinking by diſcrediting others vniuſtly to make themſelues famous, and condemning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that whereof they themſelues are chiefely to be accuſed. Who fixeth his fancie, and then changeth affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? who promiſeth loue and perfourmeth hate? who now liketh and within a moment lotheth? who wooeth one and ſueth to another? who loyall in his lippes and a lyer in
<pb facs="tcp:6147:31"/> his heart? but onelie men, and yet they muſt bée conſtant. As for the infinit examples you could inferre maſter <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles</hi> to proue the diſloialtie of women, you do well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale them becauſe you cannot reueale them: for it is hard to reape corne where no ſéed was ſowne, to gather grapes of a barraine vine, to pull haire from a balde mans head, or to bring examples of womens diſloyaltie which neuer committed ſuche trothleſſe treacherie. But as for your changing champio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which challenge to defend your crazed conſtancie, howe truſtie was <hi>Theſeus</hi> to poore <hi>Ariadne? Demophoon</hi> diſſembled with <hi>Phillis,</hi> and yet ſhe died con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. <hi>Aeneas</hi> a verie ſtragler, yet <hi>Dido</hi> neuer founde hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. <hi>Iaſon</hi> without faith, and yet <hi>Medea</hi> neuer fléeting. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> a counterfait Camelion, &amp; yet <hi>Oenone</hi> a truſtie Turtle. <hi>Vliſſes</hi> variable, and <hi>Penelope</hi> moſt conſtant. Yea, <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> infinit examples might be brought which would bréed our credite and your infamie, if time as well as matter would permit mée. So that the inconſtancie of ſuch muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Mercurialiſtes,</hi> and courtly copeſmates as you bée, is growne to ſuch a cuſtom, that flatterie is no fault, &amp; varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is rather imbraced as a vertue than reiected as a vice. In fine, the bloſſome of diſloyaltie hath brought foorth ſuch faithleſſe fruite in your mutable minds, as he that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant is counted a calfe, and he that cannot diſſemble can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not liue.</p>
            <p>How now <hi>Signor Farneſe,</hi> quoth the lady <hi>Modeſta,</hi> hath not the Marqueſſe giuen <hi>Pharicles</hi> a cake of the ſame dow, yea, hath ſhée not better defended the Fort than hée could aſſault it? Now you ſée <hi>Pharicles</hi> counterfait coine will go for no paiment, and his rampier too weake to withſtand her force, and his reaſon not ſo ſtrong but they are clearely infringed.</p>
            <p>In troth, quoth <hi>Farneſe,</hi> my Ladie Marqueſſe hath plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the valiant champion, and hath put in ſo perfect a plea to defend her clients cauſe, that if I haue euer any caſe in the
<pb facs="tcp:6147:32"/> Court, ſhe ſhall be my counſeller.</p>
            <p>Ieſt how you pleaſe, quoth the Marqueſſe, I am ſure mine aduerſarie will confeſſe, that howſoeuer I faltred in my tale, I failed not in the truth.</p>
            <p>Indéed Madame, quoth <hi>Pharicles,</hi> it is a fowle byrd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files the owne neaſt, and yet I will ſay my conſcience, that for conſtancie men are farre more to be appeached of want than women to be condemned for defect, and therefore who ſoeuer made the forepaſſed verſes, was both vniuſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious: yea, the railing of <hi>Mantuan</hi> in his Eglogs, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming of <hi>Euripides</hi> in his Tragedies, the tants of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall,</hi> and priuie quippes of <hi>Propertius,</hi> are more of courſe than cauſe, and rather inforced by rage than inferred by reaſon.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Pharicles</hi> quoth <hi>Signor Ferneſe,</hi> I ſée thou canſt hold a candle before the diuel, and that you can ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly runne a point of Deſcant, that be the plaine ſong neuer ſo ſimple thou canſt quauer to pleaſe both parts. You were euen now a condemner of womens varietie, and are you now an accuſer of mens inconſtancie? If you be ſo variable in your verdit, we wil thinke that either you ſpeak fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie without ſkill or as a flatterer to pleaſe women. But indéede it is daungerous for him to ſpeake ill of an Iriſh kearne that is offering a Cowe to Saint Patricke, and as perillous for a man to blaſpheme women that is knée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the ſhrine of <hi>Venus:</hi> ſith then you are in the ſame caſe we will take your deuotion for a ſufficient excuſe. In the meane time if it pleaſe my Ladie the Marqueſſe wée will go to dinner, and there ende our diſcourſe more at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>Content, quoth the Marqueſſe, and with that they went to dinner, where <hi>Pharicles</hi> behaued himſelfe ſo wittily, as they ſtood in doubt whether his wit, beautie, or behauiour deſerued greater commendations.</p>
            <p>Well, dinner being ended, <hi>Pharicles</hi> hauing the ſpurres
<pb facs="tcp:6147:32"/> in his ſide, alledging vrgent cauſe of his ſo haſtly departure tooke his leaue of the Marqueſſe, and the reſt of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and giuing great thanks to <hi>Signor Ferneſe</hi> for his good cheare, hyed him home in haſte to his chamber. Where ſéeing the letter of <hi>Clarynda,</hi> a gaſtly obiect to his gazing eyes, willing to returne an anſwere that ſhe might not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him of diſcurteſie, tooke Penne and Inke and wrote a letter to this effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Pharicles to Clarynda, health.</head>
                  <p>IT is hard <hi>Clarynda</hi> for him which commeth within the reach of a Crocodile to eſcape without daunger, &amp; it is as impoſſible to ſée the Cockatrice &amp; not be infected. Who ſo toucheth the <hi>Torpedo</hi> muſt néeds be charmed, and he that handleth a Scorpion cannot but be ſtriken: tis not poſſible to medle with pitch &amp; haue clean hands, nor to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a ſtrumpet &amp; haue a good name. This conſidered <hi>Clarynda,</hi> I being a ſtranger of <hi>Italie,</hi> whoſe life &amp; liuing is more noted than if I were a citizen in <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> counting my honeſt behauiour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefeſt ſtay of my vnknowen ſtate, feared leaſt thy maides arriuall to my lodging ſhould bée hurtfull to my countenance, or preiudicial to my credit. If then I gréeued to haue my parler combred with the maid, you may wel think I were loth to haue my perſon trobled with the Miſtreſſe. For ſilence &amp; modeſtie <hi>Clarynda</hi> which you ſay the force of my loue conſtrained you to paſſe, I am ſure you ſhooke hands with modeſtie, and ſtrained curteſie
<pb facs="tcp:6147:33"/> with ſilence long before you knewe me for <hi>Pharicles,</hi> or I you for a Curtizan. Indéed you haue brought forth fit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to confirme your conſequent, &amp; I allow them. For ſilent <hi>Sapho</hi> was a riming monſter of lecherie, &amp; you a roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Miſtreſſe in bawdrie: Modeſt <hi>Phedra</hi> was a moſt ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous harlot, and you a moſt infectious ſtrumpet: ſo that your compariſons hold very well, ſith the equalitie of your maners makes them not odious. Doeſt thou think <hi>Clarin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> that I am ſo careleſſe in choice as to chooſe ſuch filthie chaffre, or ſo ſoone allured as to be in loue with ſuch traſh? No, no, I haue ſuch care to my credit and ſuch regard to my calling, ſuch reſpect to my birth, and ſuch feare to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame my pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, as I meane not to match with a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe if ſhe be not honeſt, much leſſe then linke my ſelfe to a laſciuious <hi>Lais</hi> whoſe honeſtie ſhall be a pray to euery ſtraggling ſtranger. Shall I beate the buſh and others get the byrdes? Shall I hold the net and others catch the fiſh? yea, ſhall euery man get his fee of the Deare, and I get nothing but the hornes? No I will firſt faſt before I taſte of ſuch a diſh as wil turne me to ſo great diſpleaſure. But you reply that the <hi>Mirabolanes</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> are perilous in the bud &amp; pretious in the fruite, that the wine is ſower in the preſſe and yet ſwéet in the Caſke, that ſhe which is vicious in her youth may be vertuous in her age: I graunt indéede it may be, but it is hard to bring the <hi>poſſe</hi> into <hi>eſſe.</hi> For the barking whelp proues alwayes a byting dog, the yong Frie will proue old Frogges: where the bloſſome is venemous, there the fruite muſt néedes be infectious, where vice is embraced in youth, there commonly vertue is reiected in age: yea, tis a thing moſt commonly ſéene, that a yong whoore prooues alwayes an olde Bawde. As for <hi>Rodhope</hi> the curtizan of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Phyrne</hi> the ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of <hi>Athens,</hi> whome you bring in as examples of this ſtrange <hi>Metamorphoſis,</hi> I anſwere, that their particular conuerſion inferreth no generall concluſion. For though
<pb facs="tcp:6147:33"/> 
                     <hi>Rodhope</hi> of a vicious maiden became a vertuous matron, and though <hi>Phryne</hi> of a laſciuious <hi>Lamia</hi> became a loyall <hi>Lucretia,</hi> yet it followes not that you ſhould of a ſtragling harlot become a ſtaied huſwife: for we ſée it hardlie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe that a yoong diuell proues an old Saint. But put caſe you would performe as much as you promiſe, and make a change of your chaffre with better ware, of your fléeting affection with fixed fancie, that your forepaſſed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſtie would turne to perfect conſtancie, that of a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Corynna</hi> you would become a carefull <hi>Cornelia:</hi> yet I cannot recall the ſtone alreadie caſt, withhold the ſtroake alreadie ſtroken, nor reclaime affection, fancie being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie fixed. I am <hi>Clarynda,</hi> to put thée out of doubt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troathed to a yoong Gentlewoman in <hi>Padua,</hi> who in beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wealth and honeſtie, is inferiour to none in all <hi>Italie,</hi> and wouldeſt thou then haue me leaue the fine Partridge to praie on a carrion Kyte, to refuſe the Hare and hunt at the Hedgehog, to falſifie my faith to a moſt honeſt &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull dame, and plight my troth to a laſciuious and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſtrumpet? No <hi>Clarynda,</hi> thou heareſt I cannot though I would, and if I could I will not, and ſo farewell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Not thine if he could, Pharicles.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> hauing thus finiſhed his letter, ſent it by his Page to <hi>Clarynda,</hi> who receiuing it hartily and rewarding the Page bountifully, went haſtily into her cloſet, where vnripping y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeales ſhe found not a preſeruatiue, but a poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; not newes to encreaſe her ioy, but to bréed her annoy; not louing lines as from a friend, but a quipping letter as from a foe; not a comfortiue to lengthen her life, but a cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue to ſhorten her dayes: yea, ſhe found the letter ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to her former expectation, that nowe falling into a deſperate minde, ſhe turned her feruent loue into extreme
<pb facs="tcp:6147:34"/> hate, her déep delight into deadly deſpite, as now her chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt care and induſtrie was to reuenge her broyling rage vppon guiltleſſe <hi>Pharicles,</hi> which ſhe ſpéedily performed on this wiſe.</p>
            <p>It happened that vpon the ſame day wherein ſhée recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Letter, <hi>Signor Farneſe</hi> and the reſt of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> were aſſembled togither in the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hall, to conſult of matters as concerning the ſtate of their Citie, whither <hi>Clarynda</hi> came, and there openly accuſed <hi>Pharicles</hi> to be a Spie, and that his remaining in <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> was to ſée where the Citie was weakeſt, and that hée had conferred with her how and when hée might moſt conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently betraie it: and that ſhée regarding more the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of her country than the loue of a ſtranger, thought good to reueale the matter ſpéedilie, that they might the better preuent ſuch a miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>The Magiſtrates giuing credit to <hi>Clarynda,</hi> and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Pharicles</hi> had a peſtilent wit for ſuche a purpoſe, ſent the officers to apprehend him, who finding him in his lodging, made him greatly aſtoniſhed when hée knew the cauſe of their comming, yet he made them good cheare and went the more willingly, becauſe hée felte his conſcience cleare from anie ſuche cryme as might be obiected againſt him. <hi>Pharicles</hi> being come into the common Hall, <hi>Signor Farneſe</hi> ſaluted him on this maner.</p>
            <p>I ſée maſter <hi>Pharicles,</hi> quoth he, tis hard to iudge the trée by the leaues, to chooſe the ſtone by his outward hew, cloth by his colour, and a man by his faire wordes, for none ſo faire as the Panther, and yet none ſo rauenous, the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke hath moſte gliſtering feathers and yet moſt ouglie féete, the barren leafe is moſt delightfull to be ſéene &amp; moſt deadly to be taſted, the Chriſolite pleaſeth the eye and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth the ſtomack, yea, that which oft times ſéemeth moſt precious, prooueth moſt perilous, for trecherie hath a more glozing ſhewe than troth, and flatterie diſplaies a brauer
<pb facs="tcp:6147:34"/> flag than faith: ſubtill <hi>Synon</hi> could tell a finer tale than ſimple <hi>Brennus,</hi> and deceitfull <hi>Vliſſes</hi> had a fairer tongue than faithfull <hi>Aiax:</hi> ſo <hi>Pharicles</hi> I perceiue, the more wit thou haſt, the more to be ſuſpected, and thy faireſt ſpéech infers the fouleſt mind, thy curteſie here in <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> hath bene but a cloake for thy trecherie. Well <hi>Pharicles,</hi> haue I brought vp a birde to picke out mine owne eyes? haue I hatched vp the egge that wil proue a Cockatrice? yea, haue I cheriſhed thée as a friend, which wouldeſt murther mée as a foe? haue I ſought to bréed thy credit and thou deuiſed my deſtruction? haue (I ſay) I ſought thy bliſſe and thou my bale? I thy weale and thou my woe? haue our citizens here in <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> honored thée as thy friends, and thou ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred them as thine enemies? well, the greater their loue was counting thée curteous, the greater plague will they inflict vpon thée finding thée trecherous? The <hi>Troyans</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhewed more fauour to any than to <hi>Synon,</hi> who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward betraied the citie. Who ſo welcome into <hi>Carthage</hi> as <hi>Aeneas,</hi> and yet he repaied them with ingratitude: the <hi>Babylonians</hi> neuer truſted any better than <hi>Zopyrus</hi> and he moſte traiterouſly betraied them to <hi>Darius:</hi> and ſhall not their miſhaps learne vs to beware? yes <hi>Pharicles,</hi> we will preuent our daunger with heaping coales vpon thy head. The cauſe of theſe my ſpéeches I néed not rehearſe, becauſe thine owne conſcience condemnes thée as guilty. Thou art accuſed here <hi>Pharicles</hi> by <hi>Clarinda</hi> to be a ſpy, yea, thou haſt fought ſecretly to betray the citie into the hands of the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> thy countrimen, &amp; vppon this ſhe hath here ſolemnely taken her oath. And beſides this I giue thée to vnderſtand, that thou canſt not by the Statutes of <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> pleade for thy ſelfe being a ſtraunger if thou be appeached of treaſon, neither will it ſerue thee to haue a teſtimoniall from thy countrie, ſith we know that the <hi>Italians</hi> are confederate to thy treacherie, ſo that by the lawe this day thou ſhouldeſt die, ſince thy accuſer hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed the complaint with her
<pb facs="tcp:6147:35"/> corporall oath: yet I will ſtand ſo much thy friend as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue thée for fortie daies, to ſée what will fall betwéen the cup and the lip, and with that he ſate downe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharicles</hi> amazed with this trecherous accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this graceleſſe Curtizan, was ſo drenched in diſtreſſe, and ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſorrow to ſée that he might not acquite himſelfe with vnfolding this deuiſed knauerie, that if verie courage had not bene a conſerue to comfort his care, he had there with preſent death ended this diſſention. But chearing himſelfe vp as well as he could, he went to the Iailors houſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vttering anie one word, vntill there being ſolitary by himſelfe he fell into theſe extremities.</p>
            <p>It is more griefe (quoth he) to the ſilly Lambe to lie lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring in the gripe of the Tygre, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſently to be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and he which is caſt into the Lyons denne wiſheth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be torne in péeces than to liue in feare of future tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: yea, I try by experience that to die cannot be full of care, becauſe death cutteth off all occaſions of ſorrow, but to liue &amp; yet euerie day to looke to die, of all woes is the moſt helliſh miſery: for the ſtinging feare to die, and the gréedy deſire to liue make ſuch a cruell combat in the mind of the condemned perſon, as no kinde of torture (how euer ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible) is to be compared to that when as one lingereth in life without any hope at all to liue. And what then <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> is there anie miſhap ſo miſerable which thou haſt not merited, or any death ſo deſpitefull, which thou haſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued? No, were thy torment thriſe more terrible, it were not halfe ſufficient to repay thy trecherie: thy diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling with <hi>Mamillia,</hi> and thy falſhood with <hi>Publia,</hi> vnleſſe the Gods be too vniuſt, cannot eſcape without vengeance. Why but do the Gods fret more at my flatterie than they fumed at others follie? <hi>Aeneas</hi> diſſembled with <hi>Dido,</hi> and yet was proſperous: <hi>Theſeus</hi> deceiued <hi>Ariadne,</hi> and yet happie: <hi>Paris</hi> contemned <hi>Oenone,</hi> and yet the Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured his enterpriſe in gaining <hi>Helena: Iaſon</hi> was vniuſt
<pb facs="tcp:6147:35"/> to <hi>Medea,</hi> and yet returned ſafe to <hi>Greece.</hi> Yea, but <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> they were not ſo wilfull as thou wert, to ſet thy ſelfe oppoſite both to the Gods and Fortune, they tooke time while time was, and held ope the poake when the Pigge was offered. For <hi>Aeneas</hi> though he forſooke <hi>Dido,</hi> he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bayed the Gods in taking <hi>Lauinia,</hi> and <hi>Theſeus</hi> though he reiected <hi>Ariadne,</hi> yet he tooke the dame which Fortune aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him and that was <hi>Phedra:</hi> But <hi>Pharicles</hi> thou haſt committed double offence, not onely in forſaking thy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed louers, but alſo in reiecting her whome Fortune proffered thée, and that was <hi>Clarinda.</hi> Oh <hi>Pharicles</hi> bée content with thy ſtate, and let patience be the remedie to aſſwage this thy intollerable maladie: for better hadſt thou farre turne the ſtone with <hi>Syſiphus,</hi> and be torne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the whéele with <hi>Ixion,</hi> than be coupled with ſuch a common Curtizan: yea, ere it be long thou wouldeſt thinke thy ſelfe happie to ſuffer ten thouſand deathes to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from her companie: for as there is no payne to bee compared to the ſtinging of an Aſpick, ſo there is no ſuch plague as to be troubled with a ſtrumpet. And with that ſuch ſorrow ſurcharged his moleſted minde, as he was not able to vtter any more complaints.</p>
            <p>While thus <hi>Pharicles</hi> lay languiſhing in diſpaire, there was a Merchant of <hi>Padua</hi> named <hi>Signor Rhamberto,</hi> who being newly arriued in <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> and hearing of the late miſhap of <hi>Pharicles,</hi> durſt not bewray what countreyman he was for feare of further daunger, but conueyed himſelfe out of <hi>Sicillia</hi> with as much ſpéede as might be, and being come to <hi>Padua,</hi> thought good to ſhewe <hi>Signor Gonzaga</hi> in what diſtreſſe <hi>Pharicles</hi> lay in <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> but being come to the houſe, he found the Gentleman at the point of death, and all the Senatours of <hi>Padua</hi> lamenting the extremitie of his ſickeneſſe, and therefore ſate downe among the reſt and helde his peace, when as <hi>Gonzaga</hi> ſcarſe able to vtter one worde for weakeneſſe, taking his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:6147:36"/> 
               <hi>Mamillia</hi> by the hande, gaue her this fatherlie aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement.</p>
            <p>As daughter, quoth he, the man which hath the ſtone <hi>Agathes</hi> about him is ſurely defenced againſt aduerſitie, ſo he which is forewarned by counſell if he be wiſe, is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently armed againſt future miſhap and miſerie. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Mamillia</hi> hauing ſuch fatherly affection and care for thy future ſtate as duetie bindes mée by inſtinct of nature, ſeeing I lye looking euerie minute when my ſillie ſoule ſhall leaue my carefull carckaſſe, thought good to giue thée this fatherly farewell, as the onely treaſure which I charge thée by the lawe of duetie moſt carefully to kéepe.</p>
            <p>Virginitie <hi>Mamillia,</hi> is ſuch a precious Iewell to a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Gentlewoman, as <hi>Euphronia</hi> being demaunded of one of her ſuters what dowrie ſhée had to the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her marriage, aunſwered, ſuch wealth as coulde not be valued, for (quoth ſhée) I am a virgine: meaning, that no wealth doeth ſo enrich a mayden, nor no dowrie, of what price ſo euer ſo adorne a Damſell, as to be renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for inuiolable virginitie. Sith then <hi>Mamillia</hi> it ought to be more deare than life, and more eſtéemed than wealth, as thou haſt béene carefull in my dayes to keepe it without ſpot and thereby haſt reaped renowne, ſo I charge thée after my death to be as charie of ſuch precious chaffer, leaſt thy ſorepaſſed fame turne to thy greater diſcredit. Yea <hi>Mamillia</hi> and when the time commeth that thou meaneſt to match thy ſelfe in Marriage, beſtowe not that careleſlie in one moment which thou haſt kept carefully all thy life, but looke before thou leape, trie before thou truſt, haſt makes waſt, hotte loue ſoone colde, and then too late com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth repentance: contemne not the counſell of thy friends, nor reiect not the aduiſe of thy kinſemen, preferre not thine own wit before the wiſedome of thine Aunceſtours, nor leane not to wilfulneſſe leaſt had I wiſt come too late. Be not ſecure leaſt want of care procure thy calamitie,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:36"/> nor be not too carefull leaſt penſiue thought oppreſſe thée with miſerie. Build not thy loue vpon the outward ſhape of beautie, leaſt thou trie thy foundation was laide on the fickle ſands of vanitie. Vow not thy ſelfe to his wealth whome thou meaneſt to loue, nor wed not thy ſelfe to his wit, but let thy fanſie growe ſo farre as thou heareſt the report of his vertue. Chooſe not by the eye <hi>Mamillia,</hi> but by the eare, and yet be not delighted with his faire words, leaſt if thou takeſt pleaſure in hearing the Syrens ſing, thou daſh thy ſhip againſt moſt dangerous rockes. I néede not I hope <hi>Mamillia</hi> ſtand ſo much vppon theſe points, for a burnt childe will dread the fire, and thou haſt béene too ſore canuaſed in the nettes, to be allured to the ſcrap, thou haſt béene too ſore ſowſed in the waues to venter in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen foorde, and the treacherie of <hi>Pharicles</hi> is ſufficient to cauſe thée take héede of others flatterie. Well <hi>Mamillia,</hi> after thou haſt choſen howſoeuer thy choice be, ſéeke to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thy huſband with loue, and obey him with reuerence, be not too ſad leaſt he thinke thou art ſollempe, nor too light leaſt he condemne thée of leaudneſſe, and aboue all haue a regard to thy good name, and a care to the ſafe kéeping of thy honour. Let not too much familiaritie bréede any ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor ſhewe no ſuch countenance as may giue occaſion of miſtruſt, but ſo behaue thy ſelfe as thou maiſt be a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite to thy huſband, and a comfort to thy friendes. Vpon theſe conſiderations <hi>Mamillia</hi> I haue left thée by my laſt will and teſtament onely heire and ſole executor of all my landes and moueables, yet with this prouiſo, that if thou marrie with faithleſſe <hi>Pharicles,</hi> that then thou ſhalt be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inherited of all my goods and lands, and that the Citie of <hi>Padua</hi> ſhal as mine heire enter into all my poſſeſſions, and for the performance of my will, I leaue the whole Senate as ſuperuiſors. <hi>Gonzaga</hi> had ſcarſelie ſpoken theſe laſt words, but his breath was ſo ſhort that he could ſpeake no longer, and within thrée houres after he departed, leauing
<pb facs="tcp:6147:37"/> 
               <hi>Mamillia</hi> a ſorrowfull child for the loſſe of ſo good a Father.</p>
            <p>Well, after that <hi>Mamillia</hi> had by the ſpace of a wéeke worne her mourning wéede, and the dayly reſort of her friends had ſomething redreſſed her ſorrow, <hi>Signor Rham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berto</hi> (though verie loath) reuealed vnto her the whole e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of <hi>Pharicles</hi> diſtreſſe, how he was put in priſon for a ſpie, and that he was accuſed as one that ſought to betray <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> where he ſoiourned into the hands of the Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and that in liew of this his treacherie he ſhould vpon the fortith day for this ſo haynous a fact be executed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mamillia</hi> hearing into what miſerie <hi>Pharicles</hi> was fallen, although his vniuſt dealings had deſerued reuenge, yet ſhe remitted all forepaſſed iniuries, and began to take compaſſion of his miſhap, yéelding forth ſuch ſobbing ſighes and ſcalding teares, as they were witneſſes of her diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed minde, and earneſtlie intreating <hi>Signor Rhamberto</hi> for <hi>Pharicles</hi> credite to conceale y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter as ſecretly as might be, who hauing promiſed to kéepe the matter as ſecrete as ſhe could requeſt, tooke his leaue &amp; departed, but <hi>Mamillia</hi> ſeeing her ſelfe ſolitarie, fell into theſe contrarie paſſions.</p>
            <p>Well now I ſée it true by experience, that where the hedge is loweſt there euery man goeth ouer, that the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt is thruſt to the wall, and he that worſt may holdes the candle: that the ſlendreſt twig is oftimes laden with moſt fruite, the ſmalleſt ſtalke of corne hath the greateſt eare, and he that hath moſt néede of comfort is oftime moſt croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with calamitie. Alas iniurious fortune, is it not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for thée to depriue me of my Father which was more deare vnto me than mine owne life: but alſo to heape care vpon care, and ſorrowe vpon ſorrowe, I meane to murther that man whome in all the world I chiefly eſtéeme! <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles</hi> I meane, who is the fountaine of my ioy, the hauen of my happineſſe, and the ſtay of all my felicitie, who hath wonne my heart by loue, and ſhall weare it by lawe. What ſayeſt thou <hi>Mamillia,</hi> ſhall <hi>Pharicles</hi> enioy thée?
<pb facs="tcp:6147:37"/> Art thou ſo careleſſe of thy fathers commandement, ſo ſoone to forget his counſell? Shall his wordes be as winde, and his talke of ſo little effect as thou meaneſt rechleſly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde it? Wilt not thou in thy life obſerue that which hée enioyned thée at his death? Was not <hi>Pharicles</hi> the onelie man he forbad thée to marrie, and wilt thou chooſe him for thy mate? In louing him thou doeſt forfeit thy landes and ſhewe thy ſelfe a diſobedient daughter, in hating the man thou enioyeſt thy poſſeſſions, and declares thy ſelfe a duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full childe. Tuſh <hi>Mamillia,</hi> is not <hi>Pharicles</hi> the man to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art confirmed by loue and contracted by law? Did not thy father conſent to the match and agrée to the couenant? And ſhall he nowe vpon ſo light an occaſion cauſe thée to violate thine oath, breake thy promiſe, and turne thy loue to hate? No, I will obey my father as farre as the lawe of Nature commands me, but to crack my credit and clog my conſcience I wil not conſent: neither his fatherly counſell nor the loſſe of my goods and landes ſhall conſtraine mée to forſake <hi>Pharicles,</hi> no miſling miſts of miſerie, no dren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſhowers of diſaſter fortune, nor terrible tempeſts of aduerſitie ſhal abate my loue or wracke my fancie againſt the ſlipperie rockes of inconſtancie: yea if my landes will buy his raunſome or my life purchaſe his fréedome, he ſhal no longer leade his life in calamitie.</p>
            <p>And with that ſhe flung out of her chamber being ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and carefull to bring her purpoſe to paſſe, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhort ſpace ſhe furniſhed a ſhip wherein in diſguized ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell ſhée ſailed to <hi>Sicillia</hi> comming to <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> the daie before <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſhould be executed, where ſhe dealt ſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and wiſely, that not onely ſhe learned the cauſe of his impriſonment, but alſo got the coppy of thoſe letters which had paſſed betwéene <hi>Clarynda</hi> and <hi>Pharicles,</hi> thinking eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie houre a yéere till the next morning.</p>
            <p>Well the diſmall day being come wherein <hi>Pharicles</hi> by the dint of death ſhould diſpatch al his forepaſſed miſeries,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:38"/> 
               <hi>Ferragus</hi> being cladde in mourning attire with a penſiue heart and ſorrowfull countenance commeth to accompany <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſo diſtreſſed with griefe &amp; oppreſſed with ſorrow, ſo blubbered with teares and blowne vp with ſighes, that <hi>Pharicles</hi> was faine to comfort him on this wiſe.</p>
            <p>Why friend <hi>Ferragus</hi> quoth he, ſhal the patient appoint the ſalue, or the ſicke man ſet down the medicine? Shall he that is croſſed with care be a comforter, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſtreſſed man be driuen to giue counſell? Shall I which now on euerie ſide am pinched with the pains of death become a Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to cure thy calamitie? Or rather ſhouldeſt not thou in this extremitie ſéeke to aſſwage my dollor with comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble incourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Why <hi>Ferragus</hi> am I more hardy which am at the hazard of death, than thou which art deuoide of daunger? Yea: for by how much the more I féele my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience guiltleſſe of this crime, by ſo much the more I féele my minde frée from ſorrow. <hi>Socrates</hi> would not haue his friend lament when hée drunke his fatall drafte, becauſe quoth he, cauſeleſſe death ought to be without dollour: ſo good <hi>Ferragus</hi> chéere thy ſelfe ſince thy friend <hi>Pharicles</hi> is ſo far from treaſon to <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> as thou from treacherie to <hi>Padua. Pharicles</hi> ſcarſly had vttered theſe words when the officers intreated him to make haſte, for <hi>Signior Farneſe</hi> and the reſt of the Magiſtrates had ſtaied a great ſpace for his comming at the common Hall. <hi>Pharicles</hi> knowing that procraſtination in care was but to increaſe ſorrow, founde no fiſh on his fingers, nor made no delaies from his death, but went with them willingly. Hée being arriued there before the Magiſtrats, <hi>Signior Farneſe</hi> ſtanding vp to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the fatall ſentence, was interrupted by <hi>Mamillia,</hi> who comming in richly attired and ſtraungely diſguiſed, knéeling on her knées craued leaue to ſpeake, which being graunted, ſhe vttered theſe words.</p>
            <p>You haue great cauſe to muſe and maruel) O noble and worthie <hi>Sicillians</hi>) in that a ſilly virgin a ſtranger, yea and
<pb facs="tcp:6147:38"/> of the ſame Citie of <hi>Padua,</hi> which is now ſo deteſted of the citizens of <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> dare preſume not fearing any danger to preſent her ſelfe amidſt ſo many enemies. But whome the diuell driues he muſt néeds runne, and where law and neceſſitie are two ſpurs in the ſide, there the partie ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed neither maketh delaie nor feareth daunger, ſo that Gentlemen by howe much the more my arriuall is to bée thought ſtrange, by ſo much the more my diſtreſſed griefe is to be ſuppoſed greater. It is not the hope of preferment which forced me to this extremitie, becauſe I am of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent parentage and patrimonie in mine owne country, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the deſire to ſée forraine faſhions, becauſe it is not fit for a virgin to be counted a wanderer. No it is partly for thy cauſe <hi>Signior Farneſe</hi> that I came, both to kéepe thée from pronouncing vniuſt iudgement, to diſcouer the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous treacherie of a trothleſſe Curtizan, and to ſaue this guiltleſſe Gentleman from preſent danger. Who by birth is a <hi>Paduan</hi> &amp; of noble parentage, iſſued from ſuch a ſtocke as yet was neuer ſtained either for cowards or traitours. For his ſtate, he is not frée but contracted vnto me by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of both our parents. As concerning his ſoiourning in <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> it was not to betray your citie, but to learn your faſhions, not to be counted a counterfaite, but to be called curteous? But to be briefe, leaſt my tale might ſéeme tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to his vniuſt accuſation inferred by ſuch an iniurious Curtizan, thus I anſwere, that if the calling of a ſtrumpet carried as little credite here as it doth with vs in <hi>Padua, Pharicles</hi> would haue bene more fauourably examined, and her accuſation more throughly canuaſed. It was not (O noble <hi>Farneſe</hi>) that ſhe accuſed <hi>Pharicles</hi> becauſe of his tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, but in that he would not conſent to her vanitie: not becauſe ſhe had ſuch loue to her natiue countrie, but in that <hi>Pharicles</hi> would not agrée to match himſelf with ſo grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a monſter: and for the confirmation of this my alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, ſée here the Letter of <hi>Clarynda,</hi> and the replie of
<pb facs="tcp:6147:39"/> 
               <hi>Pharicles,</hi> and with that ſhe held her peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Farneſe</hi> and the reſt of the Magiſtrates hauing read the contents of the letters, maruelling at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſchieuous mind of ſo helliſh a harlot, ſent ſpéedily for <hi>Clarynda,</hi> who being come and more ſtrictly examined, confeſſed the fault, and receiued the puniſhment due for ſuch an offence. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the citizens of <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>Ferragus,</hi> heard how <hi>Pharicles</hi> was acquited and the treacherie diſcouered, they both reioyced for his happie deliuerie, and alſo wondered that ſuch maruellous wit, wiſdome, and incomparable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie could remaine within the yoong and tender yeares of <hi>Mamillia.</hi> But <hi>Pharicles</hi> ſéeing before his eyes the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe which had giuen him vnhoped for life, driuen as it were into an extaſie for ioy, with bluſhing chéekes &amp; trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ioynts as one féeling in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience the ſting of his former inconſtancie, welcomed her on this wiſe.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>Mamillia</hi> quoth hée, howe welcome thou art to thy poore perplexed <hi>Pharicles</hi> I can ſcarſly conceiue, much leſſe able to expreſſe, but if time and place were conuenient ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to confeſſe my fault or acknowledge my offence, thou ſhouldeſt perceiue I did now as heartily repent as before wilfully offend. Alas how am I bounde if it were but for this one onely deſert to remaine thy bondſlaue for euer at command, well, omitting ſuch ſecrets till a more conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent leiſure, hoping thou haſt forgiuen and forgotten al fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed follies, I bid thée once againe moſt hartily welcome to <hi>Saragoſſa. Pharicles</hi> quoth ſhée, thy <hi>Mamillia</hi> takes this thy hartie welcome as a ſufficient recompence for all her trouble and trauel, aſſuring thée ſhe hath both forgiuen and forgotten all forepaſſed iniuries, otherwiſe I would neuer haue taken ſuch paines to frée thée from daunger. Let your amorous diſcourſes alone till an other time quoth <hi>Farneſe,</hi> for you ſhall with the reſt of the Magiſtrates of <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> be my gueſts to day at dinner. <hi>Pharicles</hi> and <hi>Mamillia</hi> than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Farneſe</hi> for his curteſie, &amp; accepting his gentle profer,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:39"/> were not only his gueſts for that day, but were ſo ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly banqueted there for the ſpace of a wéeke, that they ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie perceiued by their good chéere how welcome they were to the Gentleman. At laſt taking their leaue of <hi>Farneſe,</hi> they returned home to <hi>Padua,</hi> where the Senators hearing of the ſtraunge aduentures which <hi>Pharicles</hi> had paſſed, and perceiuing the incomparable conſtancie of <hi>Mamillia,</hi> they were not onely content that they two ſhould marrie toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but alſo, contrarie to her fathers laſt will &amp; teſtament, let her peaceably enioy all his landes and poſſeſſions. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie whether <hi>Pharicles</hi> proued as inconſtant a huſband as a faithleſſe wooer, I knowe not: but if it be my hap to heare, looke for newes as ſpéedilie as may be.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robert Greene.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:40"/>
            <head>In praiſe of the Author and his Booke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IN Britaine ſoyle there is a garden platte,</l>
               <l>Which for the Aire and Nature of the place,</l>
               <l>Both holſome is and brauely ſituate,</l>
               <l>Where learning growes and hath a noble grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This plat doth yeeld vnto vs diuerſe plants,</l>
               <l>Which ſpread in time this Iland round about,</l>
               <l>Though ſome of them good iuice and moiſture wants,</l>
               <l>Yet many haue both pith and force (no doubt)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some ſharpe of taſte, but verie holſome are,</l>
               <l>Some not ſo good, yet verie toothſome bee,</l>
               <l>Some toothſome are, and verie good (though rare)</l>
               <l>Which all excell ech other in degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not firſt nor next do pleaſe my fancie much,</l>
               <l>The laſt are beſt, which pleaſant profit brings,</l>
               <l>Mongſt whom this plant, (whoſe place and grace is ſuch,)</l>
               <l>Doth yeeld a flower, which faire and liuely ſprings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Greene is the plant, Mamillia the flower,</l>
               <l>Cambridge the plat, where plant and flower groes,</l>
               <l>London the place which brought it firſt in power,</l>
               <l>The Court a ſeat moſt fit for ſuch a roſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to be ſhort (if I true prophet be)</l>
               <l>Plat, place, and ſeate, this pleaſant roſe ſhall ſee,</l>
               <l>If plant doth pleaſe court, citie, and countrie,</l>
               <l>And not diſpleaſe her noble Maieſtie.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nomen &amp; ingenium cum debet ineſſe Poëtae.</l>
                  <l>Omen ita &amp; genium debet habere liber.</l>
                  <l>Ore placet Grenus, prodeſt oculiſque colore,</l>
                  <l>Ingenium genium, nomen &amp; omen habet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vt virtutis comes inuidia, ſic</l>
                  <l>Calami comes calumnia.</l>
               </lg>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:40"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL and vertuous Gentlewoman Mary Rogers, wife to M. Hugh Rogers of Euerton, encreaſe of worſhip and vertue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Raxiteles the Painter, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded why in preſenting a curious target to Minerua hee did moſt cunnigly pourtray the picture of her Prieſt Chriſites, aunſwered that Mynerua was wiſe, &amp; ſo was Chriſites, &amp; that being his friend he thought this the beſt meanes to gratifie him. Which ſaying of Praxiteles I take as a ſufficient excuſe for my raſhneſſe. For if I be demaunded why in dedicating my Booke to others I haue inſerted your worſhippes name, I anſwere that both your conſtant, vertuous and godly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſed me with Praxiteles to ingraue your name in a worke where Gentlewomens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is ſo ſtifly defended, knowing your rare and vertuous qualities to be ſuch, as your verie ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (if you haue anie) ſhall be forced maugre their face to extoll vour fame with immortall
<pb facs="tcp:6147:41"/> praiſe, and alſo your liberall bountie &amp; friendly curteſie (whereof without any deſert I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted) draue me, though not as I would, yet as I could, to ſhew the dutifull affection wherwith I am bound to be at your commaund for euer. While thus I wiſhed more euidently to ſhewe ſome ſigne of my good will, a certaine letter of Mamillia to the yong Ladie Modeſta chaunced to come vnto my hands, wherein the Anatomy of Louers flatteries is diſplaied, which I humbly preſent vnto your worſhipfull patronage, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you to accept it, not according to the value of the gift, but to the mind of the giuer, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring you that none of your welwillers do in heart wiſh you more proſperitie, though my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie be not able in outward ſhewe to make it manifeſt. Thus ceaſing to trouble your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, I commit you to the Almightie.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Clare Hall
<date>the vij. of Iuly.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours at commaunde, ROBERT GREENE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:6147:41"/>
            <head>THE ANATOMIE OF LO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERS FLATTERIES.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Mamillia to the yong and vertuous Virgin the Ladie Modeſta.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Remember Madam that when as my grandfather <hi>Lewes Go<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>zaga</hi> was new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly created Duke of <hi>Neuers,</hi> that diuers of his friends to ſhew their dutifull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, offered him ſundry rich preſents moſt méete for ſo high a perſonage and amongſt the reſt a certaine Muſition preſented vnto his hands a ſcrole wherein were pricked two or thrée curious points of cunning deſcant, deſiring the Duke to accept of his ſimple gift, ſith therein was compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended all his riches and ſkill, to attaine the which, he had paſſed diuers countries and moſt dangerous perils. The Duke wiſely weighing with himſelfe, that nothing was more precious than that which was purchaſed with daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, accepted the gift as a moſt precious Iewell. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which, Madame, and finding my ſelfe ſo greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to your Ladiſhip for the great curteſie and good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you ſhewed me in <hi>Saragoſſa,</hi> as my inſufficiency ſhall neuer be able to requite it, I thought good leaſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I might be thought vngratefull, or counted ſo obliuious as to forget a good turne, in ſtead of precious iems and rich iewels to preſent your Ladiſhip, with a caſketful of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counſell, which ſo much the more is to be eſteemed charie chafre, by how much the more I haue bought the proofe and
<pb facs="tcp:6147:42"/> experience of the ſame with paine and perill. And if Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame you ſhall take it as a caueat to auoide the alluring ſnares of Cupids flatteries, both I ſhall be glad my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting tooke ſo good effect, &amp; you haue cauſe hereafter to thank me for my counſell.</p>
               <p>That laſciuious Poet <hi>Ouid,</hi> Madam <hi>Modeſta,</hi> whome iuſtly we may terme the foe to womankind, hath not only preſcribed in his bookes <hi>de arte Amandi</hi> a moſt monſtrous Method to all men, wherby they may learne to allure ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple women to the fulfilling of their luſt, and the looſing of their owne honor, but alſo hath ſet downe his bookes <hi>de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medio amoris,</hi> to reſtraine their affections from placing their fancies but for a time vpon any Dame, which bookes are ſo ſauced with ſuche blaſphemous deſcriptions of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens infirmities, as they ſhewe that with the Satire hée could out of one mouth blow both hote and cold. Yea <hi>Iuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, Tibullus, Propertius, Calimachus, Phileta, Anacreon,</hi> and many other authors haue ſet downe caueats for men, as armours of proofe to defende themſelues from the allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſubtilties of women. But alas, there is none contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe which hath ſet downe any preſcript rules wherewith women ſhould guide themſelues from the fained aſſault of mens pretended flatterie, but hath left them at diſcouert to be maimed with the glozing gunſhot of their proteſted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, which ſéemeth repugnant to nature. For if the ſillie Lambe had more néede of ſuccour than the luſtie Lyon, if the weake and tender vine ſtandeth in more néed of props than the ſtrong oakes, women ſure, whom they count the weake veſſels, had more néede to be counſelled than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, to be fortified than to be feared, to be defenced tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both with Nature and Art to be aſſaulted. But this their iniurious dealing were a ſufficient caueat, if women were wiſe, to cauſe them beware of mens pretended pollicies, and not to be inticed to that traine whereunder they know a moſt perillous trap to be hidden. The beaſtes will not
<pb facs="tcp:6147:42"/> come at the Panther for all his faire ſkinne, becauſe by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of Nature they know he is a murtherer: the fiſh wil not come at the baite though neuer ſo delicate, for feare of the hidden hooke? neither can the gliſtring feathers of the bird of Egypt cauſe the ſillie Larke to kéepe her companie, ſith ſhe knew her for her mortall enemie. Yet we ſimple women too conſtant and credulous, God knowes to deale with ſuch trothleſſe <hi>Iaſons,</hi> yéelde our heart and hand, our loue, life and liberties to them, whom we know ceaſe not only publikely to appeach vs of a thouſand guiltles crimes, but alſo ſecretly ſéek with forged flatterie to ſcale the Fort, and to ſacke both honour and honeſtie. But Madam, omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting womens fooliſh ſimplicitie in truſting too much mens ſubtill flatterie, ſéeing it is as well giuen by Nature for the woman to loue as for the man to luſt, I will firſt define what loue is, namely a deſire of beautie: and beautie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the minde of ſundrie writers is of thrée ſorts, of the minde, of the bodie, and of the ſpéech, which if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre in one particular perſon, and eſpecially that of the minde, ſufficiently furniſhed with vertues &amp; requiſit qual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, ſuch a one ought a Gentlewoman to chooſe: but the chance is as hard as to finde out a white Ethiopian. Sith then it is ſo difficult among infinite Scorpions to find out one ſillie Eele, amidſt a whole quarrey of flint to chooſe out one precious iemme, and amongſt a thouſande luſting lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers one loyall louer, and ſo hard to deſcrie the true ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the counterfeit coyne, and the precious medicine from the perillous confection: I will as well as I can point you out the crue of thoſe cogging companions, which outwardly profeſſe themſelues to be truſtie louers, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly are rauening Wolues and troathleſſe leachers. There are ſome, Madam, of this diſſembling troup, which rightly may be termed Maſquers, ſome hypocrites, ſome Poets, ſome Crocodiles, ſome Scorpions, and the <hi>Genus</hi> to all theſe forepaſſed <hi>Species</hi> is flatterers. The Maſquers are they, Madam, which couertly vnder the colour of curteſie
<pb facs="tcp:6147:43"/> ſhrowde a peſtilent and péeuiſh kinde of curioſitie: their countenance ſhal be graue though their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grace, and when they ſée anie Gentlewoman addicted to be curteous, honeſt, wiſe, and vertuous, they wil ſtraight with the <hi>Polipe</hi> chaunge themſelues into the likeneſſe of euerie obiect, knowing that it is impoſſible to intiſe the birds to the trap, but by a ſtale of the ſame kind. They car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in outward ſhew the ſhadow of loue, but inwardly the ſubſtance of luſt, they haue a fine die though a courſe thréed, and though at the firſt they ſhrinke not in the wéeting, yet that poore Gentlewoman ſhal haue cauſe to curſe her peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorth which tries them in the wearing: ſhée ſhall finde them whom ſhe though to be Saints to be Serpents, that thoſe who in wooing are Doues, in wedding to be diuels, that in the faireſt graſſe lies hid the fouleſt Snake, in the braueſt tombe the moſt rotten bones, &amp; in the faireſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the fowleſt conditions: thoſe whom I terme to be hypocrites, are they who pricked forward with luſt to fixe their fléeting fancie vppon ſome ſillie dame, whom nature hath beautified both with the ſhape of beautie and ſubſtance of vertue, iudging that it is naturally giuen to women to be deſirous of praiſe, ſéeke to call them to the lure with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting their ſingular quallities, and extolling their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections euen aboue the ſkies, flouriſhing ouer their flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with a Rhetoricall gloſe of fained diſſimulation, the poore mayd who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cal their miſtreſſe, they like counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feites cannonize for an earthly goddeſſe, comparing her for her beautie to <hi>Venus,</hi> for her wit to <hi>Minerua,</hi> for her chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to <hi>Diana,</hi> &amp; yet this vertue the chéefeſt thing they ſéeke to ſpoile her of: her eyes are twinkling ſtarres, her téeth pearles, her lips corall, her throate Iuorie, her voice moſt muſicall harmonie: yea ſhée is ſo perfect in all pointes, as they maruell how ſo heauenly a creature is ſhrowded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhape of mortalitie: theſe I ſay who haue honie in their mouth and gall in their heart, are ſuch hypocriticall
<pb facs="tcp:6147:43"/> flatterers as they ſéeke with ſugred words and filed ſpéech to inueigle the ſillie eyes of wel meaning Gentlewomen, when as inwardly they ſcoffe at the poore maids which are ſo blinde as not to ſée their extréeme follie and groſſe flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Pratling Poets I call thoſe who hauing authoritie with Painters to faine, lie, and diſſemble, ſéek with <hi>Syrens</hi> ſongs and inchanting charms of diuelliſh inuention, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch the mindes of young and tender virgines, vnder the colour of loue to draw them to luſt, painting out in Songs and Sonets their great affection, and deciphring in fained rimes their forged fancie: they be taken in the beames of her beautie as the Bée in the Cobweb, they are ſinged at the ſight of her faire face, as the Flie at the Candle, they ſuffer worſe paines than <hi>Siſiphus,</hi> more tormentes than <hi>Tantalus,</hi> more griefe than <hi>Ixion:</hi> they are plunged in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toes</hi> pitte, and ſo drowned in diſtreſſe, that vnleſſe the ſillie maide by ſelling her fréedome, and looſing both honour and honeſtie giue a ſalue to their ſurmiſed ſore, they ſhall ende their daies in helliſh miſerie: yea to decypher their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes more narrowly, they are ſo ouergrowne with grief, as in all their bodie they haue no place whole, but their heart, nothing at quiet but their minde, nor nothing frée but their affection, they are indéede ſo paſſionate in their penne, and ſuch inckpot louers, that the poore maid which by truſting too much is charmed with their magicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, ſhall finde their firmeſt fancie was but forged follie, their loue was but tickling luſt, and that the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in their chaſe was but to make ſhipwracke of her cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie. The nature of the Crocodill, Madame, is with gréeuous grones and trickling teares to craue helpe as one in diſtreſſe, but who ſo commeth to ſuccour him is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuoured: ſo Madame, thoſe kinde of louers whome I terme Crocodiles, are they which when neither flatterie can preuaile, nor ſuppoſed curteſies is of force to ſcale the Fort of their inuincible honeſtie, then (knowing that gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen
<pb facs="tcp:6147:44"/> are pitifull and wholie framed of the moulde of mercie) they fall with the Crocodill to their fained teares, ſeeking with diſſembled ſighes and ſobs, with wéeping and wayling, with diſtreſſed crie, and pitifull exclamations, to mooue hir to take pitie of their plaint, whome after with gréedie gripes they bring to vtter decay and ruine. But Madame, as the iuice of the hearbe Baaran drieth faſter than it can be preſſed out, and as the water of the fountaine Sibia can no faſter be powred into braſſe but it turneth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mettall, ſo there is nothing in the world that drieth ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than a louers teares, nor no ſickneſſe ſooner inwardly ſalued than a louers ſorrow, their care may ſoone be cured, becauſe it commeth not from the heart, and their mourning ſoone amended, ſith it no whit mooueth the minde: yet they can ſo cunningly counterfeit the ſhadowe of a perplexed patient, and haue trickling teares and farre fetcht ſighes ſo at their commaund, that few well meaning and pitifull maides can eſcape the traine of their alluring ſubtilties. Scorpions Madame, are they which ſting with their taile, and ſéeke with deſpightfull termes to abuſe the credite of Gentlewomen: theſe be thoſe kinde of louers which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing neither comelineſſe of perſon nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions of minde, neither wit, wiſedome, beautie, or learning, nor any other good qualitie to purchaſe them credite or winne them the fauour of women, but are vtterly reiected as vnſauerie, ſalting neither woorth the taſting nor eating, ſéeke then with blaſphemous reproches and iniurious rayling to call the fame of honeſt Gentlewomen in queſtion, then they condemne them of inconſtancie, comparing them to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melions, Polipes,</hi> and wethercocks, affirming their fancies to be fléeting, their loue to be light, and their choiſe wholy ſetled in chaunge: that they bée malicious, deceitfull, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunting <hi>Syreus,</hi> craftie <hi>Calipſoes,</hi> as ſubtill as Serpents, as cruell as Tygres, and what not? and the cauſe of this their vniuſt accuſing commeth not through any iniurie
<pb facs="tcp:6147:44"/> offered them by Gentlewomen, but that they themſelues are ſo imperfect both in minde and bodie, that both by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and arte they may iuſtly be appeached of want. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing now Madame though not eloquently yet truly ſet downe before your face in plaine collour the Anatomie of ſuch licentious louers as ſéeke with alluring baites to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap the mindes of chaſt maydens, ſith loue is the labe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth which leadeth vs to be deuoured of theſe inceſtuous monſters, let vs learne to flie it as warily as wyſe <hi>Vlyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did the Mermaides. <hi>Anacreon</hi> who ſpake by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and writ by proofe, calleth loue a tyrant, miſchéeuous, cruell, hardie, vnkinde, foule, vngratious, curſed, wicked, and the cauſe of all miſchiefe. Loue of beawtie ſayeth he is the forgetting of reaſon, the father of frenzie, the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the minde, the enemie to health, the ſincke of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, the garden of griefe, and to conclude, a confuſed <hi>chaos</hi> of miſerie: ſo that if it might be ſéene with bodilie eyes, or be an obiect to our exteriour ſenſes, the Baſiliſke is not more feared, nor the Cockatrice more auoided than lothſome loue would be eſchewed and deteſted. What fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie is it for that woman which is frée to become captiue, which is at libertie to become a perpetual ſlaue to another man, who hauing the choiſe in her own hand to liue at her own luſt, will willingly yéeld herſelfe ſubiect to be directed at another mans pleaſure? But this affection of loue natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally traineth &amp; entrappeth young mindes, and eſpecially of women, wherfore they had néede to take the more héede leaſt happily it ſtealeth vppon them, for commonly it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vpon ſuch as will not ſeeke meanes to preuent, but careleſlie receiue it as a ſweete &amp; pleaſant thing, not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing what and how perilous a poyſon lyes hid vnder that pleaſant face. Let her therefore that will auoide this fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke &amp; fooliſh affection, giue no more eare vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alluring charmes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fained louer than vnto the ſong of an inchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſorcerer, let her conſider that as it is proper to the
<pb facs="tcp:6147:45"/> Camelion to change, to the Fox to be wilie, to the Lyon to be hautie, and to the Hiena to be guilefull, ſo it is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of louers to diſſemble, that when he doth moſt frie in fancie, then he doth moſt frize in affection, when he faineth <hi>Etna</hi> he proueth <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> when hée complaineth of care then is he moſt ſecure, when he waileth outwardly then he laugheth inwardly, like to the ſtone <hi>Ceraunon,</hi> which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it burneth moſt feruently, being broken diſtilleth moſt cold liquor. The ende alſo of theſe louers affection is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, which is not for her vertue, wiſedome, or honeſtie, but either allured by her beautie which ſhe enioyeth, or her riches that ſhe poſſeſſeth. The ſkinne of the <hi>Ermelyn</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired and the carkaſſe deſpiſed, the horne of the <hi>Vnicorne</hi> moſt preciouſly receiued and his fleſh reiected, the hoofe of the <hi>Leopard</hi> is the thing that hunters ſéekes or elſe hée is contemned, ſo the beautie and riches of a woman is highly regarded, but her vertue and honeſtie lightly eſtéemed, that as the taſte being once glutted thinketh the ſwéet wine ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, or as the fineſt delicates to a full ſtomacke ſéemeth but courſe cates, ſo he that buildeth his loue vppon beautie of the bodie and onely regardeth riches when the beautie is faded, his loue decreaſeth or being ſatiate with pleaſure loatheth the plentie, or if wealth want, his loue pineth with extréeme penurie. But put caſe the minde is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die caught in the ſnares of <hi>Cupid,</hi> and hath yéelded her ſelf as a vaſſall vnto <hi>Venus,</hi> let vs finde a remedie to draw her out of this perillous Laborinth. I remember the ſaying of <hi>Dant,</hi> that loue cannot roughly be thruſt out but it muſt eaſilie créepe, and a woman muſt ſéeke by litle and litle to recouer her former libertie, wading in loue like the Crab whoſe pace is alwaies backward, calling to her remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that if her louer be faire, he will be proud of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if rich, his ſubſtance procureth ſtatelineſſe, if of noble parentage, it maketh him diſdainfull: that the ſtone <hi>Echi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> is moſt pleaſaunt to the eye, but moſt infectious to be
<pb facs="tcp:6147:45"/> handled, that the hearbe called <hi>Flos Solis</hi> is beautifull to behold but deadly to be taſted, that the faireſt face hath oft times the falſeſt heart, and the comelieſt creature moſt curriſh conditions: who more faire than <hi>Paris,</hi> yet a troth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe traitor to his loue <hi>Oenone. Vliſſes</hi> was wiſe, yet wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, <hi>Eneas</hi> a pleaſant tongue, yet proued a paraſiticall flatterer, <hi>Demophoon</hi> demure and yet a diſſembler, <hi>Iaſon</hi> promiſeth much yet performed little, and <hi>Theſeus</hi> addeth a thouſand othes to <hi>Ariadne,</hi> yet neuer a one proued true. Conſider the hearbe of <hi>India</hi> is of pleaſant ſmell, but who ſo commeth to it féeleth preſent ſmart, the <hi>Goorde</hi> leafe profitable, the ſéede poyſon, the rinde of the trée <hi>Tillia</hi> moſt ſwéete and the fruite moſt bitter, the outward ſhew of ſuch flattering louers full of delight, but the inward ſubſtance ſawſed with deſpight. Call alſo to minde their often periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, their vaine oathes, falſified promiſes and inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, their proteſtations, pilgrimages, &amp; a thouſande diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled flatteries, and if thy louer be infected with any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular fault, let that be the ſubiect whereon to muſe, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that many vices are hidden vnder the coloured ſhape of vertue, if he be liberal thinke him prodigall, if eloquent a babler, if wiſe inconſtant, if bolde raſh, if timerous a da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, if he be well backt thinke it is the taylers art &amp; not natures workemanſhip, if a good waſte attribute it to his coate that is ſhapt with the Spaniſh cut, if wel legd think he hath a bumbaſt hoſe to couer his deformitie, yea driue all his perfections out of thy minde, and muſe vpon his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, ſo ſhalt thou leade a quiet life in libertie and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer buy repentance too deare, and though hée countes thée cruell becauſe thou art conſtant and doeſt refuſe to yéeld to thine owne luſt, thinke it no diſcredite: for muſtie caſkes are fit for rotten grapes, a poyſoned barrell for infectious liquour, and crueltie is too milde a medicine for flattering louers. Thus Madame, you haue heard my counſel which I haue learned by proofe and ſpeake by experience, which if
<pb facs="tcp:6147:46"/> you willingly accept, I ſhall thinke my labour well beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, and if you wiſely vſe, you ſhall thinke your time not ill ſpent, but if you do neither, my well wiſhing is neuer the worſe, and ſo fare you well.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours to command, Mamillia.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>MODESTA TO HER BELO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Mamillia.</head>
               <p>IT is too late, Madame <hi>Mamillia,</hi> to ſound the retrait, the battaile being already fought, to drie the malt the kil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on fire, to wiſh for raine when the ſhower is paſt, to apply the ſalue the ſore being remedileſſe, &amp; to giue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile the caſe being paſt cure, for before the coroſiue came, the ſore was growne to a feſtred Fiſtula, &amp; ere your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable confect was preſented to my hand, I was fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtrange Feuer. Thou didſt <hi>Mamillia</hi> counſell me to beware of loue, and I was before in the laſh. Thou didſt wiſh me to beware of fancie, and alas I was faſt fettred, I haue choſen <hi>Mamillia</hi> (What do I ſay?) haue I choſen? yea: but ſo poore ſoule as all my friends do wiſh me to change, and yet I haue ſatiſfied my ſelf though not contented them. My friendes regarded the mony and I reſpected the man, they wealth and I wiſedome, they lands and lordſhips and I beautie and good bringing vp, ſo that either I muſt chooſe one rich whom I did hate and ſo content them, or take one poore, whom I did loue and ſo ſatiſfie my ſelfe. Driuen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millia</hi> into this <hi>dilemma,</hi> I am to aſke thine aduiſe what I
<pb facs="tcp:6147:46"/> ſhould do, whether I ſhould lead my life with aboundance of wealth in loathe, or ſpende my daies with no riches in loue. In this if thou ſhalt ſtand my friend to giue me thy counſel, I will if euer I be able requite thy curteſie. From <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> in haſte.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thine aſſuredlie, doubtfull Modeſta.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mamillia</hi> hauing receiued this Letter, returned her as ſpéedily as might be an anſwere to this effect.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>MAMILLIA TO THE Ladie Modeſta.</head>
               <p>MAdame <hi>Modeſta,</hi> I haue receiued your letters, &amp; haue viewed your doubtfull demaund, whereunto thus I anſwer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to liue we muſt follow the aduiſe of our friends, but to loue our owne fancie: for to another mans liuing they may giue preceptes, but to fixe fancie in loue they can preſcribe no certaine principles. Then Madame, ſith you haue riches which may of a poore woer make a welthy ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, wed not for wealth, leaſt repentance caſt the accounts, nor match not with a foole, leaſt afterward thou repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thine own follie, but chooſe one whoſe beautie may content thine eye, and whoſe vertuous wiſedom may ſatiſfie thy minde, ſo ſhalt thou haue neither cauſe to repent, nor occaſion to miſlike thy choyce, and that thou maiſt perceiue my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning more plainly, reade this following hiſtorie with good aduiſement.</p>
               <p>There dwelt in <hi>Toledo</hi> a certaine <hi>Caſtilian</hi> named
<pb facs="tcp:6147:47"/> 
                  <hi>Valaſco</hi> by parentage a Gentleman, by profeſſion a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, of more wealth than worſhip, and yet iſſued of ſuch parents as did beare both great countenance and credit in the countrie. This <hi>Valaſco</hi> after the deceaſe of his father was a ward to the Duke of <hi>Zamorra,</hi> who ſéeing him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with great wealth and large poſſeſſions hauing the diſpoſition of his marriage in his hands, married him to a kinſwoman of his named <hi>Sylandra,</hi> a Gentlewoman nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indewed with wit nor adorned with beautie: and yet not ſo witleſſe but ſhe was wilfull, nor ſo deformed but ſhe was proude, inſomuch as her inward vices and outward vanities, did in tract of time ſo quat the queaſie ſtomacke of her huſband <hi>Valaſco,</hi> that although in his childiſh yéeres he did not miſlike of her follie, yet in his ripe yéeres when reaſon was a rule to direct his iudgement, he ſo deteſted the infirmities of her nature and the infections of her nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as ſhe was the onely woman his craſie ſtomack could not digeſt. <hi>Valaſco</hi> being thus combred with ſuch a croſſe, as the burthen thereof was to him more heauie than the weight of the heauens to the ſhoulders of <hi>Atlas,</hi> and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by experience what a miſerie it was to marrie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loue, or make his choice without ſkill, and how loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome it was to liue without liking, or to be wedded to her whom neither his fancie nor affection did deſire to enioy: hauing by his wife <hi>Sylandra</hi> one onelie daughter named <hi>Syluia,</hi> determined with <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> to marrie her ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to a man than to monie, and neuer to match her with anie whom ſhe did not both intirely loue and like. While he was in this determination <hi>Sylandra</hi> died, leauing <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſco</hi> a diligent huſband for the finiſhing of his wines fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, and a carefull father for the well bringing vp of his daughter <hi>Syluia,</hi> who now was about the age of ſixtéene yéeres, ſo beautified with the gifts of nature, and adorned with ſundrie vertues and exquiſite quallities, as the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Toledo</hi> were in doubt whether her beautie or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb facs="tcp:6147:47"/> deſerued greater commendation. <hi>Syluia</hi> flouriſhing thus in the prime of her youth and proouing daylie more excellent as well in the complexion of the bodie as in the perfection of her mind, grew ſo renowmed for her famous feature almoſt throughout all <hi>Europe,</hi> that as they which came to <hi>Memphis</hi> thought they had ſéene nothing vnleſſe they had viewed the <hi>Pyramides</hi> built by <hi>Rhodope,</hi> ſo the ſtrangers which arriued at <hi>Toledo</hi> thought their affaires not fully finiſhed vntill they had obtained the ſight of <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia.</hi> So that as the moſt charie chafre hath euer moſt choice of chapmen, and as the richeſt iem hath euer moſt reſort to viewe it and buy it, ſo by the meanes of <hi>Syluia</hi> the houſe of <hi>Valaſco</hi> was ſo frequented with a noble traine of worthie Sutors, as if it had béene a common Burſe for exchange of Marchandize. Yet all their woing proued ſmall ſpéeding, ſith <hi>Syluia</hi> kept a loofe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeaſing on the lure. For although there were diuers of moſt noble parentage and great poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions which required her in mariage, offering for her feoffment great lands and Lordſhips: yet <hi>Valaſco</hi> would neither condiſcende without her conſent, nor conſtraine her to conſent to his commaundement. Well, <hi>Syluia</hi> thus glorying in her fréedome, and taking pleaſure to trace in the large lées of libertie, was not ſuffered ſo quietly to fortifie the bulwarke of her chaſtitie, but ſhe had ſundrie aſſaultes and daylie canuizadoes to force her yéeld the fort to ſome of her importunate ſuters, amongſt whome, there repaired by meare chance at one time and in one day thrée Gentlemen of ſundry nations and diuers diſpoſitions, the firſt an Italian called <hi>S. Gradaſſo,</hi> the ſecond a Frenchman named <hi>Monſieur de Vaſte,</hi> the third, an Engliſhman called maſter <hi>Petronius. Signor Gradaſſo,</hi> was verie olde but of great wealth, <hi>Monſieur de Vaſte</hi> of ſurpaſſing beautie, but ſomewhat fooliſh, and maſter <hi>Petronius</hi> of great wit, but of verie ſmall wealth, theſe Gentlemen were verie courteouſly entertayned by <hi>Signor Valaſco,</hi> whome they
<pb facs="tcp:6147:48"/> requited with ſundrie ſalutations to this effect. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne ſir, quoth <hi>Signor Gradaſſo,</hi> not onely of your daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters beautie, but alſo of her ſingular vertue is ſo blowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad by fame in euerie place, and in euery mans eares, as there hath bene no talke for a time in Italie but of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of <hi>Syluia,</hi> which forced mée being now olde and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in yeares, to repaire hither as one deſirous not onelie to ſée your daughter, but alſo to take her to wife, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due her with ſuch feoffements and large poſſeſſions as ſhe ſhalbe ſatiſfied and you ſufficiently contented. <hi>Gradaſſo</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſaid his mind, <hi>Monſieur de Vaſte</hi> not being the wiſeſt man of the world in telling a tale, let a man of his called <hi>Iaques</hi> be his interpreter, faining that he was vtterlie ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in the Spaniſh tongue, who in his maſters behalfe framed his talke to this effect. Sir, quoth he, my maſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the onely ſonne and heire to his parents, and being left the onely piller of all his parentage, hath euer ſince the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe of his father bene verie careful to match himſelf with ſuch a one in marriage as might content him for her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and be his countenance and credite for her vertue &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie. Hearing therefore of your daughters ſingular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as well in the one as in the other, he was inforced by an inward affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come as one very deſirous to match himſelfe with ſo good a mate, offring all his lands in dower as a perfect pledge of his vnfained good will. <hi>Iacques</hi> had no ſooner made an end of his parle, but poore <hi>Petronius</hi> offered his ſute verie rufully. Sir quoth <hi>Petronius,</hi> as it is a ſigne of follie to cheape that chaffre for the which there is farre more offered than he is able to affoord: ſo the beautie, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and parentage of your daughter <hi>Syluia,</hi> the great dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and large feoffments offred by ſundrie ſutors had dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my feruent affection, ſith being a poore ſcholler by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, &amp; yet a Gentleman by birth, far vnfit by the meanes of want to be a wooer, had I not heard that you haue giuen the rains of libertie to your daughter to be miſtreſſe of her
<pb facs="tcp:6147:48"/> owne choice, neither reſpecting the defect of want, nor the ſuperfluitie of wealth, ſo your daughter like and loue the partie. Incouraged with this her frée libertie in choice, I am come to offer her neither landes nor Lordſhips but my ſillie ſelfe, readie in what I may and ſhe pleaſe to pleaſure her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Signor Valaſco,</hi> hauing heard and diligently marked the effect of their talke, ſmiling and maruelling at their ſtraunge aduenture, that thrée Gentleman ſo farre diſtant in place and diuerſe in condition ſhould ſo fitly méete at one inſtant, yea and framing their ſutes all to one effect, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them this friendly and curteous anſwere. Gentlemen quoth he, you are not come in more haſte, than welcome with a good heart, and for my part I conceiue ſuch good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of you all in generall, as I could be content to beſtow my daughter vppon anie of you in particular. For neither thy olde age <hi>Signor Gradaſſo,</hi> nor your want of learning, <hi>Monſieur de Vaſte,</hi> nor thy lacke of wealth maiſter <hi>Petro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> do bréede in me any ſuch miſliking, but that if it pleaſe my daughter to conſent, I will willingly condeſcend: for in her and not in me conſiſteth your deniall. Therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me and I will bring you where euerie man ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his ſuite, and haue a ſpéedie anſwere. And with that he carried them to <hi>Syluias</hi> chamber, whome they found ſitting ſolitarie at her muſes. Who eſpying her father accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with theſe thrée Gentlemen entertained euerie one of them ſo curteouſly with a kiſſe, her countenance notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting importing ſuch grauitie, as they perceiued ſhe was neither infected with curioſitie, nor deuoyd of ſurpaſſing modeſtie: which ſo aſtoniſhed the paſſionate hearts of theſe thrée patients, that as the deare with the ſigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of a faire ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtandeth at gaze, ſo they were with her beautie &amp; vertue driuen into ſuch a maze, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Signor Valaſco</hi> was fain to break ſilence in this maner. <hi>Syluia</hi> quoth he, theſe thrée gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inforced by affection, &amp; drawne by the report of thy beautie
<pb facs="tcp:6147:49"/> (as they ſay) are come from forraine countries to craue thée in marriage, which ſith it conſiſteth not in my power to graunt without thy conſent, I haue brought them to thy Chamber, that both they may ſpeake for themſelues, and thou giue them ſuch an anſwere as fancie or affection ſhall commaund thee. This Gentleman being olde is of great riches to maintaine thy eſtate: the other is as thou ſéeſt verie faire, but not verie wiſe: the laſt is learned and wiſe, but not of any wealth. Now <hi>Syluia</hi> the choice is in thine own hands, if thou loue one of them I ſhall like him, if thou refuſe them all, I am ſtill contented. <hi>Syluia</hi> yéelding moſt dutifull thanks to her father for his natural affection, returned him ſoberlie this ſolemne anſwere.</p>
               <p>Sir quoth ſhe, I now ſée by experience that dreames are not alwayes vaine illuſions and fond fantaſies, but that ſometime they prognoſticate &amp; foreſhewe what afterward ſhall happen. For <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> a little before he was Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of the world dreamed that he had ouercome <hi>Mars</hi> in plaine battell. <hi>Penelope</hi> the night before her long looked for <hi>Vliſſes</hi> came home, ſawe in her ſléepe <hi>Cupide</hi> pricking an Oliue branch at her beds head, and this night laſt paſt I did ſée in a dreame <hi>Venus</hi> ſtanding in a moſt braue and delicate garden wherein were but onely thrée trées, the one a verie olde and withered Oake, yet laden with Ackornes, the other a faire and beautifull Ceder trée, and yet the roote decayed and rotten, the third a gréene Bay trée flouriſhing and yéelding foorth an odoriferous ſmell, but being bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine and without beries. And me thought as I thus ſtoode taking the viewe of the trées, <hi>Venus</hi> chaunged me into a turtle Doue, and bad me build my neſt in one of theſe trées which beſt pleaſed my fancie. And as I was readie to yéeld her an anſwere, I ſodeinlie awooke, and <hi>Venus</hi> loſt her verdit. To diuine of this dreame it paſſeth my ſkill, but I coniecture the thrée trées did repreſent theſe thrée Gentlemen, and the Turtle my ſelfe: but what either
<pb facs="tcp:6147:49"/> 
                  <hi>Venus</hi> or the building of the neaſt do ſignifie, it paſſeth my ſkill to coniecture. But omitting my dreame and the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification thereof till tract of time ſhall diuine it, ſith you are Gentlemen of ſundrie countries and diuerſe diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and yet all ſhoote at one marke: let me heare what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one of you can ſay in commendation of his owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and then as Fortune ſhall fauour you, and fancy force me, you ſhall receiue an anſwere. <hi>Syluia</hi> had no ſooner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her talke, but the Gentleman began to diuine of the dreame very deuoutly, deſcanting diuerſly of the building of the neaſt, and applying the interpretation to their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular preferment. The Turtle alwaies or moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, quoth <hi>Gradaſſo,</hi> buildeth on the tall and ſtrong oake, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring it becauſe it is <hi>Arbor Iouis,</hi> the trée of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and delighting to build in it by a ſecret motion of nature, and therefore I haue cauſe if the dreame proue true, to count my part the beſt portion. Nay ſir, quoth <hi>Iacques</hi> in his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters behalfe, you haue leaſt hope &amp; greateſt cauſe to doubt, for the oake was old &amp; withered, &amp; the turtle naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in gréene &amp; flouriſhing trées, and eſpecially in the tall and beautifull Cedar, and therefore you are exempted. As for the bay trée although it be gréene, yet <hi>Plinie</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it is the onelie trée which the turtle Doue abhorreth, and therfore of theſe premiſſes I infer this concluſion, that by the diuination of this dream my maiſter ſhal obtain the priſe at this turnay. Wel maſters quoth <hi>Petronius,</hi> though you thruſt mée out for a wrangler, and count me as a Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher in <hi>Algoriſme,</hi> yet I ſay, that neither I haue occaſion to doubt nor you cauſe to hope. For though by the meanes of <hi>Venus</hi> there chanced ſuch a Metamorphoſis, yet though her body was tranſformed, her heart, mind &amp; vnderſtanding was not changed, though ſhe were a Turtle in ſhewe, yet ſhe was <hi>Syluia</hi> in ſenſe, not hauing ſo baſe a minde, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to build her neaſt in a withered oake, where it were more méete for a myrie ſowe to féede, than ſo gallant a bird
<pb facs="tcp:6147:50"/> to build, or on a faire Cedar, ſith the roote was rotten and readie to fall, but would rather make her choice of a faire and flouriſhing bay trée, which may both profite her ſelfe and pleaſure her ſences. So that if we haue part I hope and aſſure my ſelfe mine to be the beſt. Tuſh Gentlemen quoth <hi>Syluia,</hi> fiſh not before the net, nor make not your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countes without your hoſtes, leaſt happily your gaines be ſmall, and your ſhot vncertaine. But if you pleaſe to haue my companie, leaue off all circumſtances and goe to the matter. <hi>Signor Gradaſſo</hi> hearing <hi>Syluia</hi> to grow ſo ſhort, began the aſſault with this March. It is neceſſarie ſaith <hi>Callymachus,</hi> for him which will be a perfect louer to haue experience in his wooing and conſtancie in his wedding, leaſt by want of ſkill he looſe his labour, and his miſtreſſe through his inconſtancy repent the bargain. For where ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience wanteth, there commonly the choice hath an ill chaunce, and where conſtancie beares no ſway, there the match is alwaies marred. Now theſe two ſo commendable quallities are alwaies found in olde age, and neuer ſéene in yong yéeres. The old Bucke maketh better choice of his food than the little Fawne, the olde Lyon chooſeth alwaies a better praie than the yong whelpe, the bird Acanthis in her age buildeth her neaſt with moſt diſcretion, and an old man hath more experience to make a perfect choice, than a yong mans ſkill to gaine a happie chaunce, age directs all his doings by wiſedome, and youth doteth vpon his owne will, age hauing bought witte with paine and perill, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeth daungers and eſcheweth the ſame, but youth follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wanton witte too wilfully, neuer preuenteth perilles while they be paſt, nor dreadeth daungers while hée be halfe drowned, yea there is ſuch a difference betwéene an olde man and a young ſtripling, betwéene hoarie haires and flouriſhing youth, that the one is followed as a friend to others, and the other eſchewed as an enemie to himſelf. The <hi>Brachmans</hi> &amp; <hi>Gymnoſophiſtes</hi> made a law that none
<pb facs="tcp:6147:50"/> vnder the age of fortie ſhould marrie without the conſent of the Senior, leaſt in making their choice without ſkil, the man in proceſſe of time ſhould begin to loathe, or the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man not to loue. For youth fiereth his fancy with the flame of luſt, and olde age fixeth his affection with the heate of loue. Young yeares make no account but vppon the glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering ſhewe of beautie, and hoarie haires reſpecteth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the perfect ſubſtance of vertue. Age ſéeketh not with ſubtilties to inchaunt the minde, nor with ſleightes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap the maide, he weareth not a veluet ſcabbard and a ruſtie blade, nor a golden Bell with a leaden clapper, he frameth not his affection in the forge of flatterie, nor draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not a falſe colour with the Penſill of diſſimulation: he doth not coyne his paſſions with a counterfeit ſtampe, nor faine his loue with a coloured lye, he beareth not honie in his mouth &amp; gall in his heart, he hath not an Oliue branch in his boſome and a ſworde at his backe, hée carrieth not bread in his hand and a dagger in his ſléeue, but if he fancie tis with faith, and if hée tell his tale it is tempered with truth, which ſhineth in a louer as a polliſhed iemme ſet in moſt gliſtring gold. So that old me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are oft enuied for their vertue, and yong men pittied for their vice. The hearbe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſnum</hi> being newly ſprung vp hath a moſt ſowre iuice, but being come to his groweth a moſt delicate ſappe. The olde Firre hath the ſwéeteſt ſmell, the aged Panther the pureſt breath, and the oldeſt man the moſt perfect conditions: ſo that as it is naturall for the Palme trée to be ſtraight, for the Corall to be red, for the Tygre to be fierce, for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to be ſubtill, and the Camell to haue a crookt back, ſo is it proper to olde men to be endued with vertue, and young men imbrued with vice, for horie age to be entangled with loue, and ſtaileſſe youth to be entrapped with luſt, that as the braueſt Sepulchre cannot make the dead carkaſſe to ſmell ſwéete, nor the moſt delicate ienimes make a defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med face faire, ſo the richeſt attire or moſt coſtly apparrell
<pb facs="tcp:6147:51"/> cannot make a young minde ſauour of vertue. The olde Pine trée is more eſtéemed for the profit, than the flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing buds of the trées in the Ile of <hi>Colchos</hi> for their poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the olde Serpents Serapie are of greater account for their vertuous ſkinne, than the yoong and gliſtring Euets for their inuenomed hides. Age is alwaies more eſtéemed for his ſtaied minde than youth for his ſtaileſſe mood. That flouriſhing and beautifull dame <hi>Rodophe</hi> which married old <hi>Sampniticus</hi> the King of <hi>Memphis,</hi> was woont to ſaie that ſhe had rather be an olde mans darling than a young mans drudge, that ſhe had rather content her ſelfe with an old man in pleaſure, than féed her fancie with a yoong man in penurie, that ſhe had rather be loued of an old man euer, than liked of a yoong man for a while. The mind of a yoong man is momentarie, his fancie fading, his affection fickle, his loue vncertaine, and his liking as light as the winde, his fancie fiered with euerie new face, and his minde moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a thouſand ſundry motions, loathing that which alate he did loue, &amp; liking that for which his longing mind doth luſt, frying at the firſt, and frizing at the laſt, not ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner inflamed than quickly cold, as little permanent as vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and like the melting wax which receiueth euery im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, where as age is conſtant like to the Emeraulde, which hauing receiued a forme neuer taketh other ſtampe without cracking. The mind of an old man is not mutable, his fancy fixed, and his affection not fléeting, he chooſeth not intending to chaunge, nor chaungeth not til death maketh the challenge. The olde Oake neuer falleth but by the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters axe, nor the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of age but by the dint of death. The olde Cedar trée is leſſe ſhaken with winde than the yoong Bramble, and age farre more ſtaied than youth, yea though an old man be withered in age, yet he flouriſheth in affection, though he want the beautie of bodie, yet hée hath the bountie of the minde, though age had diminiſhed his colour, yet it hath augmented his vertue, though youth
<pb facs="tcp:6147:51"/> excelleth in ſtrength, yet age ſurpaſſeth in ſtedfaſtneſſe, ſo that I conclude by how much the more the vertues of the minde are to be preferred before the beautie of the bodie, by ſo much the more ought an olde louer to be preferred before a young leacher. You haue heard <hi>Syluia</hi> what I haue ſaid, and you know I haue ſpoken nothing but truth. If then it pleaſe you to thinke well of my part and accept of my perſon, to requite my loyall loue with lawfull li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and my fixed fancie with feruent affection: aſſure your ſelfe you ſhall haue <hi>Signor Gradaſſo</hi> ſo at your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, as you in euerie reſpect can wiſh, and in the pledge of this my good will I will make your feofment a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crownes of yéerely reuenewes. <hi>Signor Gradaſſo</hi> had no ſooner ended, but <hi>Iacques</hi> in his maiſters behalfe framed his talke to this effect. There is nothing quoth he, which among mortall creatures is more deteſted than deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor nothing more imbraced than beautie, which aboue all the giftes both of Nature and Fortune doth make vs moſt reſemble the gods. So that where the bodie is ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with beautie and perfection of nature, there it ſéemeth the gods ſhewe moſt fauour and affection, ſith that they tooke ſuch care in caruing a péece of ſo curious perfection. Inſomuch that they ſay when the gods made beautie, they ſkipt beyond their ſkill, in that the maker is ſubiect to the thing made, for what made <hi>Thetis</hi> be inconſtant but beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, what forced <hi>Venus</hi> to be in loue with <hi>Anchiſes</hi> but beautie? what cauſed <hi>Luna</hi> to like <hi>Endymion</hi> but beautie? yea, it is ſayde to be of ſo great force, that it bewitcheth the wiſe, and inchaunteth them that made it. There is none ſo addicted to chaſtitie whome beautie hath not chaunged, none ſo vowed to virginitie whome beautie hath not char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, none ſo ſeuere whome beautie hath not beſotted, nor none ſo ſenſeleſſe whome the name of beautie can not either breake or bende. Loue commeth in at the eye not at the eares, by ſéeing natures workes not by hearing
<pb facs="tcp:6147:52"/> ſugred wordes, and fancie is fedde by the faireneſſe of the face not by the fineneſſe of the ſpéech. Beautie is the <hi>Syren</hi> which will drawe the moſt adamant heart by force, and ſuch a charme as haue conſtrained euen the veſtal virgins to forſake their celles, yea it ſo inueigleth the ſight and bewitcheth the ſences, it ſo troubleth the minde and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the braine, yea it bringeth ſuch extreame delight to the heart, ſo that as the Viper being tyed to a Béech trée, falleth into a ſlumber, ſo diuerſe beholding beautifull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons haue ſtoode as though with <hi>Meduſas</hi> head they had bin turned to a ſtone. <hi>Anacharſis</hi> being demaunded what hée thought was the greateſt gift that euer the Gods beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vppon man, anſwered beautie, for that it both deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the eye, contenteth the minde, and winneth good will and fauour of all men. <hi>Pigmaleon</hi> for beautie loued the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Iuorie, and <hi>Apelles</hi> the counterfeite which he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured with his owne ſkill, &amp; the picture <hi>Ganimides</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſtoniſhed the Ladies of <hi>Cypres.</hi> What made <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſo beloued of the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> but beautie? what gayned <hi>Theſeus</hi> the good wil of <hi>Ariadne</hi> but beautie? what wonne <hi>Demophoon</hi> the loue of <hi>Phillis</hi> but beautie? and what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Syluein Nimph <hi>Oenone</hi> to leaue the lawnes but the incomparable beautie of <hi>Paris?</hi> The Gentlewoman which hath a huſband that is endued with beautie &amp; ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the giftes of Nature, ſhall haue euer wherewith to be ſatiſfied, and neuer whereof to miſlike: wheras con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie the deformed man is ſuch a monſter in nature, and ſuche a ſorrowe to a womans heart, as ſhe bewailes her chaunce to haue choſen one that euery one doth loath. The fouleſt Serpent is euer moſt venimous, the trée with a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered rinde hath neuer a ſugred ſap, the durty puddle hath neuer good fiſh, and a deformed bodie ſeldome a reformed mind. The wiſe <hi>Lapidaries</hi> ſay that the pretious ſtone with the moſt gliſtring hue hath alwaies the moſt ſecret vertue. The pure gold is choſe by the perfect colour, the beſt frute,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:52"/> by the braueſt bloſſomes, and the beſt conditions by the ſwéeteſt countenance. But perhaps miſtreſſe <hi>Syluia</hi> you will ſay his faire face inflameth my fancie and his beautie bewitched my ſences, his ſhape in déede doeth perſwade me to requite his good will with mutuall affection, but then his folly againe quaileth my ſtomacke and is a cooling card to quench the fire of fancie, to which I anſwer <hi>Syluia,</hi> that his follie is not ſo preiudiciall as profitable, not ſo much hurtfull as commodious. <hi>Aſpaſia</hi> the louer of <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> being demanded what thing a woman in the worlde chiefly deſired, anſwered to rule, thinking that ſoueraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was the thing that women moſt deſire, and men moſt feare to grant them. If then it be a womans wiſh to haue her owne will, and as the common prouerbe ſaith, to rule the roſt after her owne diet, you ſhall in taking my maſter to your mate, haue ſo much your hearts eaſe as either you can deſire or imagine. For my maiſter will whollie be led by your lyne, and you ſhalbe the ſtarre, by whoſe aſpect hée will direct his courſe, your yea ſhalbe his yea, and your nay his deniall. Thus although his follie be preiudiciall in one reſpect, it ſhalbe moſt profitable in another, ſo that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable beautie ſhall ſufficiently delight your fancie, and his follie be a meanes that without reſtraint you may enioy frée will and libertie. Thus miſtreſſe <hi>Sylua,</hi> you haue heard what I in my maiſters behalfe can alledge. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you meane to repaie his good will with loue, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth not onely to make you ſole miſtreſſe of his heart, but of all his lands and lordſhips. <hi>Iacques</hi> hauing finiſhed this tale, maſter <hi>Petronius</hi> as one betwixt feare &amp; hope gaue the Fort the ſoreſt aſſault with this Alarme. <hi>Plato</hi> the wiſe and graue Philoſopher was wont to ſay, that as man diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from brute beaſts in reaſon, ſo one man excelleth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by wiſedome and learning: eſtéeming him that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted knowledge, ſcience, and nourture, but the ſhape of a man though neuer ſo wel beautified with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gifts of nature,
<pb facs="tcp:6147:53"/> ſuppoſing that although he were indewed with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhadow of beautie, as iuſtly he might compare with <hi>Paris:</hi> or ſo ſtored with treaſure and riches, as he might caſt his countes with <hi>Craeſus:</hi> yet if he wanted learning to enlarge his beautie, or wiſedome to direct his wealth, he was to be counted no other but a beautifull picture burni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with golde. He that enioyeth wealth without wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſayeth <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> poſſeſſeth care for himſelfe, enuie for his neighbours, ſpurres for his enimies, a praie for théeues, trauaile for his perſon, anguiſh for his ſpirite, a ſcruple for his conſcience, perill for his loue, ſorrow for his children, and a curſſe for his heires, becauſe although hée knowes how to gather, he wanteth ſkill to diſpoſe. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great made ſo great account of knowledge and wiſedome, that he was oft woont to ſay, he was more bound to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> for giuing him learning, than to his father <hi>Philip</hi> for his life, ſith the one was momentarie, and the other neuer to be blotted out with obliuion. <hi>Neſtor</hi> was more honoured and eſtéemed for his learning and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome at the ſiege of <hi>Troye,</hi> than either <hi>Achilles</hi> for his ſtrength, <hi>Aiax</hi> for his valour, or <hi>Agamemnon</hi> for his ſtout courage. <hi>Cyrces</hi> was not enamoured with the beautie of <hi>Vliſſes</hi> but intangled with his wiſedome. <hi>Aeneas</hi> when as <hi>Dido</hi> ſate in Parliament, tolde his tale with ſuch wit and diſcretion, ſo ſeaſoned with the ſalt of learning, and ſwéete ſap of ſcience, that not onely ſhe was ſnared in his loue, but alſo ſaide, ſurely thou art come of the offſpring of the Gods, alluding to this ſaying of <hi>Empedocles,</hi> that as we in nothing more differ from the Gods than when we are fooles, ſo in no thing we do come neare them ſo much as when we are wiſe. <hi>Socrates</hi> thanked the Gods onely for three things, firſt, that they made him a man and not a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that he was borne a <hi>Grecian</hi> and not a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> thirdly, that he was a Philoſopher and not vnlearned, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeming the gifts of nature and fortune of no value vnleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6147:53"/> they be beautified with the gifts of the mind. <hi>Byas</hi> the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher being reproued by a certain iniurious perſon that he was poore and ilfauoured, anſwered that he was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceiued both in his beautie and his riches, for quoth he, how can I be poore when I am wiſe, hard fauoured when I am learned, thinking it the chiefeſt beautie to be indued with learning, &amp; the greateſt treaſure to be enriched with wiſedome? The Philoſopher <hi>Critolaus</hi> being verie defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as hauing a crooked backe and verie poore as begging with a ſtaffe &amp; a wallet, was notwithſtanding ſo well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of a certaine Gentlewoman of great wealth and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull parentage, as ſhe would willingle haue accepted him for her huſband, which <hi>Critolaus</hi> perceiuing, laid down his ſtaffe and his wallet, and put off his cloake, the more to ſhew his crookt back, wiſhing her with more diligence to marke his deformed ſhoulders, to whom ſhe anſwered, O <hi>Critolaus,</hi> thy deformitie cannot quench that which thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and learning hath ſet on fire. It is learning in déede which allureth when euerie word ſhall haue his waight, when nothing ſhall procéede but either it ſhall ſauour of a ſharpe conceite or a ſecret concluſion. It is wiſedome that flouriſheth when beautie fadeth, that waxeth yoong when age approacheth, reſembling the ſea huluer leafe, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be dead ſtill continueth gréene. Beautie withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with age, and is impaired with ſickneſſe, be the face neuer ſo beautifull, the leaſt ſkarre or mole maketh it moſt deformed, but learning and knowledge by tract of time encreaſeth like to the Cygnets which being young are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie blacke, but in their age moſt perfectly white: like the birdes that build in the rockes of the Sea, whoſe feathers grow moſt gliſtering in their age. As for riches it is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie, ſubiect to the chance of inconſtant fortune, it may be conſumed with fire, ſpent with follie, waſted with riot, and ſtolne away by théeues: but wiſedome is a treaſure ſo certaine as no miſhap can diminiſh, neither be impaired by
<pb facs="tcp:6147:54"/> any ſiniſter frowne of fortune. <hi>Artemiſia</hi> the Quéene being demanded by a certain gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what choice ſhe ſhuld vſe in loue, marrie, quoth ſhe, imitate the good Lapidaries, who meaſure not the value of the ſtone by the outwarde hue, but by the ſecret vertue: ſo chooſe not a huſband for the ſhape of the bodie, but for the qualities of his minde, not for his outward perfectneſſe, but for his inward perfection. For if thou like one that hath nothing but a little beautie, thou ſhalt ſéeme to be in loue with the counterfeit of <hi>Gani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes,</hi> and if thou fancie onely riches, thou chooſeſt a wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den picture with a golden coate. Learning is the Iemme which ſo decketh a man, and wiſedome the Iewel which ſo adorneth the minde, that ſhe which chooſeth a wiſe man to her mate, though neuer ſo poore, ſaith <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a good match. Thus miſtreſſe <hi>Syluia</hi> you haue heard my opinion, though not ſo wiſely as I would, yet as lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly as I could, not daring to be too bold, leſt in wading too farre in an vnknowne foord I ſodeinly ſlip ouer my ſhooes. Lands I haue none, to offer you large feoffements, nor li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings to aſſigne you a great dowrie: but if it pleaſe you to accept of a poore gentleman, I ſhall be bound by det &amp; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be yours for euer. <hi>Syluia</hi> hauing giuen attentiue héed to theſe thrée gentlemen, as one of a verie quicke wit and ſharpe conceit, returned them theſe anſweres. <hi>Signor Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſſo,</hi> quoth ſhe, it was a law among the <hi>Caſpians,</hi> that he which married after he had paſſed fiftie yéeres ſhould at the common aſſemblies and feaſtes ſit in the loweſt and vileſt place as one that had committed a fact repugnant to the law of Nature, calling him which was well ſtrooken in yeeres, &amp; yet enamoured, that would frie in affection when he was wholie frozen in complexion, not an old louer, but a filthie foole, and a doting old leacher, and in my iudgement they had great reaſon ſo to tearme him. For olde rotten ſtrawes, are more fit for doong than for the chamber, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered flowers to be caſt away, than to be placed in a braue
<pb facs="tcp:6147:54"/> noſegay, olde ſtickes more méete for the fire than for ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous building, and aged men are more fit for the graue than to ſpende their time in loue. <hi>Cupid, Signor Gradaſſo,</hi> alloweth none in his court but yoong men that can ſerue, freſh and beautifull to delight, wiſe that can talke, ſecret to kéepe ſilence, faithfull to gratifie, and valiant to reuenge his miſtreſſe iniuries. He that is not indued &amp; priuiledged with theſe conditions, may well loue but neuer be liked. How can a yoong woman fixe her affection vppon an olde man, who in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night time in ſtéed of talke telleth the clock, crieth out of the gout, complaineth of the Ciatica, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with crampes, and troubled with the cough, hauing neither health to ioy himſelfe, nor youth to enioy her. To the ende that loue be fixed ſure, perpetuall and true, there muſt be equalitie betwéen the enamoured. For if the louer be olde and ſhée be yoong, he ouergrowne with age, and ſhe in flouriſhing youth, aſſure your ſelfe that of fained louers they ſhalbe euer profeſſed and vnfained enemies. For it is not loue but ſorrow, not mirth but diſpleaſure, not taſte but torment, not delight but deſpight, not ioy but annoy, not recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but confuſion, when in the louer there is not both youth and libertie: yea, &amp; the withered ſtraw is ſoone ſet on fire and eaſily quenched, the olde and drie wood eaſily inflamed and quickly put out, age ſoone doteth and ſoone de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth, now ſwimming in loue and preſently ſinking in hate like to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone <hi>Draconites,</hi> that no ſooner commeth out of the flame but it is vehemently cold. What a fooliſh moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nay what a frantike madneſſe is it for him whom na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture denieth any longer to liue to intangle himſelfe in the ſnares of loue whoſe naturall heate is turned to froſt, with the match of fancie to kindle a new fire when ſickneſſe ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons him and age warnes him that death draweth nye, than to become a clyent vnto <hi>Cupid,</hi> to pleade for bountie at the cruell barre of beautie, knowing that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearbe <hi>Adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> cannot abide to touch the withered graſſe, that the trées
<pb facs="tcp:6147:55"/> in the mount <hi>Verneſe</hi> deteſt to be claſped of the olde Iuie, and that youth greatly abhorreth to be coupled with age. Further whoſoeuer being yoong, faire and beautifull, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth her with a doting old louer be ſhe as chaſte as <hi>Lucre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> as truſtie as <hi>Penelope,</hi> as honeſt as <hi>Turia,</hi> as faithfull as <hi>Artemiſia,</hi> as conſtant as <hi>Cornelia,</hi> yet her honor, hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and good name ſhall not onely be ſuſpended but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſpected: yea, in ſo much that the olde man himſelfe to kéepe his doting wits warme, will couer his head with a ielous cap, being very credulous to beléeue ech flying tale, and ſuſpicious euermore to iudge the woorſt. If his young wife be merie ſhe is immodeſt, if ſober, ſullen, and thinkes of ſome louer whom ſhe likes beſt, if pleaſant inconſtant, if ſhe laugh it is leaudly, if ſhe looke it is lightly: yea, he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth beyond the Moone, &amp; iudgeth that which neither ſhe would nor could imagine, reſtraining her from all libertie &amp; watching as the craftie Cat ouer the ſillie Mouſe, ſhould I than <hi>Gradaſſo</hi> ſeeing the trap follow the train, ſpying the hooke, ſwallow the baite, and ſéeing the miſchiefe, runne wholie into miſerie? No, no, I meane not to be ſo fooliſh as the birdes of <hi>Cholchos,</hi> which although they ſée the nettes, yet willingly ſtrike at the ſtale, or like the <hi>Tortuſe</hi> which deſireth the heat of the Sunne that notwithſtanding brée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his deſtruction, nor ſo ſottiſh as with frée conſent to croſſe my ſelfe with perpetuall calamitie. Sith then <hi>Signor Gradaſſo</hi> I count you being ſo olde, not a fit match for my tender youth, I pray you at this time be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to take my nay for an anſwere. And as for you <hi>Iacques</hi> which haue ſaid ſo well in your maſters behalf, I commend you for a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruant, though your reaſons were to ſmall effect. I confeſſe <hi>Iacques,</hi> that nothing ſooner delighteth the eye, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenteth the ſenſe, or allureth the minde of a young maide than beautie: but as the ſtone <hi>Topaſon</hi> is not more loued for the outward hue than hated for the poiſon which ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is hid within it, or as the hearbe <hi>Nepenthes</hi> is not more
<pb facs="tcp:6147:55"/> liked for the pleaſant ſhape, than loathed for the poyſoned ſap: ſo beautie cannot inflame the fancie ſo much in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, as ridiculous follie can quench in a moment: nay, as of all things wit ſooneſt ſetteth the fancie on edge &amp; ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth affection, ſo follie cooleth deſire, and forceth loue in the lowdeſt gale to ſtrike ſaile and be quiet. What ioy can that Gentlewoman haue, whoſe huſband hath neither modeſtie to moderate his affection, nor manner to be haue himſelfe well in companie, who can neither be conſtant becauſe hée is a foole, nor ſecret ſith he is without ſence, but as the <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> hath nothing to couer his deformitie but a few gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſcales, or as the clowniſh Poet <hi>Cherillus</hi> had nothing to be praiſed in his verſes but the name of <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſo he hath nothing to ſhadow his follie but a faire face, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be commended but a litle fading beautie. Wheras you alledge that <hi>Venus</hi> was intangled with the beautie of <hi>Anchiſes,</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> with the feature of <hi>Endymion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dido</hi> with the braue ſhape of <hi>Aeneas.</hi> I anſwere, that <hi>Anchiſes</hi> was neither a foole, <hi>Endymion</hi> a ſot, nor <hi>Aeneas</hi> witleſſe: for if they had, they might aſſoone haue perſwaded olde <hi>Sylenus</hi> to deſpiſe the rytes of god <hi>Bacchus</hi> as haue procured any of theſe thrée to yéeld to their allureme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: ſith they knew that beautie in a foole is as a ring of gold in a ſwines ſnout. We read that a Conſull in <hi>Rome</hi> married a daughter of his to a faire foole, becauſe he was endued with great poſſeſſions, who was not long married to his wife <hi>Iulia,</hi> for ſo was the Conſuls daughter called, but for want of wit and lacke of wiſedome, he ſo burned in ielouſie and ſurged in the ſeas of ſuſpicious follie, that as the poore Gentlewoman was ſtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to pull on her ſhooe, he eſpying her faire and chriſtall necke, entred into ſuch a ſuſpicious furie, that preſently he thruſt her through with his ſword, verifying the ſaying of <hi>Caſtymachus,</hi> that a foole depriued of reaſon is no other but a mad man bereaued of his ſence. Whereas you ſay that ſoueraintie and rule is the chiefeſt thing a woman doth
<pb facs="tcp:6147:56"/> deſire, and that by marrying a foole I ſhall haue the readie meanes to attaine it, put caſe I graunt the antecedent, yet I deny the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent, for if I were as gréedy to beare ſway as <hi>Semiramis</hi> that craued of her huſband <hi>Nynus</hi> to rule the kingdome thrée daies, or as <hi>Cleopatra</hi> that coueted only to be maiſter of <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> yet a foole is ſo obſtinate in his ſenſleſſe opinion, and ſo peruerſe to be perſuaded, that he will not only denie me the ſuperioritie, but he wil himſelfe rule the roſt though it be to his vtter ruine. So that <hi>Iaques</hi> I conclude that your maiſter being ſomwhat fooliſh, and I my ſelfe none of the wiſeſt, it were no good match: for two fooles in one bed are too many. But now maiſter <hi>Petronius</hi> no longer to féed you with hope I giue you this <hi>A dio,</hi> that although I confeſſe wiſedome to be the moſt pretious iem wherewith the mind may be adorned, and learning one of the moſt famous qualities, wherefore a man may be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet if you were as wiſe as <hi>Salomon,</hi> as learned as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> as ſkilfull as <hi>Plato,</hi> as ſenſible as <hi>Socrates,</hi> as elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent as <hi>Vliſſes, Si nihil attuleris ibis Homere foras,</hi> for wit doth not more frie than want can frize, nor wiſedome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not ſo ſore as pouertie cooleth, &amp; rather had I in welth content my ſelfe with folly, than wedding myſelf to a poore wiſe man pine in pouertie. But ſith I hope <hi>Petronius</hi> thou wilt proue like the ſtone <hi>Sandaſtra</hi> which outwardlie is rough, but inwardly full of gliſtring beames, and that thou wilt trie thy ſelfe ſo good a huſband as thy vow, learning, and wiſedome promiſeth, I will not only ſupply thy want with my wealth, and thy pouertie with my plentie, but I will repaie thy fancie with affection, and thy loue with loi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, hoping that although my friends wil count me a foole for making my choice, yet I my ſelfe ſhall neuer haue cauſe to repent my chance, &amp; in pledge of this my plighted troth, haue here my heart and hand for euer at thy commaund. How <hi>Gradaſſo</hi> and <hi>Monſieur de Vaſte</hi> liked of this verdit I néede not relate, nor what their anſweres were I know
<pb facs="tcp:6147:56"/> not, and if I knew to recount them it auaileth not, but I am ſure <hi>Petronius</hi> thought he had made a fortunate iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Well <hi>Signor Valaſco</hi> hearing the determination of his daughter, was as well contented with the chaunce as ſhe ſatiſfied with the choice, and euer after made as great account of his ſonne in law <hi>Petronius,</hi> and liked as well of the match as though ſhe had married the richeſt Duke in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Madam <hi>Modeſta,</hi> I haue recounted this hiſtorie that your doubtfull queſtion might be throughly debated &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie decided. You ſée that <hi>Siluia</hi> who was wiſe, faire, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, would not be allured with the golden ſhew of riches becauſe ſhe loathed the perſon, nor be inchaunted with the charme of beautie ſith ſhe deteſted his folly, but chooſe poore <hi>Petronius</hi> who might both comfort and counſell her with his wiſedome, and be her credite and countenance for his learning. If then your louer be both faire and wiſe though without wealth, why ſhould you miſlike your choice ſith you are able to applie to his ſore the like ſalue with <hi>Syluia,</hi> and of a poore ſcholler make him a wealthie Gentleman. Chooſe not <hi>Modeſta</hi> ſo that thy friends ſhall like the choice and thou miſlike the chaunce, leaſt time and triall make thée account Rue a moſt bitter hearbe: thus wiſhing thy loue proſperous ſucceſſe howſoeuer the matter happen, I bid thée hartily farewell.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thine to her power contented Mamillia.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON Printed by Th. C. for William Ponſonbie. 1593.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
